. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE FEBRUARY 10TH 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER
PRESENTS SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WANG WONG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGED THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAHMATULLAH LONEY WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE PROMOTER SHALL ONLY HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMAKRISHNA LUNA COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I'D LIKE
TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY THAT'S
PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU WANT TO
TAKE US TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER?
>> YES. THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS
THE APPEARANCE BY THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE.
THERE BEING NO QUESTIONS SUBMITTED FROM ELIGIBLE MEMBERS
THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> WELCOME MR. MAYOR. >> THANK YOU.
GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD PRESIDENT MALCOLM
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. THIS MORNING I VISITED YOUTH
FIRST IN INGLESIDE, A CITY FUNDED ORGANIZATION THAT IS
HELPING TO TAKE CARE OF 65 PUBLIC SCHOOL SCHOOL STUDENTS
TODAY WHILE SCHOOLS ARE CLOSED. YESTERDAY THE CITY SERVED
THOUSANDS OF MEALS TO STUDENTS IN OUR COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATION AND CARED FOR THOUSANDS OF KIDS.
I VISITED SITES IN THE MISSION THE TENDERLOIN AND THE OUTER
SUNSET. THE STAFF AT THESE
ORGANIZATIONS AND OUR CITY EMPLOYEES HAVE REALLY STEPPED
UP AND I'M GRATEFUL TO ALL OF THEM.
AS THE SCHOOL DISTRICT AND UNION CONTINUE NEGOTIATING,
WE ARE CONTINUING TO PROVIDE SUPPORT TO FAMILIES TODAY
AND MONITORING CONSTANTLY TO PREPARE MOVING FORWARD.
I AM GLAD THAT BOTH SIDES ARE AT THE TABLE TODAY AS THEY WERE
YESTERDAY. I WILL SAY HERE WHAT I HAVE
SAID TO BOTH SIDES DAY AFTER DAY.
LET OUR KIDS GET BACK TO SCHOOL WHERE THEY BELONG.
OUR KIDS DESERVE SCHOOLS WHERE THEY CAN THRIVE AND THEIR
EDUCATORS FEEL TRULY SUPPORTED .
I FIRMLY BELIEVE THAT IF BOTH SIDES STAY AT THE TABLE THEY
CAN COME TO AN AGREEMENT. I'VE ENCOURAGED THEM TO DO THAT
AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE SO WE CAN GET SCHOOLS BACK OPEN
AND KIDS BACK IN THE CLASSROOM. NOW ON ANOTHER TOPIC THIS PAST
WEEK SAN FRANCISCO HOSTED NEARLY 300 EVENTS ACROSS THE
CITY THE PRO BOWL AND MOSCONE CENTER CONCERTS AT BILL GRAHAM
AND PIER 80 COMMUNITY ACTIVATIONS LIKE NFL PLAY 60,
THE FERRY BUILDING LATE SHOW AND MORE TO CELEBRATE SUPER
BOWL WEEK. >> WE WELCOMED VISITORS FROM
AROUND THE WORLD WITH AN ESTIMATED $440 MILLION
IN ECONOMIC IMPACT TO OUR CITY FROM JUST TUESDAY THROUGH
MONDAY. SFO SAW ROUGHLY 800,000
ARRIVALS AND DEPARTURES. AS I TRAVELED ACROSS THE CITY.
I HEARD FROM VISITORS, MEDIA AND LOCAL ALIKE.
SAN FRANCISCO WAS SHINING. NONE OF THIS WOULD HAVE BEEN
POSSIBLE WITHOUT OUR CITY WORKERS OUR PUBLIC SAFETY TEAMS
AT SPEED THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE, PARK RANGERS, THE DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT, FIRE DEPARTMENT, EMTS AND PARAMEDICS
WERE DEPLOYED ACROSS THE CITY TO KEEP RESIDENTS AND VISITORS
SAFE. S.F. MTA MUNI OPERATORS PARKING
CONTROL OFFICER AND FRONTLINE STAFF KEPT OUR TRANSPORTATION
SYSTEM SAFE AND RELIABLE. ON AVERAGE THIS IS A WHILE STAT
WE CARRIED 17,000 MORE PASSENGERS PER DAY THAN THE
PREVIOUS WEEK TOTALING 2.7 MILLION TRIPS DURING THE
WEEKDAYS. I WANT TO THANK AS WELL PUBLIC
WORKS AND REC AND PARK FOR SUPPORTING OPERATIONS CITYWIDE
. WE ALSO HAD SUPPORT FROM
REGIONAL AND STATE PARTNERS. I WANT TO THANK THE GOVERNOR
FOR ADDITIONAL SUPPORT FROM CALIFORNIA HIGHWAY PATROL AS
WELL AS BART POLICE AND CALTRANS WHO HELP MAINTAIN
TRANSIT AND ROADWAY SAFETY THROUGHOUT THE REGION.
SAN FRANCISCO SHOWED WHAT WE CAN DO WHEN WE WORK TOGETHER.
THANK YOU TO EVERY CITY WORKER AND PARTNER WHO HELPED MAKE
THIS SUCCESSFUL AND HELPED MAKE IT A PROUD WEEKEND FOR SAN
FRANCISCO. AND I WANT TO THANK ALSO ALL OF
THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR YOUR CONSTANT
SUPPORT OF THAT EVENT. AND IT WAS ONE THAT WILL LONG
BE REMEMBERED SO THAT IS THAT IS ALL.
I APPRECIATE THAT OPPORTUNITY. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR WEEK OR ALL OF YOUR WORK OVER SUPER
BOWL WEEKEND BOTH ON ON THE SUPER BOWL ITSELF AND ON TRYING
TO BRING RESOLUTION TO THE SCHOOL DISTRICT SITUATION.
>> AND WITH THAT THIS MATTER HAS BEEN DISCUSSED AND IS NOW
FILED. >> THANK YOU, SIR.
WE HEAR FROM THE CITY. >> YOU'RE OUT OF ORDER.
OKAY. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO BACK
TO COMMUNICATIONS. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR
ATTENDANCE HERE IN PERSON IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE
CHAMBER. ROOM TWO 52ND FLOOR OF CITY
HALL. WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE, THE PROCEEDING IS AIRING LIVE ON S.F. GOVEE TV'S CHANNEL
26 OR YOU CAN WATCH THE LIVE STREAM ON THE GO AT W W W DOT
AS F G OR VTV.ORG. IF YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR
PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU CAN SEND AN EMAIL TO B OS AT
S F GOV DAWG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE.
>> JUST ADDRESS YOUR ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102
IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A
FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT
OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S
OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU.
MEMBERS MR. PRESIDENT THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES.
YES, APPROVAL OF THE JANUARY 20TH JANUARY 6TH, 2026 BOARD
MEETING MINUTES UH UH, COLLEAGUES, CAN I HAVE A MOTION
TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN
AND SECONDED BY MELGAR. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED SUPERVISOR WONG WONG
EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN I MANDEL
MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE
APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS ITEM NUMBER ONE ITEM ONE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE TO
REVISE HOW THE AULT OR THE ACCESS LINE TAX APPLIES TO THE
VOIP. THE VOICE OVER INTERNET
PROTOCOL SERVICES TO REQUIRE COLLECTION AND REMITTANCE OF
THE ALT ON VOIP SERVICES USING THE LOWER OF THE NUMBER OF
TELEPHONE NUMBERS PROVIDED TO A SUBSCRIBER AND THE NUMBER OF
CALLS THAT THE SUBSCRIBER CAN MAKE AND OR RECEIVE AT THE SAME
TIME USING THOSE TELEPHONE NUMBERS PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEM ONE SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM TWO ITEM TWO THIS ORDINANCE ACCEPT AN
EXPENSE A $7 MILLION GRANT FROM BLUE BLOOMBERG PHILANTHROPIES
AND TO FUND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF INNOVATION JANUARY 1ST, 2026
THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2028 TO APPROVE THE ASSOCIATED GRANT
AGREEMENT AND TO AMEND THE ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE
CONTAINED IN FILE NUMBER 25 0590 FOR FISCAL YEARS 20 2526
AND 20 2627 TO PROVIDE FOR THE CREATION OF FOUR GRANT FUNDED
FULL TIME POSITIONS IN THE OFFICE OF THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR AND I BELIEVE WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM THREE.
ITEM THREE THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO
PERMIT PARKING OF UP TO TWO OPERABLE VEHICLES NOT INCLUDING
BOATS, TRAILERS, RECREATIONAL VEHICLES, MOBILE HOMES OR
BUSSES IN DRIVEWAYS LOCATED IN REQUIRED FRONT SETBACK SIDE
YARDS OR REAR YARDS TO AFFIRM THE SECRETARY TERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM FOR ITEM FOR THIS ORDINANCE
AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO MAKE VARIOUS CLARIFYING
AND TYPOGRAPHICAL CHANGES TO PROHIBIT MASSAGE ESTABLISHMENTS
AND MASSAGE SOLD PRACTITIONER USES AS ACCESSORY USES TO
RESIDENTIAL USES TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL ITEMS FIVE AND SIX TOGETHER.
>> YES. ITEM FIVE IS AN ORDINANCE THAT
AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO ADD A NEW APPENDIX P TO ARTICLE TEN
PRESERVATION OF HISTORICAL ARCHITECTURAL AND ESTHETIC
LANDMARKS TO CREATE THE CHULA ABBEY EARLY RESIDENTIAL
HISTORIC DISTRICT. AND ITEM SIX THIS ORDINANCE
AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO ADD A NEW APPENDIX Q TO ARTICLE TEN
PRESERVATION OF HISTORICAL ARCHITECTURAL AND ESTHETIC
LANDMARKS TO CREATE THE ALERT ALLEY EARLY RESIDENTIAL
HISTORIC DISTRICT AND FOR BOTH ITEMS TO AFFIRM THE SECOND
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN THIS
ORDINANCE AMENDS THE POLICE CODE TO EXPAND THE CURRENT
TENDERLOIN RETAIL HOURS RESTRICTION PILOT PROGRAM UNDER
WHICH RETAIL FOOD AND TOBACCO ESTABLISHMENTS IN THE
RESTRICTED AREA ARE PROHIBITED FROM BEING OPEN TO THE PUBLIC
FROM 12 A.M. TO 5 A.M. OR FROM 2 A.M. TO 5 A.M. IF SUBJECT TO
REGULATION BY THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC
BEVERAGE CONTROL TO ENCOMPASS HIGH CRIME AREA ACROSS THE
TENDERLOIN AND SOUTH OF MARKET NEIGHBORHOODS AND TO EXTEND THE
DURATION OF THE PILOT PROGRAM CURRENTLY SET TO EXPIRE JULY
2026 TO INSTEAD EXPIRE 18 MONTHS FROM THE EFFECTIVE DATE
OF THE ORDINANCE. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM
SEVEN SUPERVISOR WANG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON KNOW THERE ARE NINE EYES
AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER AND WALTON VOTING NO
THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW
BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM EIGHT ITEM EIGHT ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE POLICE CODE TO REVISE THE PROCEDURES FOR ALARM COMPANIES
AND ALARM USERS TO CLAIM REFUNDS OR CREDITS OF OVERPAID
ALARM FEES UNDER THE POLICE EMERGENCY ALARM ORDINANCE
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM EIGHT SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I ADELMAN
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NINE
ITEM NINE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO DO APPROPRIATE 250,000 FROM
GENERAL CITY RESPONSIBILITY AND TO APPROPRIATE 250,000 TO
THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN YOUTH AND THEIR FAMILIES TO
SUPPORT THE DISTRICT TEN SAFETY PLAN TO INCLUDE SERVICES AT THE
HOPE SAFE SITES VIOLENCE PREVENTION EVENTS, SAFE
PASSAGES, RESPONSE TO SCHOOLS AND AS NEEDED SUPPORT TO THE
YOUTH AND RESIDENTS MOST IMPACTED BY VIOLENCE IN FISCAL
YEAR 2025 2026. >> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER TEN. >> ITEM TEN THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE TERMS AND CONDITIONS AND TO AUTHORIZE
THE GENERAL MANAGER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES
COMMISSION AND OR THE CITY'S DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO EXECUTE
CERTAIN AGREEMENTS WITH THE CITY OF DALY CITY FOR SALE OF
EASEMENTS FOR STORMWATER FACILITIES AT LAKE MARE SAID
AND LICENSE AGREEMENTS AND A PURCHASE AND SALE AGREEMENT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
11. >> ITEM 11 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO AUTHORIZE THE TAX COLLECTOR TO SELL CERTAIN PARCELS OF TAX
DEFAULTED REAL PROPERTY AT PUBLIC AUCTION AND SEALED BID
AUCTION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 12.
ITEM 12 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE
CITY AND COUNTY ACTING THROUGH THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE TO ENTER
INTO A PROFESSIONAL SERVICES CONTRACT WITH CONNECTIONS S.A.
LLC FOR OPERATING THE RAPID ENFORCEMENT SUPPORT EVALUATION
AND TRIAGE CENTER A SAFE ALTERNATIVE TO INCARCERATION
FOR INDIVIDUALS BROUGHT IN BY LAW ENFORCEMENT FOR PUBLIC
INTOXICATION OR DRUG USE SUBMITTED AS A CORE INITIATIVE
CONTRACT FOR A TOTAL NOT TO EXCEED AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY
14.5 MILLION WITH AN INITIAL TERM OF TWO YEARS AND TWO
MONTHS TO COMMENCE ON FEBRUARY 1ST, 2026 THROUGH MARCH 31ST
2028 WITH AN ADDITIONAL OPTION TO EXTEND FOR ONE YEAR.
>> SUPERVISE FIELDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, I HAVE A
QUESTION FOR THE BALLET. >> HOW CAN YOU EXPLAIN THE PART
IN THE FISCAL IMPACT ANALYSIS IN THE BLAZE REPORT IN FISCAL
YEAR 2526 THE CONTRACT IS FUNDED BY GENERAL FUND WORK
ORDER FROM PAGE THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE SHERIFF SERVICE OFFICERS
IS REQUESTING FUNDING FOR THE CONTRACT IN SUBSEQUENT YEARS.
>> HOWEVER, AT LEAST 3.1 MILLION IN CONTRACT COSTS ARE
NOT BUDGETED IN FISCAL YEAR 2627.
>> SO WHERE WHERE IS THIS FUNDING COMING FROM?
NICK MENARD FROM THE BUDGET LEGISLATIVE ANALYST'S OFFICE.
SO WE DON'T KNOW IT WILL PROBABLY BE THE GENERAL FUND.
>> SO THE SHERIFF IS GOING TO REQUEST THE FULL COST OF THE
CONTRACT NEXT YEAR IN THEIR BUDGET OF $6.3 MILLION.
THERE'S $3.1 MILLION IN HIS BUDGET NEXT YEAR THAT COULD
PROBABLY OFFSET AT LEAST A PART OF THAT.
BUT THE REMAINING COST WOULD NEED TO BE OUR NEW GENERAL FUND
COST THAT WILL NEED TO BE FUNDED IN THE UPCOMING BUDGET.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES, I FIRST OFF I HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT THIS CONTRACT AS
I UNDERSTAND THE RESET CENTER MAY OR MAY NOT BE SUBJECT TO
STATE STANDARDS AROUND THESE KINDS OF FACILITIES AND WE
DON'T ACTUALLY KNOW THE ANSWER TO THAT AT THE MOMENT.
SECONDLY, AT A TIME WHEN PAIGE IS MAKING $17 MILLION
IN PAINFUL BUDGET CUTS TO PROGRAMS IN THE COMMUNITY THAT
SERVE SOME OF THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE LIKE HEALTHY
STEPS AT THE CHILDREN'S HEALTH CENTER ORGANIZATIONS THAT SERVE
TRANS AND ELDERLY COMMUNITIES, COMMUNITIES OF COLOR.
THIS AGREEMENT WOULD TRANSFER AROUND 3 MILLION A YEAR IT
SOUNDS LIKE FROM TO THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT FOR
COMPLETING THE COMPLETELY NEW PROGRAM RUN BY OUT OF STATE
PROVIDERS. AND SO I WILL NOT BE SUPPORTING
SPENDING THE CITY FUNDS FOR NEW SHERIFF FACILITIES THAT COME AT
THE EXPENSE OF COMMUNITY HEALTH PROGRAMS.
>> CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT YOU KNOW
FIRST AND FOREMOST DURING BUDGET COMMITTEE TIME WE HAVE
THIS DISCUSSION ABOUT THE FUNDING.
I THINK WE INTENDED TO AT THAT TIME WAS TO PUT THE DOLLAR ON
RESERVE OR I SHOULD SAY ACTUALLY ONLY RELEASE FOR
CERTAIN DOLLAR AMOUNT AND THEN WE WANT TO WITHHOLD THE
REMAINING OF THE CONTRACT. BUT ACCORDING TO CITY ATTORNEY
WE COULDN'T DO THAT BECAUSE THEN IT WILL BE DONE.
THE BOARD AMENDING THE SPECIFIC CONTRACT TERM AND WHAT WE HAVE
END UP SETTLING IS THAT WE KNOW THAT IT'S NOT A FULLY FUNDED
CONTRACT AND WILL COME TO THE BOARD OR I SHOULD SAY THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE DURING THE BUDGET PROCESS AT WHICH TIME IT
WAS WE HAD ARTICULATED THAT IT WAS OUR INTENTION TO WITHHOLD
OR TO PUT THE FUNDING REMAINING OF THE CONTRACT FUNDING FOR THE
REMAINING CONTRACT ON RESERVE UNTIL WE UNDERSTAND WHAT THE
CENTER LIKE WHAT'S THE PILOT DETAIL?
MORE DETAILS HOWEVER THAT I HAVE READ NOW RECEIVE
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION NOT I DID NOT HAVE DURING THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE AND THE ADDITIONAL INFORMATION THAT I RECEIVE.
I FIND IT TROUBLESOME AND PROBLEMATIC AND ABOUT JUST
THE MODEL OF THE CENTER TERM AND I JUST THINK THAT THIS IS
THIS IS PROBLEMATIC. I THINK THAT THIS THIS
INFORMATION SHOULD REALLY SHOULD HAVE BEEN PROVIDED TO
THE BUDGET COMMITTEE PRIOR TO IT GOING THROUGH THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE. SO I ALSO SEE THAT MY SHIRT
SUPERVISOR DORSI IS ON THE DOCKET AND I, I WANTED TO KIND
OF OPEN UP THE CONVERSATION ABOUT THE ADDITIONAL
INFORMATION THAT THIS BODY AND ARE RECEIVING BEFORE THAT
BEFORE THE BUDGET COMMITTEE. IT'S REALLY NOT TRADITIONALLY
WHAT WE WOULD HAVE LIKE THESE ACTUALLY THESE INFORMATION WE
SHOULD ACTUALLY HAVE BEFORE COMING TO THE FULL BOARD
AND ALLOW SOME DISCUSSION. >> BUT SO NOW I AM I'M JUST
CONCERNING ABOUT HOW THIS THIS WAS ALL COMING TOGETHER.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
SO AS I SAID IN THE COMMITTEE HEARING, THIS ITEM MATTERS A
LOT TO ME AND NOT SOLELY BECAUSE THE FACILITY IS IN MY
DISTRICT AND NOT SOLELY EVEN BECAUSE THIS IS AN ISSUE THAT'S
A PRIORITY TO ME AS A RECOVERING ADDICT MYSELF.
>> IT MATTERS BECAUSE IN MY VIEW THIS IS THE SINGLE MOST
IMPORTANT DRUG POLICY INNOVATION SAN FRANCISCO HAS
OFFERED SINCE THE ADVENT OF THE FENTANYL CRISIS.
I THINK THIS WILL WORK. I THINK IT IMPOSES A MUCH
NEEDED MEASURE OF ACCOUNTABILITY THAT HAS BEEN
TOO LONG MISSING IN OUR APPROACH TO PUBLIC DRUG USE
AND ITS MYRIAD RELATED HARMS. I THINK IT WILL HELP START TO
SHUT DOWN THE MAGNET SAN FRANCISCO HAS BECOME AS A
NATIONAL AND EVEN GLOBAL DESTINATION FOR DRUG RELATED
LAWLESSNESS AND I THINK IT WILL SAVE LIVES.
FOR TOO LONG WHEN OFFENDERS ARE ARRESTED FOR PUBLIC DRUG USE OR
INTOXICATION, OUR ONLY REAL OPTIONS HAVE BEEN JAIL OR AN
EMERGENCY ROOM BOTH OF WHICH TAKE POLICE OFFICERS OFF PATROL
FOR SEVERAL HOURS. NEITHER OPTION WORKS WELL.
BOTH OF US KEEP STUCK IN THE SAME CYCLE AND FRANKLY THIS
SAME CYCLE IS SOMETHING THAT WE CAN ILL AFFORD AND TODAY'S
FENTANYL ERA WITH A DRUG OVERDOSE CRISIS THAT IS STILL
SETTING RECORDS RESET IS AN INNOVATIVE APPROACH THAT WILL
IMPROVE EFFICIENCIES AND OUTCOMES SCALED UP.
I THINK THIS IS THE MODEL FOR HOW WE WILL FINALLY MAKE
PROGRESS TOWARD ENDING THE PHENOMENON OF PUBLIC DRUG USE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. IT IS AN INVOLUNTARY CUSTODIAL
INTERVENTION FOR PEOPLE ENGAGED IN ILLICIT DRUG DRUG USE
IN PUBLIC. IT WILL REDUCE FROM SEVERAL
HOURS TO 15 MINUTES THE AMOUNT OF TIME POLICE NEED TO MAKE AN
ARREST TO CONFISCATE USERS DRUGS AND PARAPHERNALIA TO GET
DRUG USE OFF THE STREET AND TO PUT DRUG USERS IN A SUPERVISED
AND COERCIVE SETTING TO HOPEFULLY MAKE BETTER CHOICES
OR TO FACE ESCALATING CONSEQUENCES THAT ARE
THEMSELVES FOUNDATIONAL ELEMENTS FOR MOST PEOPLE TO
HAVE SUCCESSFUL RECOVERY JOURNEYS.
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER THE CLINICAL TERM FOR DRUG
ADDICTION IS A MEDICAL CONDITION BUT IT FREQUENTLY
ALSO RESULTS IN CRIME AND NOT SOLELY THE CRIME OF USING
ILLICIT DRUGS IN PUBLIC. IT FUELS RETAIL THEFT STREET
DISORDER AND NO SMALL NUMBER OF EPISODES OF SERIOUS PROPERTY
AND VIOLENT CRIME. IT IS ALSO AMONG OUR LEADING
CAUSES OF PREVENTABLE DEATH. AND IF WE ARE SERIOUS ABOUT
SAVING LIVES, WE NEED BETTER, MORE CONSEQUENTIAL DEMAND SIDE
INTERVENTIONS LIKE THE RESET CENTER THAT GIVE THOSE WITH
ADDICTIONS A REAL CHANCE FOR RECOVERY AND THAT RECOGNIZE
ILLICIT DRUGS ARE A PUBLIC HEALTH AND A PUBLIC SAFETY
PROBLEM. I KNOW WE'VE HEARD FROM SOME
ADVOCATES WHO FEEL OUR CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM HAS NO ROLE TO
PLAY IN ADDRESSING PUBLIC DRUG USE AND I WOULD SAY THAT THEY
ARE FREE TO PETITION OUR STATE LEGISLATURE TO REPEAL OUR DRUG
LAWS. BUT UNTIL AND UNLESS THAT
HAPPENS, SAN FRANCISCANS HAVE A REASONABLE EXPECTATION TO SEE
THEIR STATE LAWS ENFORCED. WE OWE SAN FRANCISCANS NOTHING
LESS THAN TO TAKE EVERY STEP WE CAN TO MAKE OUR CITY A
DESTINATION FOR RECOVERY INSTEAD OF A DESTINATION FOR
DRUG RELATED LAWLESSNESS. THE RESEARCH CENTER ALONE WON'T
ACCOMPLISH THIS BUT I HAVE EVERY CONFIDENCE THAT IT
REFLECTS THE BOLD APPROACH OUR CITY NEEDS THAT WILL AND I HOPE
IT EARNS EVERYONE SUPPORT. LET'S GO TO SUPERVISOR SHERYL
AND WE CAN CIRCLE BACK TO FIELDER AND JAN.
>> I'D LIKE TO BE ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR TO THIS MEASURE.
>> IT'S TIME TO SAVE SOME LIVES.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
AND THANKS PRESIDENT MENEM AND I WANT TO SEE A SUCCESSFUL
RESET CENTER. THIS IS A HUGE NEED IN THE
MISSION FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE USING DRUGS IN PUBLIC TO BE
SOMEWHERE. AND I UNDERSTAND FROM FROM.
DPW AS A PD THIS IS A HUGE NEED AND WANT FOR A LONG TIME.
AND IF WE DON'T DO IT CORRECTLY THIS PRICE TAG IS GOING TO GO
WAY UP WAY, WAY WAY, WAY, WAY UP.
AND I'M CONCERNED THAT THERE'S GOING TO BE VERY FEW OUTCOMES
ACTUALLY SHOW THAT IT WAS WORTH IT.
>> IT'S NOT ABOUT AN EITHER OR HARM REDUCTION IN ENFORCING
DRUG LAWS. >> IT'S ACTUALLY NONE OF THAT.
IT IS ABOUT HAVING SOMEWHERE FOR PEOPLE TO GO.
BUT IF WE DON'T DO IT CORRECTLY, IF WE DON'T ABIDE BY
STATE STANDARDS WHEN WE'RE TALKING ABOUT COERCION WE HAVE
TO BE SO CAREFUL. >> AND I AM JUST NOT SURE THAT
IT IS WORTH THE COST OF ALSO CUTTING OFF OTHER PARTS OF OUR
CRITICAL CARE SYSTEM. >> AGAIN, LIKE COMMUNITY
PROGRAMS SERVING SOME OF THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE THAT
ALSO COULD BE OVERLAPPING WITH THIS POPULATION.
AND AGAIN I REMAIN VERY CONCERNED ABOUT DOING THIS
CORRECTLY AND AND I'LL LEAVE IT AT THAT.
>> CHAIR CHAM THANK YOU. I THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
MANDELMAN. I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, BECAUSE
OF THE ADDITIONAL INFORMATION THAT WE ALL RECEIVED I JUST
FIND THAT THE THAT IS MATERIAL. AND I THINK I WOULD HAVE A VERY
DIFFERENT PERSPECTIVE ABOUT THE RESEARCH CENTER.
LAST WEDNESDAY WHEN IT WAS DISCUSSED AND TEC UPON IN FACT
I THINK IF I HAD THAT INFORMATION EVEN BEFORE PUTTING
THAT ITEM ON AGENDA I THINK I WOULD HAVE VIEW IT VERY
DIFFERENTLY BECAUSE MY ASSUMPTION HAS BEEN THE FACT
THAT THERE'S A LOT OF ISSUES OPERATIONALLY WERE SOLVED.
AND I SHOULD SAY THAT I THOUGHT THAT IN ON MANY LEVELS THAT IS
SOLVED, VETTED AND WELL THOUGHT OUT.
BUT WITH THE ADDITIONAL INFORMATION I JUST THINK THAT
IT'S NOT AND THAT THERE ARE STILL CHALLENGES THAT WE
HAVEN'T COMPLETELY VET. >> AND AND AND THEN ALSO I
THINK I COULD AT LEAST LAST WEDNESDAY FELT THAT WHILE IS
NOT FULLY FUNDED BUT MAJORITY TWO THIRD OF THE FUNDING WAS
MADE AVAILABLE YOU KNOW MAYBE ROUGHLY A MORE TO A LITTLE BIT
MORE THAN $3 MILLION WAS IN FULL, YOU KNOW PROVIDED WE
COULD ACTUALLY HAVE THAT CONVERSATION IN THE SECOND YEAR
AND DURING THE BUDGET PROCESS AND POTENTIALLY RELEASE OUR
DOLLARS. AND THEN WITH FOLSOM AWAITING
FOR RESULTS OF THE CENTER BUT WHAT ADDITIONAL INFORMATION IT
WOULD MAKE ME DEEPLY QUESTIONS THE OPERATION MODEL.
AND IT'S IT'S LEGITIMATE. SO I WOULD THAT LIKE BECAUSE OF
THE NEW INFORMATION THAT WAS PROVIDED LITERALLY JUST A A DAY
AGO LESS THAN 24 HOURS I REGRETTABLE.
I MEAN I THINK THAT WE NEED AN INNOVATIVE INNOVATIVE APPROACH
TO WHAT WHAT WE ARE SEEING AS A PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS ON OUR
STREETS. BUT NOW I THINK I IT JUST THREW
IT THREW ME OFF AND THEN I HAVE A WHOLE SET OF NEW QUESTIONS
ABOUT THIS. SO REGRETTABLY I WILL BE NOT
SUPPORTING THIS SIMPLY BECAUSE THE INFORMATION THAT I RECEIVE
ON MONDAY. >> THANK YOU.
SURPRISE MELGAR. I JUST WANTED TO ASK A QUESTION
OF THE CHAIR OF THE BUDGET COMMITTEE BECAUSE USUALLY YOU
KNOW LIKE THOSE OF US WHO ARE NOT ON THE COMMITTEE RELY ON
THE COMMITTEE, YOU KNOW, DOING THE WORK AND IT COMES OUT WITH
A RECOMMENDATION OR NOT. >> AND SO DO YOU THINK THAT THE
OUTCOME AND THE RECOMMENDATION OF THE COMMITTEE WOULD HAVE
BEEN DIFFERENT IF YOU HAD HAD THIS INFORMATION LAST WEEK
AND THEN MY OTHER QUESTION WAS WOULD IT BE HELPFUL TO SEND
THIS BACK TO COMMITTEE RATHER THAN VOTING ON IT TODAY?
>> THANK YOU. I THINK THROUGH PRESENT
AMENDMENT I, I THINK WHAT I WOULD HAVE DONE PROBABLY IS
DURING THE PRESENTATION OF THIS CENTER I THINK I WOULD HAVE
PROBABLY DIVE DEEPER IN TRUTH TRUSTEE PROCESS AND REALLY THE
PROCESS ITSELF MEANING LET LET'S LET'S CALL IT WHAT IT IS
RIGHT RIGHT NOW THIS MODEL AS IT CURRENTLY IS IS THAT PEOPLE
WILL BE DETAINED IN THIS SPACE AND AND IT'S NOT VOLUNTARILY TO
BE DETAINED IN THIS FACILITY. MY EXPECTATION IS THAT WE WOULD
HAVE WORKED OUT MANY, MANY LEGALITY OF THAT OPERATIONS TO
ENSURE THAT WE CAN KEEP THIS OPERATION GOING.
>> BUT I THINK WITH THE NEW INFORMATION THAT CLEARLY EITHER
WE IGNORE THAT OR WE DIDN'T FIGURE OUT THE OPERATION MODEL
FIRST. >> MULDER, ARE YOU.
THE SECOND QUESTION IS WOULD IT BE HELPFUL TO SEND IT BACK TO
COMMITTEE OR I PERSONALLY WOULD THINK THAT I MEAN I THINK THAT
THIS IS A MOMENT WHERE LIKE YOU KNOW, I, I DON'T KNOW EVEN IF
YOU SENT BACK TO THE COMMITTEE THAT YOU WILL CHANGE THE
OPERATION MODEL I THINK LIKE YOU KNOW, I THINK THAT THIS IS
COLLECTIVELY WE ALL SHOULD DECIDE THAT.
>> I MEAN I WISH WE ARE HAVING A CLOSED SESSION RIGHT NOW.
YOU KNOW, LIKE LET ME ACTUALLY YOU KNOW WHAT CAN I I'M GOING
TO ANSWER THIS QUESTION. I THINK THAT THIS IS ONE OF
THOSE QUESTIONS THAT I WILL LOVE TO SEND IT BACK TO
COMMITTEE BUT THEN BUT ALSO ALLOW COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE
AND NOT I SHOULD SAY I WOULD LOVE TO SEND IT TO COMMITTEE OF
THE WHOLE AND THEN TO ALLOW A CLOSED SESSION FOR US TO HAVE
THIS TYPE OF DISCUSSION AND WE HAVE SIMILAR WE HAVE SIMILAR
IDEAS IN THE PAST FRANKLY IN A DIFFERENT KIND OF WAY LIKE SAFE
INJECTION SITE WE HAVE VERY SIMILAR IDEA IS FLOATING
AROUND. IN THE PAST WE DECIDED THAT
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A CLOSED SESSION AND DISCUSSION SO I AM
JUST GOING TO LEAVE IT LIKE THAT.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY SO I WOULD BE DISINCLINED TO SEND IT BACK
TO COMMITTEE OR TO HAVE A CLOSED SESSION ON IT.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT I WOULD JUST REMIND COLLEAGUES IS THIS
IS A IT IS A 25 BED FACILITY. THIS IS A PILOT PROGRAM AS AS
THINGS GO IN THE DRUG POLICY REALM, THIS IS SOMETHING THAT
WE ARE TRYING AND ONE OF THE THINGS THAT I THINK REALLY
DISTINGUISHES DRUG POLICY IN THE FENTANYL ERA THAT HAS
BEDEVILED A LOT OF THINGS IS WE NEED TO TRY DIFFERENT THINGS
AND A LOT OF THINGS THAT WORKED BACK IN THE GOOD OLD HEROIN
DAYS AREN'T WORKING IN THE FENTANYL ERA.
WE'RE NOT ALONE AMONG CITIES IN DEALING WITH THIS.
THIS IS AN APPROACH THAT I'M SATISFIED READING THE CITY
ATTORNEY ADVICE AND TALKING TO THE MAYOR IS GOING TO BE DOABLE
. I DON'T THINK THAT IT WOULD.
I THINK WE HAVE TIME BEFORE THIS OPENS TO HAMMER OUT ANY
ANY ISSUES THAT MAY COME UP BUT I DON'T THINK THAT THERE IS A
REASON NOT TO APPROVE THIS CONTRACT AS IT'S PRESENTED TO
US. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER I WOULD
JUST SAY RESPECTFULLY THAT IS OUR ROLE AT THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO IRON THIS OUT BEFORE IT'S APPROVED TO IRON
OUT THESE QUESTIONS AND I THINK WE'RE NEVER IT IS HERE OR BACK
AT COMMITTEE A CLOSED SESSION WOULD BE ABSOLUTELY APPROPRIATE
. UM I WAS GOING TO ASK FOR
PROCEDURE WISE AND RULE WISE WHAT I COULD DO TO MAKE THE
MOTION TO SEND IT BACK TO COMMITTEE BUT YOU JUST MADE A
MOTION. >> IS THERE A SECOND AVENUE
MOTION THAT OH, YOU KNOW, I THINK THAT AT SOME POINT YOU
COULD MAKE I'M SORRY. >> ARE YOU?
WELL, I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE TO SEND IT BACK TO COMMITTEE.
SO IS THERE A SECOND? SECOND IS ALL RIGHT.
SO THERE'S A MOTION FROM FIELDER TO SEND IT BACK TO
COMMITTEE. THERE IS A SECOND FROM CHAN.
UM, I BELIEVE THAT THE BOARD LIAISON WOULD LIKE TO BE
RECOGNIZED. MISTER TALKS ABOUT MR.
PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTIONS.
BOARD MEMBERS I'M GOING TO ACTUALLY ASK SHERIFF MIYAMOTO
IF HE AND UNDERSHERIFF JOHNSON IF THEY COULD COME UP TO THE
PODIUM AND HELP SHED A COUPLE MORE THOUGHTS ON MAYBE THE
QUESTIONS THAT THE SUPERVISOR CHAN HAS ON THIS.
>> THANK YOU. HI.
GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE. I APPRECIATE THE OPPORTUNITY TO
COME AND CLARIFY SOME THINGS. I HEAR THE DISCUSSION.
I UNDERSTAND WHAT SOME OF THE CONCERNS ARE.
I WANT TO PAINT A VERY SIMPLE PICTURE THOUGH OF WHAT WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT THIS CENTER IS DESIGNED AS AN ALTERNATIVE TO
BRING SOMEBODY TO JAIL FOR A HEALTH REASON BEING UNDER THE
INFLUENCE IN THE PUBLIC IS AN OFFENSE TO THE JAIL WHEN
INDIVIDUALS ARE ARRESTED AND DETAINED AND BROUGHT
IN UNDER THIS CIRCUMSTANCE HAS LIMITED CONDITIONS IN WHICH
THEY CAN ACCOMMODATE THE INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE COMING
IN THAT ARE INTOXICATED OR UNDER THE INFLUENCE.
THE HOLDING CELLS ARE JUST HOLDING CELLS.
THERE IS ACCESS TO MEDICAL CARE AND JAIL HEALTH SERVICES BUT IT
IS NOT TO A DEGREE THAT IS NURTURING OR THERAPEUTIC OR
CONSTANT CARE BECAUSE OUR JAIL HEALTH SERVICES STAFF DEAL WITH
THE ENTIRE THE ENTIRETY OF THE POPULATION IN THE JAIL.
THIS CENTER THE RESET IS DESIGNED TO BE AN ALTERNATIVE
LOCATION TO BRING AN INDIVIDUAL WHO IS BEING COMPELLED TO COME
WITH US BECAUSE OF THE PUBLIC OFFENSE TO A MORE THERAPEUTIC
ENVIRONMENT AND THE ABILITY TO HAVE THAT OPTION TO PLACE THEM
IN A RECLINING CHAIR TO PLACE THEM IN A PLACE WHERE THEY CAN
SOBER UP IN A SAFE ENVIRONMENT NOT ON THE FLOOR OF A HOLDING
CELL OR ON THE BENCH OF A HOLDING CELL IS MY INTEREST AS
THE SHERIFF TO HAVE THAT SPACE FOR THEM TO COME TO THIS SAME
INDIVIDUAL WILL BE PICKED UP IN THE PUBLIC BY POLICE, BY
SHERIFFS ARRESTED AND DETAINED UNDER THOSE CIRCUMSTANCES
AND WITHOUT THIS CENTER WOULD BE BROUGHT TO EITHER JAIL OR IF
THEIR CONDITION NECESSITATED IT TO THE HOSPITAL AND THIS IS THE
OPTION RIGHT BETWEEN A JAIL IN RIGHT BETWEEN A HOSPITAL
THAT WE ARE ASKING FOR AS AN OPTION TO HELP PEOPLE THAT ARE
UNDER THE INFLUENCE RIGHT. >> THANK YOU, MR. SHERIFF
CHURCH YEAH. >> WELL, I MEAN I THINK SINCE I
DIDN'T HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO ASK THOSE QUESTIONS WITHOUT YOU
KNOW AND WITH SOME OF THE NEW INFORMATION, THEN I WOULD LIKE
TO ASK THIS QUESTION. >> SO IS IS IS THIS CENTER A
DETENTION FACILITY OR IS IT NOT?
>> SO WE REQUESTED AN EVALUATION FROM THE BOARD OF
STATE COMMUNITY CORRECTIONS THERE EVALUATION ASCERTAIN THAT
THIS IS NOT A DETENTION FACILITY, WHAT WE CALL A TYPE
ONE HOLDING FACILITY TO PAINT THE PICTURE AGAIN, THIS DOESN'T
HAVE BARS. THIS DOESN'T HAVE LOCKED DOORS
. THIS IS AN OPEN ALMOST
DORMITORY LIKE ENVIRONMENT SIMILAR TO A 20 DEGREE WHERE
THERE IS ACCESS IMMEDIATE ACCESS TO CARE.
THE INTENTION IS TO MAKE SURE PEOPLE HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO
SOBER UP AND THEN WHAT WE DO AFTER THEY'RE SOBER IS AND THEY
ARE ABLE TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES OR AT LEAST ARE IN THE PROCESS
OF BECOMING ABLE TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES.
WE ISSUE A CERTIFICATE OF RELEASE RIGHT THERE SO THEY ARE
NOT BOOKED INTO THE SYSTEM AND THEY'RE STILL GIVEN THE
OPPORTUNITY TO REST UP TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES UNDER THE
SUPERVISION OF A HEALTH CARE PERSONNEL, CLINICIANS
AND PEOPLE WHO HAVE CONNECTIVITY TO OTHER SERVICES
OUTSIDE OF THE CENTER. AND SO WHAT YOU'RE SAYING IS
THAT WE HAVE RECEIVE A FORMAL DETERMINATION AND FROM THE
BOARD OF STATE AND COMMUNITY CORRECTIONS THAT THIS IS NOT A
DETENTION FACILITY. >> YES, WE ASKED FOR THAT NOT
JUST VERBALLY BUT IN WRITING AND WE DID RECEIVE THAT
IN WRITING. >> SO WE SAW THAT IN WRITING.
YES. OKAY.
THAT'S NOT WHAT I'M BEING TOLD BUT AND SO HAVE WE THEN BEEN
FORMALLY DETERMINED THAT THE FACILITY IS A TEMPORARY HOLDING
FACILITY? NO, ACTUALLY IT'S NOT A
TEMPORARY HOLDING FACILITY AND IT'S A SOBERING CENTERS FOR
LACK OF A BETTER TERM. >> YES.
AND BUT HOW DO PEOPLE GET TO THE CENTER?
>> ARE THEY ARE THEY THE THE THE POPULATION IN THAT END UP
ARRIVING AT THE CENTER IS VOLUNTARILY OR WERE THEY AT OR
AFTER THEY WERE DETAINED THEY WOULD BE COMPELLED TO COME TO
THE CENTER UNDER OUR CUSTODY BECAUSE THEY'RE BEING ARRESTED
ON THE STREET FOR BEING UNDER THE INFLUENCE.
>> SO THE ONLY TIME THAT THE SO THE ONLY POPULATION OR ONLY
ONLY THE INDIVIDUALS, ONLY THE INDIVIDUALS THAT WILL BE
ARRIVING AT A CENTER ARE THE INDIVIDUALS THAT WILL BE
DETAINED AND ARRESTED. >> THE YES, CORRECT.
WE HAVE ALL THE OTHER OPTIONS CURRENTLY AVAILABLE FOR
INDIVIDUALS FOR VARYING DEGREES OF VOLUNTARY ACCESS TO SERVICES
FOR BEING SUPPORTED BY STREET PROTEST RESPONSE TEAMS BY OUR
AMBASSADORS, BY OUR VOLUNTEERS OUT THERE.
THE ONE STEPPED AT THIS THIS ONE GAP THAT THIS FILLS IS
INSTEAD OF HAVING SOMEBODY WHO IS ARRESTED OR DETAINED UNDER
THE INFLUENCE BEING BROUGHT TO JAIL, THEY'RE BEING BROUGHT TO
THIS FACILITY TO SOBER UP. BUT THEN THIS WOULD NOT
CONSIDER EVEN AS A TEMPORARY DETENTION CENTER NO, IT WOULD
NOT BE UNDER THE EVALUATION OF THE BOARD OF STATE COMMUNITY
CORRECTIONS. THIS IS NOT A TYPE ONE HOLDING
FACILITY, A DETENTION FACILITY AND WE HAVE RIGHT.
WE HAVE LIKE WRITTEN DOCUMENTS BY THEM SAYING THAT THIS THEY
HAVE DEEMED THAT THIS IS NOT A DETENTION FACILITY.
>> I HAVE I HAVE ACTUALLY SEEN THE EMAILS THAT WERE WRITTEN BY
OUR REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE BORDER STATE COMMUNITY
CORRECTIONS WHICH CLEARLY STATE THAT THIS IS NOT A TYPE ONE
DETENTION FACILITY. I WOULD LIKE TO SEE THAT.
>> I WOULD LIKE TO SEE THAT INFORMATION AS WOULD AND IF
THAT CITY ATTORNEY ALSO AGREE THAT CONSIDER THAT AS A FORMAL
ASSESSMENT FROM FROM FROM THE BORDER STATES AND COMMUNICATE
COMMUNITY A CORRECT YOU WANT US TO COME BACK TO US WE COULD DO
OUR 232 TO COME BACK OKAY SO WE WILL BEFORE WE DO SUPERVISOR
ONE WE HAVE A MOTION ON THE FLOOR BUT WE CAN WHEN WE WILL
TAKE THAT UP WHEN WE COME BACK. WE CAN DO THAT.
YEAH RIGHT. OKAY SO WE ARE GOING TO TAKE A
LITTLE BREAK TO GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL COMMENDATION.
>> MADAM CLERK, THIS IS THE RECOGNITION OF COMMON DONATIONS
FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO SPECIAL ORDER 230. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
AND WE WILL START WITH THE DISTRICT TO SUPERVISOR CHERYL
WELL, COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM HONORED TO COMMEND THE ANIMAL
CARE AND CONTROL SEC TEAM WHO RECENTLY DID OUR COMMUNITY A
GREAT SERVICE BY SAFELY CAPTURING AND RELOCATING A
ROAMING MOUNTAIN LION ON JANUARY 27TH 2026.
THEY INCLUDE OFFICERS PETER QUIRKE AND MCKENNA THOMAS.
SORRY IF I MISPRONOUNCED YOUR NAME.
>> LIEUTENANT STEPHANIE RYDER. LIEUTENANT JASON CANTU COULDN'T
JOIN US TODAY. >> CAPTAIN REBECCA BENSON
AND DEPUTY DIRECTOR AMY CORSO. >> PLEASE COME STEP UP TO THE
DAIS. RIGHT.
MEOW. >> THANK YOU FOR SUPERVISOR
CHERYL. FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU FROM
ALL OF US. THANK YOU.
>> AS YOU MAY HAVE SEEN, LOCAL RESIDENTS FIRST SIGHTED A
MOUNTAIN LION EARLY. YOU KNOW IT SAYS PAWS HERE
IN MY REMARKS BUT IS SPELLED P A U S GOD.
>> SO THE MOUNTAIN LION WAS SIGHTED EARLY ON THE MORNING OF
MONDAY, JANUARY 26TH CLOSE TO LAFAYETTE PARK AND IMMEDIATELY
THE ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL TEAM LEAPT INTO ACTION.
>> FIRST THE ACT TEAM ISSUED A STATEMENT TO THE PUBLIC
EDUCATING ALL OF US ABOUT WHAT TO DO TO STAY SAFE.
THEN THE OFFICERS ALONG WITH REC AND PARK RANGERS AND THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE PATROLLED
LAFAYETTE PARK, THE SURROUNDING AREA RESPONDING TO TIPS
AND CALLS FROM THE PUBLIC. THESE OFFICERS ERS WERE
STATIONED ALL NIGHT IN ORDER TO ENSURE THE SAFETY OF THE PUBLIC
AND THE MOUNTAIN LION. AND EVEN AFTER LOCATING THE
LION THEY STRATEGICALLY WAITED FOR THE ANIMAL TO BE IN A
POSITION WHERE THE TEAM COULD SAFELY TRANQUILIZE HIM
SUCCESSFULLY SECURING HIM FOR RELOCATION AT 10:30 A.M. ON
TUESDAY JANUARY 27TH. NOW FOR THOSE WHO ARE WORRIED,
THE SEC TEAM THEN COORDINATED WITH THE BIOLOGY COURSE FROM
THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE AND THE SAN
FRANCISCO ZOO CHIEF VETERINARIAN DR. ADRIAN MELLO
TO ENSURE THAT THE YOUNG LION WAS IN GOOD HEALTH EQUIPPING
HIM WITH A NEW TRACKING COLLAR AND SENDING HIM BACK TO HIS
HABITAT IN THE SANTA CRUZ MOUNTAINS.
THIS TEAM'S READINESS, COORDINATION AND EXECUTION WERE
TRULY PERFECT AND WE ARE ALL GRATEFUL FOR THEIR QUICK WORK
TO CAPTURE THE MOUNTAIN LION JUST 30 HOURS AFTER BEING
NOTIFIED. >> IT TURNS OUT THE LION WAS
ORIGINALLY TAGGED BY THE PUMA PROJECT BUT HE'D LOST HIS
ORIGINAL TRACKING COLLAR AS A KITTEN WHICH ALLOWED HIM TO
WANDER FROM THE SANTA CRUZ MOUNTAINS TO SAN FRANCISCO
WITHOUT BEING NOTICED. AND WHILE THIS EVENT IS NORMAL
FOR MALE LIONS AT AROUND TWO YEARS OLD OR TRYING TO CLAIM
THEIR OWN TERRITORY. IT IS POSITIVELY NOT NORMAL FOR
THESE LIONS TO ARRIVE IN SAN. THAT'S THE LAST PUN I SWEAR FOR
THESE LIONS TO ARRIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THIS LION SEEMS
TO HAVE FOUND THE CITY'S INCLINES TO MOUNTAINOUS.
>> BUT ABOVE ALL ONE THING IS VERY VERY CLEAR.
WE ALL HAVE TO EXPECT THE UNEXPECTED IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND YOU ALL WERE REMARKABLE IN YOUR QUICK ABILITY TO DO
JUST THAT. >> THE STAFF AT ASSISI ARE
UNSUNG HEROES OF THIS CITY NOT JUST LAST MONTH BUT ALL YEAR
ROUND. YOU PROVIDE VITAL CARE FOR OUR
BELOVED PETS AND YOU ENSURE PUBLIC SAFETY IN FRANKLY WILD
INSTANCES LIKE THIS. AND WITH THAT I AM SO GRATEFUL
FOR THE PROACTIVE INFORMED, ACTIVE, CAREFUL, THOUGHTFUL
MANNER IN WHICH YOU ALL ACTED TO ENSURE BOTH OUR COMMUNITY
AND THE WILDLIFE THAT CALLS THE AREA HOME SAFE.
IT IS MY HONOR AND PLEASURE TO COMMEND YOUR ACTIONS HERE TODAY
AT THE BOARD. SO THANK YOU TO ALL OF YOU
AND I'D LIKE TO INVITE DEPUTY CORSO TO SHARE A FEW WORDS ON
BEHALF OF THE GROUP. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHERYL
FOR THIS HONOR. I'M PROUD TO BE STANDING HERE
WITH FOUR OF OUR ANIMAL CONTROL OFFICERS WHO REPRESENT A SMALL
BUT MIGHTY ECHO TEAM. WE CURRENTLY HAVE 14 OFFICERS
WHO SERVE THE ENTIRE CITY FROM 6 A.M. TO MIDNIGHT SEVEN DAYS A
WEEK. >> NOW THIS JOB CAN OFTEN BE A
THANKLESS JOB BUT THEY DO IT BECAUSE THEY LOVE IT AND THEY
TRULY CARE. >> AND THE EVENTS OF JANUARY 26
AND 27TH PERFECTLY HIGHLIGHT THE DEDICATION OF THIS TEAM.
THESE OFFICERS WORK TIRELESSLY THROUGHOUT THE NIGHT TRACKING
THIS LION, WORKING EXTRA HOURS ON TOP OF AN ALREADY LONG TEN
HOUR SHIFT. >> AND THEN THEY SHOWED UP THE
NEXT DAY FOR WORK. >> NO COMPLAINTS.
SO THIS WAS ACTUALLY THE FOURTH INCIDENT OF A MOUNTAIN LION
SINCE 2017 THAT HCC SUCCESSFULLY COORDINATED A
MULTI-AGENCY RESPONSE TO RELOCATE.
AND THEY DID IT SUCCESSFULLY. >> AND WE PRIORITIZE PUBLIC
SAFETY WHILE MAINTAINING THE WELFARE OF THE LION.
AND WHILE WE DON'T DO THIS JOB FOR THE RECOGNITION, THIS
ACKNOWLEDGMENT MEANS A GREAT DEAL TO US ALL.
>> SO ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE TEAM, THANK YOU.
AND I'D ALSO LIKE TO RECOGNIZE SEC DIRECTOR VIRGINIA DONOHUE
WHO I BELIEVE IS HERE WITH US TODAY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP DIRECTOR
DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT MANDO MIN. COLLEAGUES TODAY AS WE CONTINUE
TO HONOR THE CONTRIBUTIONS OF BLACK PEOPLE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO, IT IS TRULY AN HONOR TO RECOGNIZE AND CELEBRATE A
REMARKABLE LEADER ADVOCATE AND COMMUNITY PILLAR MISS
SHIBLI SCOTT. AS YOU WALK UP TO THE PODIUM
FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES, SHIBLI HAS POURED HER HEART,
HER TIME AND HER UNWAVERING COMMITMENT INTO THE BAYVIEW
HUNTERS POINT COMMUNITY. SIBLEY'S DEDICATION TO OUR
YOUNG PEOPLE IS ESPECIALLY POWERFUL.
DURING HER TEN YEARS WITH HUNTERS POINT FAMILY AND GIRLS
2,001ST AS A CASE MANAGER AND LATER AS PROGRAM DIRECTOR,
SHE HELPED GUIDE MENTOR AND UPLIFT COUNTLESS YOUTH
ENSURING THEY HAD THE TOOLS CONFIDENCE AND SUPPORT NEEDED
TO THRIVE. >> HER WORK WAS NEVER JUST A
JOB. IT WAS A CALLING ROOTED
IN BUILDING STRONGER FUTURES FOR THE NEXT GENERATION.
>> HER LEADERSHIP EXTENDS FAR BEYOND ONE ORGANIZATION.
SIBLEY HAS PLAYED A KEY ROLE IN ENVIRONMENTAL
AND NEIGHBORHOOD BEAUTIFICATION EFFORTS WORKING ALONGSIDE
COMMUNITY LEADERS LIKE GEOFFREY OF MORRIS TO ADVANCE THE 94124
PARKS GRANT PROPOSAL AND EFFORT FOCUSED ON IMPROVING
AND PRESERVING THE PUBLIC SPACES OUR FAMILIES RELY ON
EVERY DAY. >> SIBLEY HAS ALSO BEEN A
CONSISTENT PRESENCE IN YOUTH SPORTS AND RECREATION
CONTRIBUTING HER VOICE AND ENERGY AS A FOOTBALL
ANNOUNCER WITH THE BROWN BOMBERS AND SUPPORTING ADULT
SOFTBALL PROGRAMS THROUGH SPORTS.
SHE HAS HELPED FOSTER TEAMWORK, DISCIPLINE AND JOY FOR
RESIDENTS OF ALL AGES AND ALUMNI OF MCATEER HIGH
SCHOOL IN SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY.
SIBLEY CONTINUES TO LEAD BY EXAMPLE AS PRESIDENT OF BLACK
WOMEN INVESTORS, AN ALL FEMALE AFRICAN-AMERICAN INVESTMENT
ORGANIZATION DEDICATED TO BUILDING WEALTH, HOSTING
COMMUNITY CENTERED EVENTS AND CREATING FINANCIAL
OPPORTUNITIES THAT STRENGTHEN BOTH FAMILIES AND NEIGHBORHOODS
. >> THROUGH THIS WORK SHE IS
HELPING REDEFINE WHAT COLLECTIVE EMPOWERMENT
AND ECONOMIC JUSTICE LOOK LIKE IN REAL TIME.
>> CURRENTLY SHE IS ALSO OUR. I WAIT FOR THE SUPERVISORS.
>> THANK YOU. CURRENTLY SHE IS ALSO 13 YEARS
WITH MTA. >> DEPARTMENT OF TRAFFIC.
>> AND NOW SERVES AS A SUPERVISOR.
BUT BEYOND HER MANY TITLES AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS, SIBLEY IS
MOST PROUD OF HER FAMILY. SHE IS A DEVOTED MOTHER TO HER
SONS. KAREEN, A RECENT GRADUATE OF
JACKSON STATE UNIVERSITY AND A MERE.
SHE IS DEEPLY SUPPORTED BY HER HUSBAND, MR. EMIL ROBINSON,
WHOSE LOVE AND PARTNERSHIP HAVE BEEN A CORNERSTONE OF HER
STRENGTH. TODAY WE RECOGNIZE NOT JUST THE
WORK SIBLINGS SCOTT HAS DONE BUT THE LIVES SHE HAS TOUCHED.
THE DOOR SHE HAS OPENED AND THE LASTING LEGACY SHE CONTINUES TO
BUILD. AND BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT.
HER COMMITMENT REMINDS US WHAT TRUE COMMUNITY LEADERSHIP LOOKS
LIKE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE,
YOUR LEADERSHIP AND FOR CONTINUING TO INSPIRE US ALL
TODAY SHOULD BELIEVE WE HONOR YOU.
>> YOU MAKE ME SOUND LIKE A GOOD.
ALL RIGHT. >> SO THANK YOU TO EVERYBODY.
I'M A BEE SHORT AND SWEET. ANYBODY WHO KNOWS ME KNOW I'M
DEFINITELY NEVER SHORT AND SWEET BUT I'M GONNA KEEP
THIS SIMPLE SMILE YOU MADE ME SOUND EXCELLENT.
>> I FEEL LIKE MICHELLE UP HERE RIGHT?
BUT NO THANK YOU TO EVERYBODY THAT CAME OUT.
OF COURSE I'M SUPPORTING MY COMMUNITY AS MUCH AS I POSSIBLY
CAN ALWAYS AND CONTINUOUSLY WILL.
BUT I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO MY COMMUNITY.
DO YOU SEE MY PEOPLE IN HERE SUPPORTING ME?
>> I GOT MY MOTHER. I GOT MY MOTHER HERE, MY TWO
SONS IN HERE, MY STEP MOM, MY MOTHER IN LAW, MY AUNTIE.
I GOT THREE BEST FRIENDS THAT'S BEEN MY FRIENDS FOR OVER 40
YEARS AND MY PCOS LOOK AT MY STAND UP PCOS PEOPLE STILL
GETTING TICKETS, PEOPLE STILL GETTING TICKETS I PROMISE.
BUT THANK YOU GUYS. SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU
TO MY COMMUNITY IF THAT MAKES SENSE.
IT TAKES A COMMUNITY TO BUILD A COMMUNITY AND SHARE MY THANK
YOU FOR TAKING CARE OF MY MY BOY PERCY AS JAY JUST MADE
MAJOR LOVE TO EVERYBODY. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
OH, I'M SO SORRY EVERYBODY IS WAITING AND HE AND HIS
SUPERVISOR WALTON WANTS TO BE PART OF THE CONVERSATION ABOUT
ITEM 12. SO WE'RE GOING TO GO TO ITEM 13
. >> ITEM 13 THIS RESOLUTION
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $1.1 MILLION GRANT FROM THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE FOR THE 2025 TOBACCO
GRANT PROGRAM TO FUND PERSONNEL AND OPERATING EXPENSES FOR THE
S.F. PD'S DMA CC THE DRUG MARKET AGENCY COORDINATION
CENTER PROJECT TERM BEGINNING ON NOVEMBER 21ST, 2025 THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2029. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM
13. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN EYE SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR
EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYE AND SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON ABSENT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 14 ITEM 14.
THIS ITEM WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE. ITEM 14 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
APPROVE A HOTEL DEVELOPMENT INCENTIVE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE
CITY AND COUNTY AND BESPOKE HOSPITALITY LLC FOR THE HEARST
HOTEL DEVELOPMENT PROJECT TO PROVIDE 40 MILLION IN FINANCIAL
ASSISTANCE AND NET PRESENT VALUE OVER 20 YEARS CALCULATED
FOR MEASUREMENT PURPOSES ONLY AS A PERCENTAGE OF NEW
TRANSIENT OCCUPANCY TAXES THE CITY ACTUALLY RECEIVES FROM
OCCUPANCY OF GUEST ROOMS IN A PROPOSED NEW HOTEL RELATED TO
THE DEVELOPMENT AND OPERATION OF A PROJECT ON CERTAIN REAL
PROPERTY KNOWN AS FIVE THIRD STREET AND 17TH THROUGH 29
THIRD STREET TO WAIVE CHAPTER 21 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
AND CERTAIN SECTIONS OF THE LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT CODE
AND TO RATIFY PASSED AND TO AUTHORIZE FUTURE ACTIONS
IN FURTHERANCE OF THIS ORDINANCE AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU PRESENT
AMENDMENT I FIRST REALLY WANT TO THANK VICE CHAIR DORSEY FOR
JUST ALL THE CONVERSATION DURING THE BUDGET COMMITTEE.
I KNOW THAT VICE CHAIR DORSEY THIS IS NOT ONLY A PROJECT THAT
HE SUPPORTS THAT HE'S A CO-SPONSOR OF BUT ALSO WITH THE
WILLINGNESS TO HAVE THE OPEN DISCUSSION ABOUT NOT JUST ABOUT
THIS PROJECT AND WITH THE UNDERSTANDING THAT MY QUESTION
REALLY MAINLY FOCUSED ON THE INVESTMENT AGAIN IN DOWNTOWN
AND AND IN THE AREA THAT WE ARE PUTTING A LOT OF RESOURCES
IN THIS SPACE AND THAT BE IT AROUND MOST RECENTLY LAST WEEK
COLLEAGUES OUT THE DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION FINANCING PLAN
THAT DEDICATED $610 MILLION OF FUTURE REVENUE THAT FOR TO OVER
45 YEARS INVESTMENTS IN THAT AREA NOT TO MENTION THE IMPACT
FEE WAIVERS AS INCLUSIONARY WAIVERS OR ALLOWING COMMERCIAL
SPACES TO CONVERT INTO RESIDENTIAL AND I THINK THAT
HERE WE ARE ANOTHER PROPERTY WITHIN THAT ZONE THIS TIME IT'S
A HOTEL DEVELOPMENT WITH $40 MILLION TO DEDICATE IT AGAIN
FUTURE REVENUE OF THE $40 MILLION DEDICATED OVER 20 YEARS
OF TIME IN THE HOPE THAT THIS WILL AGAIN BOOST BOOST BREW
STREET CORNER SPICES SPECIFICALLY AT THIRD STREETS
AND MARKET. >> WOW I REALLY THINK THAT
DOWNTOWN IS CRITICAL TO SAN FRANCISCO'S LOCAL ECONOMY
AND AND HOW WE CAN BOUNCE BACK. THIS IS SOMETHING THAT WE MUST
DO IN TERMS OF INVESTING IN DOWNTOWN.
>> I BEGIN TO HAVE MORE QUESTIONS THAN ANSWER TO
MAYOR AND HIS TEAM ABOUT THIS INVESTMENT AND HOW THESE
INVESTMENTS ACTUALLY ALL GOING TO COME TOGETHER.
I WOULD LIKE TO HAVE A BETTER UNDERSTANDING OF A VISION FOR
THE ENTIRE ZONE BEFORE I CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THESE TYPES
OF PIECEMEAL PROJECTS SO TO SPEAK.
I WOULD LIKE TO HAVE A MORE COHESIVE INVESTMENT PLAN FOR
DOWNTOWN AND SO THAT WE CAN COLLECTIVELY AND COMPREHENSIVE
WE CALCULATE AND PROJECT BOTH OUR INVESTMENTS DOLLARS FROM
THE PUBLIC DOLLARS AND THEN AS WELL AS THE TYPE OF REVENUE
THAT WE EXPECT US TO GENERATE SO THAT WE HAVE A BETTER IDEA.
BUT ALSO BETTER METRICS TO MEASURE THAT SUCCESS CLEARLY
THESE ARE LONG TERM INVESTMENTS TYPICALLY MORE THAN A DECADE OF
YOU KNOW UP TO A 45 YEARS. BUT I STILL WOULD LIKE TO HAVE
A MORE COMPREHENSIVE EVALUATION AND COMPREHENSIVE ANALYSIS
AND ALLOW US TO MAKE A BETTER DETERMINATION WHETHER THESE
TYPE OF INVESTMENTS WILL YIELD A RESULT THAT WE ARE LOOKING
FOR. AND SO FOR THAT I WOULD NOT BE
SUPPORTIVE OF THIS ITEM 14 ALTHOUGH I THINK THAT THAT IS
NOT TO SAY THAT I WILL NOT CHANGE MY MIND DOWN THE ROAD
WHEN I HAVE A BETTER UNDERSTANDING OF THE
INFORMATION THAT I HAVE JUST MENTIONED FROM THE MAYOR AND
THE MAYOR'S TEAM. >> THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU. PRESIDENT EDELMAN.
THE BUDGET COMMITTEE SENT THIS OUT AS YOU KNOW WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION AND AS I SAID IN COMMITTEE I TEND TO VIEW
DOING THAT AS A COURTESY THAT WE SEND FROM THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE TO YOU WHEN THERE IS AN ACTIVE CONTENTION OR ISSUE.
AND I KNOW CHAIR CHAN HAD CONCERNS AND INCLUDING CONCERNS
BY THE WAY THAT I SHARE ABOUT BEING MAXIMALLY TRANSPARENT
WHEN WHENEVER WE'RE DOING SOMETHING THAT IS COMMITTING
RESOURCES OR IN THIS CASE DENYING OURSELVES RESOURCES IF
WE HAVE AN OBLIGATION TO BE TRANSPARENT WITH THE FINANCES
ON THAT I AM 100% ON BOARD. THAT SAID, HOWEVER, THIS IS
SOMETHING THAT I FEEL VERY STRONGLY ABOUT.
THIS IS THE KIND OF INCENTIVE THAT WE NEED FOR PROJECTS LIKE
ADAPTIVE REUSE PROJECTS THAT ARE UNIQUELY IMPORTANT.
I PERSONALLY AM STRONGLY ENTHUSIASTIC ABOUT ADAPTIVE
REUSE PROJECTS LIKE THIS ONES AND AND OTHERS THAT I MAY TALK
ABOUT EVEN TODAY. OFFICE CONVERSION IS LIKE THIS
PROJECT ENABLE US TO RETAIN THE RICH ARCHITECTURE ARCHITECTURAL
HERITAGE OF OUR HISTORIC ASSETS WHICH MAKE OUR DOWNTOWN
STREETSCAPE SUCH A GLOBALLY ADMIRED DESTINATION BUT IT ALSO
ENABLES US TO FACILITATE NEW USES THAT REINVIGORATE OUR
DOWNTOWN FOR 21ST CENTURY ECONOMIC IMPERATIVES.
THIS IS AN INTENTIONAL INCENTIVE LIKE THE $40 MILLION
CREDIT THAT FILLS THE PROJECT FEASIBILITY GAP AND WE HAVE
GUARDRAILS IN PLACE TO EXERCISE FISCAL OVERSIGHT.
THE PROGRAM WILL EXPIRE IN 20 YEARS EVEN IF THE HOTEL DOES
NOT SUCCEED AND THE BENEFIT WILL CUT OFF SOONER IF IT'S A
SUCCESS. THE CONVERSATION AT THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE CENTERED ON THE NEED TO HAVE A COMPREHENSIVE VISION
FOR DOWNTOWN AND I AND OUR USE OF FINANCIAL INCENTIVES.
I DON'T DISAGREE BUT I THINK THIS THIS AGREEMENT IS PART OF
A POLICY FRAMEWORK FROM WHAT WE NEED TO SPECIFICALLY
INCENTIVIZE HOTELS WHICH I THINK WE NEED AN INDIVIDUAL
AGREEMENT LIKE THIS ONE IS TAILORED IN A WAY THAT STRIKES
A BALANCE BETWEEN KICKSTARTING A PROJECT AND RETAINING AS MUCH
OF OUR TAX BENEFITS AS WE CAN. AND THIS IT WILL BE A PROJECT
BY PROJECT CALL. SO COLLEAGUES, I HOPE TO HAVE
YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS FAIR AGREEMENT THAT WILL BRING 150
JOBS DOWNTOWN PRESERVE HISTORIC RESOURCE AND INVIGORATE PART OF
MARKET STREET THAT I REPRESENT .
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM AND I'M LOOKING
FORWARD TO SUPPORTING THIS AS WELL.
THIS HOTEL SITS JUST A FEW FEET OUT OF MY DISTRICT AND I THINK
IT'S A REALLY IMPORTANT SPACE ON MARKET STREET.
YOU KNOW I'VE LOOKED AT THE NUMBERS HERE AND I'M VERY
COMFORTABLE WITH THE NUMBERS. THE PROPOSED DEVELOPMENT IS
PROJECTED TO PROVIDE NET GENERAL FUND REVENUES OF
APPROXIMATELY $713,000 PER YEAR COMPARED TO THE EXISTING LAND
USE. WHEN YOU LOOK AT WHAT'S THERE
RIGHT NOW 7,080% OFFICE VACANCY ON THAT SITE YOU COMPARE IT TO
WHAT WILL BE THERE. WE'RE LOOKING AT A TEN X
INCREASE IN PROPERTY TAX REVENUE EACH YEAR.
WE'RE ALSO LOOKING AT APPROXIMATELY $157,000 IN NET
REVENUE TO THE MTA EACH YEAR. THAT IS MONEY I THINK WE CAN
ALL AGREE THAT WE'D LIKE TO SEE PUT INTO TRANSIT INVESTED
IN OUR PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION. YOU KNOW THE THE STRUCTURE OF
THESE INCENTIVES AND DEALS MEANS THAT WE LOOK AT THESE ONE
BY ONE ONE OFF. THAT'S WHAT WE'RE DOING HERE
AND THIS PARTICULAR DEVELOPMENT IS A GOOD DEAL FOR THE CITY.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO SEEING IT BUILT.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
I HAVE A QUICK QUESTION BECAUSE I KNOW THERE'S TALK ABOUT THE
INCREASE OF PROPERTY TAX REVENUE.
WHO CAN TELL ME HOW MUCH OF THAT GOES TO THE DEVELOPER
AND HOW MUCH OF THAT GOES TO THE CITY?
DOES WHO HAS A POTENTIAL L.A.? I'M GONNA TRY MR. MINARD.
>> YEAH. NICK MENARD FROM THE BUDGET
LEGISLATIVE ANALYSIS OFFICE. SO THIS AGREEMENT REBATES THE
HOTEL TAX, NOT THE PROPERTY TAX.
AND SO THE HOTEL TAX GENERATED BY THIS PROJECT WILL BE ABOUT
$3 MILLION A YEAR. THAT WOULD BE THE CITY GIVING
THAT BACK TO THE DEVELOPER. BUT THE CITY WOULD RETAIN ITS
SHARE OF THE PROPERTY TAXES UNDER THE AGREEMENT.
SO IT'S NOT LIKE WE DON'T GET ANY OF THE HOTEL TAX.
>> WE GET OUR REGULAR TRADITIONAL PROPERTY TAX
AND UNTIL UNTIL THE CITY PAYS $40 MILLION OR THE PAYMENTS
HAPPEN OVER 20 YEARS. >> AND THEN HOW DOES THIS
INCREASE PROPERTY TAX REVENUE BECAUSE THE VALUE OF THE HOTEL
IS HIGHER IS PROJECTED TO BE HIGHER THAN THE VACANT OFFICE
BUILDING THAT'S THERE NOW. >> SO THEY'RE NOT THEY'RE NOT
PAYING THEY'RE GOING TO PAY MORE PROPERTY TAX THAN THEY PAY
TODAY. >> CORRECT.
HOW MUCH MORE OFF THE TOP OF MY HEAD I BELIEVE IT'S ABOUT
$500,000 A YEAR ADDITIONAL. >> THANK YOU.
>> OKAY. IF THERE'S NO MORE COMMENTS OR
QUESTIONS, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 14
AND ITEM 14. >> SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN
AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING. ALL RIGHT COLLEAGUES WE'VE GOT
A COUPLE OF 3 P.M. OR A FEW 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDERS WE WILL GET
THROUGH THOSE THEN WE WILL COME BACK TO ITEM 12 AND THEN WE
WILL MAKE OUR WAY THROUGH THE REMAINDER OF OUR OF OUR ITEMS.
>> SO WITH THAT MADAM CLERK I THINK WE'RE GOING TO TAKE OUR 3
P.M. SPECIAL ORDERS NOT IN THE ORDER THAT THEY ARE IN OUR
AGENDA BECAUSE I THINK WE THINK WE MAY BE ABLE TO RELATIVELY
QUICKLY DISPOSE OF ITEMS 27 THROUGH 30 SO COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL ITEM 27 TO THROW TOGETHER? >> YES ITEM 27 THIS IS A PUBLIC
HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE DE FACTO DENIAL OF A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR A PROPOSED PROJECT AT 524
THROUGH 526 VALLEJO STREET AND FOR FOR A SAN ANTONIO PLACE
TO LEGALIZE THE MERGER OF THREE DWELLING UNITS ON SECOND
AND THIRD FLOORS INTO ONE DWELLING UNIT AND TO REINSTATE
ONE DWELLING UNIT ON THE GROUND FLOOR WITHIN AN EXISTING FOUR
UNIT RESIDENTIAL BUILDING ITEM 2829 AND 30 ARE THE MOTIONS
ASSOCIATED WITH THAT PUBLIC HEARING SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK
YOU PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN ON THESE ITEMS IN THE LAST DAY OR
SO NEW INFORMATION HAS COME TO LIGHT THAT I THINK BOTH PARTIES
AND THIS BODY SHOULD HAVE MORE TIME TO DIGEST.
AND SO GIVEN THAT BOTH THE PARTIES INVOLVED HERE HAVE
AGREED TO A CONTINUANCE AND I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION
THAT WE CONTINUE THIS ITEM UNTIL MARCH 10TH MARCH 10TH
SECONDED BY WALTON. ALL RIGHT.
I THINK WE NEED TO TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCE
BEFORE WE VOTE ON IT. SO MADAM CLERK, DO YOU WANT TO
CALL FOR PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCE?
>> YES. THE PRESIDENT IS HAS NOW OPENED
PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCE FOR ITEMS 27
THROUGH 30. THIS IS THE APPEAL OF THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION DE FACTO DENIAL FOR THE VALLEJO
STREET PROJECT. IF YOU'RE HERE, NOW'S YOUR
OPPORTUNITY TO COME FORWARD. ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE
CONTINUANCE IS CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE MOTION ON THE MOTION TO CONTINUE ITEMS 27
THROUGH 30 TO MARCH 10TH 2026. >> SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL
MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED AND THESE AND ITEMS 27 TO 30 ARE CONTINUED UNTIL MARCH
10TH. >> ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK THAT
TAKES US BACK. LET'S GO TO OUR FIRST TO 3 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDERS PLEASE CALL ITEMS 19 THROUGH 26 TOGETHER.
>> YES I WILL GROUP ITEMS 19 THROUGH 22 FIRST THEY COMPRISE
THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE DETERMINATION
OF EXEMPTION FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT ISSUED AS A CATEGORICAL
EXEMPTION BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ON MAY 29TH 2025 FOR
THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 350 AMBER DRIVE TO INSTALL A NEW
AT&T MACRO WIRELESS TELECOMMUNICATIONS FACILITY ON
AN APPROXIMATELY 104 FOOT TALL MONOPOLE CONSISTING OF 12 NEW
ANTENNAS AND NINE NEW REMOTE RADIO UNITS AND ANCILLARY
EQUIPMENT WITHIN THE PUBLIC ZONING DISTRICT AND THE OS THE
OPEN SPACE HEIGHT AND BULK DISTRICT.
ITEM 20 THIS MOTION AFFIRMS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S
DETERMINATION THAT THE PROPOSED AMBER DRIVE PROJECT IS
CATEGORICALLY EXEMPT FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW.
ITEM 21 IS THE MOTION TO CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE
DETERMINATION SUBJECT TO THE APPROVED FINDINGS BY THE BOARD
IN SUPPORT OF THAT DETERMINATION.
AND ITEM 22 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF
FINDINGS. THE SECOND GROUPING THIS IS
ITEM 23 THROUGH 26 COMPRISE THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS
INTERESTED IN THE APPROVAL OF A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
FOR THE SAME PROJECT AT THREE 5350 AMBER DRIVE AGAIN ISSUED
BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION BY ITS MOTION DATED SEPTEMBER 25TH
2025 TO INSTALL THE AFOREMENTIONED WIRELESS
TELECOMMUNICATIONS FACILITY FROM AT&T.
ITEM 24 IS THE MOTION TO APPROVE THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DECISION TO APPROVE A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION. ITEM 25 IS THE MOTION TO
DISAPPROVE THAT DECISION BASED UPON APPROVED FINDINGS BY THE
BOARD AND ITEM 26 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE CLERK TO PREPARE
FINDINGS. >> ALL RIGHT COLLEAGUES, THIS
WOULD BE A LITTLE BIT REPETITIVE BUT AS YOU HEARD WE
HAVE BEFORE US TWO APPEAL HEARINGS WITH ONE APPELLANT ON
THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 350 AMBER DRIVE.
ITEMS 19 TO 22 COMPRISE THE APPEAL OF THE DETERMINATION OF
EXEMPTION FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW AND ITEMS 23 THROUGH 26
ARE THE APPEAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION.
AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD WILL VOTE ON TWO THINGS ONE
WHETHER TO AFFIRM OR CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION THAT THIS PROJECT
IS CATEGORICALLY EXEMPT FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW AND TWO
WHETHER TO APPROVE OR CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR THIS PROJECT CONSISTENT
WITH PAST PRACTICE UNLESS THERE ARE OBJECTIONS WE WILL PROCEED
AS FOLLOWS WE WILL GIVE UP TO TEN MINUTES FOR A PRESENTATION
BY THE APPELLANT. THEN WE WILL OPEN THE FLOOR FOR
PUBLIC COMMENT WITH TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE
APPEAL THEN WE WILL HEAR FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR UP
TO TEN MINUTES. THEN WE WILL HEAR FROM THE
PROJECT SPONSOR FOR UP TO TEN MINUTES.
THAT WILL BE FOLLOWED BY PUBLIC COMMENT AGAIN UP TO TWO MINUTES
PER SPEAKER IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL.
FINALLY WE'LL BRING THE APPELLANT BACK UP FOR THREE
MINUTES OF REBUTTAL AND THEN WE WILL DELIBERATE.
COLLEAGUES, I DON'T SEE ANY OBJECTIONS OR QUESTIONS
AND SEEING NONE THE PUBLIC HEARING WILL PROCEED AS
INDICATED AND IS NOW OPEN. ALL RIGHT AND I WILL INVITE
CATHERINE DODD UP TO PRESENT ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANTS.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MANAGEMENT GOOD AFTERNOON
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS CATHERINE DODD.
I'M A SITTING COUNTY RETIREE, A FORMER AIDE TO TWO SUPERVISORS,
FORMER CHIEF OF STAFF, DEPUTY CHIEF OF STAFF TO MAYOR NEWSOM
AND FORMER DIRECTOR OF YOUR HEALTH SERVICE SYSTEM.
>> I'VE LIVED AND SERVED SAN FRANCISCO FOR 49 YEARS.
>> TODAY I SPEAK AS A MEMBER OF THE DIAMOND HEIGHTS COMMUNITY
ASSOCIATION. WE REQUESTED THE BOARD UPHOLD
BOTH APPEALS THE CIA AND THE SEQUOIA EXEMPTION AND DENY THIS
PROJECT WERE REMANDED BACK TO PLANNING.
FIND THAT THE APPLICATION IS INCOMPLETE AND ORDER ADDITIONAL
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW 104 FOOT MACRO TOWER WOULD BE THE
TALLEST STRUCTURE IN THE AREA AND THEREFORE NOT NECESSARY OR
DESIRABLE OR COMPATIBLE WITH THE NEIGHBORHOOD COMMUNITY.
>> MOREOVER, THE PROPOSED TOWER IS NOT CONSISTENT WITH THE CITY
SAVING GUIDELINES FOR WIRELESS FACILITIES REMANDING BACK TO
THE PLANNING COMMISSION WOULD BE APPROPRIATE AS THE APPLICANT
HAS RECEIVED. >> THE APPLICANT HAS MADE
SIGNIFICANT CHANGES TO THE PROJECT SINCE THE PLANNING
COMMISSION APPROVED IT SEVERAL RECENT APPELLATE AND TRIAL CASE
RULINGS HAVE FOUND THAT TOWERS ARE NOT A SMALL STRUCTURE
AND EXEMPT FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW.
>> AT&T HAS NUMEROUS ALTERNATIVES FOR PROVIDING
WIRELESS SERVICE THAT DON'T INVOLVE CONSTRUCTING A 104 FOOT
TEN STOREY TOWER. THE BOARD SHOULD DENY THE
PROJECT AND ORDER THE CITY TO CONSIDER ALTERNATIVES.
THE REQUEST IS SQUARELY IN THE BOARD'S DISCRETION.
WE'RE NOT ASKING YOU TO NEGOTIATE WIRELESS SERVICE OR
RF EMISSIONS. >> WE'RE ASKING YOU TO EXERCISE
CORRALES JUST CITED AUTHORITY OVER LAND USE ESTHETICS
AND ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW. >> FEDERAL LAW PRESERVES THIS
LOCAL CONTROL. SO FAR IN 2018 THE CALIFORNIA
SUPREME COURT UNANIMOUSLY UNANIMOUSLY UPHELD SAN
FRANCISCO'S PERSONAL WIRELESS FACILITY ORDINANCE CONFIRMING
YOUR AUTHORITY TO CONSIDER A SET OF EXCITING IMPACTS
AND NEIGHBORHOOD COMPATIBILITY .
>> THE FAIRNESS OF THIS PROCESS WAS UNDERMINED BY AT&T LATE
SUBMITTAL OF FINAL ARGUMENTS OUR ATTORNEYS SUBMITTED
INFORMATION ON TIME BY JANUARY 30TH AND AT&T SUBMITTED THERE'S
FIVE DAYS LATER SPECIFICALLY RESPONDING TO OUR FILING
AND INTRODUCING NEW INFORMATION THAT WE DID NOT HAVE SUFFICIENT
TIME TO RESPOND TO. BIAS HAS BEEN SHOWN IN IN THE
FINDINGS DOCUMENTED THROUGH PUBLIC INFORMATION REQUESTS.
THE PLANNING STAFF REQUESTED AT&T TO HELP DRAFT THE FINDINGS
THAT WERE ULTIMATELY APPROVED BY THE COMMISSION.
THIS COLLABORATION GAVE AT&T ADVANTAGES THAT RESIDENTS WERE
DENIED. >> THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FALLS SQUARELY IN SECTION 3O3 STANDARD
REQUIRING PROJECTS TO BE NECESSARY OR DESIRABLE FOR
AND COMPATIBLE WITH THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
THIS MASSIVE TEN STOREY TOWER ON THE BOUNDARY OF OPEN SPACE
PARKS SURROUNDED BY RH ONE RESIDENTIAL ZONING DOES NOT
MEET THAT TEST AND AT&T PREFERENCES FOR NECESSARY
AND DESIRABILITY SHOULD NOT BE TAKEN INTO CONSIDERATION.
>> AN OVERWHELMING 83 LETTERS WERE SENT TO THE PLANNING
COMMISSION EXPRESSING SUBSTANTIAL SPECIFIC ESTHETIC
AND SAFETY CONCERNS THAT DEMONSTRATE THAT DEMONSTRATE
THAT IT'S NOT DESIRABLE OR NECESSARY.
FOR EXAMPLE, RESIDENTS WROTE THE VIEW OF THE TREES COMFORTED
ME DURING CHEMOTHERAPY MY KIDS PLAY CHRISTOPHER PARK AND I
WANT THEM IN NATURE NOT DOMINATED BY AN INDUSTRIAL
TOWER. >> I MOVED HERE FOR THE OPEN
OPEN SKY PRESERVED BY UNDERGROUND WIRES AND WATCHING
A RED TAILED HAWK SITTING ON THE POLICE ACADEMY FENCE IS
MAGICAL. >> SINCE SEPTEMBER ANOTHER 75
COMMENTS WERE SUBMITTED WHICH INCLUDE BROWN.
>> THESE ARE EXAMPLES BROWN PAINT WON'T CAMOUFLAGE A
STRUCTURAL TOWER 20FT ABOVE THE TREE LINE OR A 700 CUBIC FOOT
ANTENNA ATOP THE TREE CANOPY ARRAY IS UNACCEPTABLE WHETHER
IT'S PAINTED BROWN OR BLUE AND THE NEWLY ANNOUNCED STREET
LEVEL TRANSFORMER WILL BE VISIBLE AND NOISY CONTRADICT
THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S FINDINGS FROM SEPTEMBER 25TH
THAT ALL EQUIPMENT WOULD BE BEHIND THE POLICE ACADEMY
AND NOT VISIBLE FROM THE PUBLIC STREET.
>> IT'S NOT COMPATIBLE WITH THE NATURE OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
DIAMOND HEIGHTS WAS DESIGNED IN THE 60S BY FAMOUS MODERNIST
ARCHITECTS TO PRESERVE VIEWS OF THE PARK AND OPEN SKY A TEN
STORY STRUCTURE 20FT ABOVE THE TREES IN OPEN SPACE SURROUNDS
SURROUNDED BY RH ONE ZONING OF MAXIMUM FOUR STOREYS VIOLATES
THE CHARACTER AS WELL AS THE GENERAL PLANS GOAL OF
PRESERVING OPEN SPACE AND PROTECTING PARKS FROM
DEVELOPMENT. >> OUR PARK OUR PARKS ARE FOCAL
GATHERING PLACE WHERE FAMILIES SEEK NATURE EXPERIENCES NOT
INDUSTRIAL STRUCTURES. IT ALSO VIOLATES THE CITYWIDE
BIODIVERSITY POLICY BY ENDANGERING WILDLIFE IN OUR
FORESTS AND GLEN CANYON SCIENTIFIC LITERATURE DOCUMENTS
BIRD DEATHS FROM TOWER COLLISIONS BOTH PLANNING
AND AT&T CLAIM THAT ANIMALS DON'T MOVE AROUND MORE THAN
200FT. >> EVEN A FIVE YEAR OLD WOULD
DISPUTE THAT FURTHER. >> THE GENERAL PLAN CALLS FOR
THE POLICE ACADEMY TO BE MOVED AND CENTRALIZED.
>> CENTRALIZED RESEARCH SHOWS PROPERTY VALUES DECLINE NEAR
ANTENNAS THAT WILL THAT WILL AFFECT THE POLICE ACADEMY'S
PROPERTY VALUE AS WELL AS OURS. >> IN A MEETING SUPERVISOR
MANAGEMENT ASKS WHETHER WHETHER AT&T WOULD COMPROMISE ON SIZE,
ALTERNATIVE NETWORKS OR LOCATION.
>> THEY REFUSED, STATING THIS PROJECT IS NECESSARY FOR OUR
BUSINESS GOALS. >> THE STATEMENT MATCHES AT&T
HEADQUARTERS COMMENTS IN DECEMBER OF 2025 ON FCC
REGULATIONS PROPOSING TO ELIMINATE ALL LOCAL CONTROL
WHEREIN THEY SAID WE WE WE SUPPORT THE PROPOSED
REGULATIONS THEY WILL ALLOW US TO DENSIFY OUR MACRO TO OUR
NETWORK AND ADVANCE OUR GOALS. AT&T IN THAT MEETING WITH
SUPERVISOR MANAGEMENT ALSO REFUSED TO AGREE NOT TO ADD A
SECOND LETTER LEVEL OF BULKY ANTENNAS.
>> AT&T MISLED THE FOR THE SEVEN PLANNING COMMISSIONERS
AND CONVINCE THEM THAT THIS TOWER WAS NECESSARY FOR SAFETY
SPECIFICALLY FOR FIRSTNET SAFETY FIRSTNET EMERGENCY
COMMUNICATIONS ARE USED ONLY BY FIRST RESPONDERS RIGHT NOW
FIRSTNET IS THE COMMUNICATION USED BY ICE AND AT&T WAS GIVEN
ADDITIONAL FUNDS TO TRACK UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS WITH
IT. WE DO NOT NEED FIRSTNET IN SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE CHIEF CHRISMAN AND INGLESIDE CAPTAIN NEW BECK
STATED AT AN OCTOBER 25TH COMMUNITY MEETING THAT FIRSTNET
IS OPTIONAL. IT'S NOT REQUIRED FOR OUR FIRST
RESPONDERS. >> A DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
SERVICES MANAGER SAID SHE DIDN'T EVEN KNOW WHAT FIRSTNET
WAS. AT&T REQUESTED SUPPORT LETTERS
FROM THE FIRE CHIEF INTERIM POLICE CHIEF YEP AND SHERIFF
MIYAMOTO AND PROVIDED EACH DRAFT LETTER.
FIRE CHIEF CRISPIN DECLINED TO SEND A LETTER.
CHIEF YIP DIDN'T RESPOND AND DIDN'T SEND ONE.
ONLY ELECTED SUPERVISOR MIYAMOTO SENT A LETTER DRAFTED
BY AT&T. >> AT&T ALSO MEDLOCK MISLED THE
COMMISSION ABOUT 911 SERVICES. >> CHIEF CHRISMAN AND AND
CAPTAIN NEW BACK CONFIRMED TO US THAT 911 CALLS FROM ANY
CARRIER REACH THE NEAREST TOWER AT&T TOWER DOESN'T CHANGE 911
ACCESS EVERYONE ALREADY HAS IT .
>> MOST IMPORTANTLY A GIANT MACRO TOWER ISN'T REQUIRED TO
STRENGTHEN SIGNAL STRENGTH AND IN SPECIFIC AREAS IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD, VERIZON AND T-MOBILE USE UNKNOWN
INTRUSIVE SMALL CELL NETWORKS THROUGHOUT THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> AT&T REFUSED TO REFUSE TO CONSIDER THESE BECAUSE THEIR
BUSINESS PLAN IS TO REACH FAR BEYOND OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
PLANNING APPROVED THIS LOCATION IS PREFERENCE WANTED THE CITY'S
WIRELESS SITING GUIDELINES PREFERENCE ONE IS FOR
FACILITIES MOUNTED ON PUBLIC STRUCTURES, FIRE STATIONS,
UTILITY STRUCTURES, COMMUNITY FACILITIES.
THIS MACRO TOWER IS NOT MOUNTED ON AN EXISTING STRUCTURE.
IT'S A NEW FREE STANDING TEN STORY FOOT MACRO TOWER IN A LOT
ZONED FOR FOUR PUBLIC BUT IT'S SURROUNDED BY RESIDENTIAL,
RESIDENTIAL AND BORDERING PARKS .
THEREFORE IT SHOULD BE CLASSIFIED AS PREFERENCE SIX OR
PREFERENCE SEVEN PREFERENCE SIX IS LIMITED PREFERENCE SEVEN IS
A DISFAVORED LOCATION SPECIFICALLY FOR RESIDENTIAL
NEIGHBORHOODS AND PARKS. THIS MISCLASSIFICATION ALLOWED
THE PROJECT TO BYPASS HEIGHTENED SCRUTINY REQUIRED
FOR NEW GROUND MOUNTED INSTALLATIONS IN RESIDENTIAL
AREAS AND NATURAL AREAS. THIS APPEAL, IF DENIED, SETS A
DANGEROUS PRECEDENT FOR TOWERS THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
THE SECRET CLASS THREE EXEMPTION IS IMPROPER.
THIS IS NOT A SMALL STRUCTURE PLANNING RELIED ON INACCURATE
ARTICULATION THAT DOESN'T MATCH THE STATUTORY TEST.
>> THE PROJECT ALSO TRIGGERED EXEMPTIONS INCLUDING FIRE
HAZARDS, HISTORIC NEIGHBORHOOD STATUS AND THREATS TO
BIOLOGICAL SERVICES. AT&T MADE SIGNIFICANT
MATERIAL CHANGES AFTER THE PLANNING COMMISSION APPROVAL.
THEIR LATE FEBRUARY 2ND SUBMISSION REVEALS DRAWINGS
LABELED FUTURE ANTENNAS SECOND LAYER.
>> THE SECOND LAYER WAS NOT APPROVED BY THE COMMISSION.
IF ONE LAYER THAT THEY'VE PROPOSED IS ENOUGH TO COVER THE
CURRENTLY WEAK SIGNALS, WHY PLAN FOR TWO?
>> BECAUSE AT&T WILL GENERATE FUNDING FROM RENTAL AGREEMENTS
ON THE SECOND LAYER. ADDITIONALLY THEY EXPAND IT
WOULD EXPAND COVERAGE BEYOND OUR NEIGHBOR AND LET THEM
BETTER COMPETE WITH CABLE PROVIDERS.
>> ON JANUARY 12TH AT&T NOTIFIED OUR ASSOCIATION OF A
NEW NEW NOISY TRANSFORMER PLAN FOUR IN FRONT OF THE PLACE
ACADEMY. WE LIKE TO LISTEN TO THE BIRDS
IN THE PARK BUT NOW THERE'LL BE A NOISY TRANSFORMER.
>> THIS ADDITION CONTRADICTS BOTH THE SEAWAY AND SECRET
FINDINGS. WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?
>> YOU HAVE 28 SECONDS LEFT. OKAY, I'LL SAY THAT THE PROJECT
IS NOT COMPATIBLE WITH THE PLANNING CODE OR GENERAL PLAN.
IT WILL HAVE ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT AND IT WILL NOT
CONTRIBUTE TO NEIGHBORHOOD CHARACTER STABILITY.
IT DOES NOT IT CONSTITUTES A DEVELOPED DEVELOPMENT
BENEFICIAL DEVELOPMENT ONLY FOR AT&T BUSINESS GOALS, NOT OUR
COMMUNITY. WE URGE YOU TO UPHOLD THESE
APPEALS AND PROTECT OUR NEIGHBORHOOD AND OTHER
NEIGHBORHOODS FROM THIS UNNECESSARY INCOMPATIBLE
PROJECT. >> THANK.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. DO YOU WANT ME TO CAUTION THE
AUDIENCE THAT WE DON'T ACTUALLY HAVE APPLAUSE, MR. PRESIDENT?
>> ALL RIGHT. SO WE HAVE RULES IN THE CHAMBER
THAT WE'RE NOT SUPPOSED TO APPLAUD ALTHOUGH OKAY, BUT BUT
VISUAL MANIFESTATIONS OF APPROVAL ARE OUR OKAY.
THERE WE GO. THE CLERK HAS DEMONSTRATED.
>> ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, I DO NOT HAVE ANY QUESTIONS FOR THE
APPELLANT AT THIS TIME ALTHOUGH I MAY LATER.
AND SO SEEING IT LOOKS LIKE NO ONE ELSE DOES EITHER.
AND SO MADAM CLERK, LET'S OPEN UP PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPEAL. IF FOLKS COULD LINE UP OVER ON
YOUR RIGHT OUR LEFT OUR CLERK WILL TAKE US THROUGH PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
YOU'LL FIRST HEAR THE SOFT BELL THAT WILL LET YOU KNOW TO WRAP
UP YOUR COMMENTS AS YOU'LL HAVE 30S AND ONCE THE SECOND TIMER
DOES RING I DO APOLOGIZE IF I INTERRUPT YOU BUT PLEASE TRY TO
KEEP YOUR COMMENTS TO TWO MINUTES.
>> WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER.
THANK YOU FOR HAVING ME. AND GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS DANIEL SHERAK AND I AM PRESIDENT OF THE DAMON
HEIGHTS COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION. I'D LIKE TO BE CLEAR THIS
APPEAL IS NOT ABOUT A PROHIBITION OF SERVICE.
IT'S ABOUT HOW THAT SERVICE IS DELIVERED.
A LARGE MONOPOLE COVERED IN ANTENNAS ISN'T THE ONLY WAY
TO PROVIDE COVERAGE BUT IT IS THE MOST VISUALLY
AND ENVIRONMENTALLY INTRUSIVE OPTION.
IT SHOULD NOT BE ALLOWED. THERE ARE VIABLE ALTERNATIVES
THAT WOULD EASILY ALLOW AT&T TO EXPAND ITS BUSINESS GOALS WHILE
ALSO DELIVERING ON THE NEEDS AND RIGHTS OF DIAMOND HEIGHTS
RESIDENTS. HERE ARE TWO SIMPLE EXAMPLES.
FIRST, DISTRIBUTED ANTENNA SYSTEMS KNOWN AS DAS DAS USES
MULTIPLE SMALLER TOWERS WITH SMALLER ANTENNAS EITHER MOUNTED
ON EXISTING INFRASTRUCTURE OR SMALL PURPOSE BUILT TOWERS TO
PROVIDE AREA WIDE COVERAGE INSTEAD OF CONCENTRATING
MASSIVE IMPACTS IN A SINGLE LOCATION.
DAS DISTRIBUTES SERVICE DISCREETLY AND IS PERFECT FOR
DENSE AND HILLY NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE OURS.
THE IMPACT OF SMALL TOWERS ON THE COMMUNITY WOULD BE MINOR.
A SECOND OPTION ARE JUST SMALL ANTENNA CELLS LOCATED ON
EXISTING UTILITY POLES OR STREET LIGHT POSTS.
THESE FACILITIES ARE COMPACT, LOW PROFILE AND DESIGNED
SPECIFICALLY TO AVOID THE NEED FOR GIANT TOWERS.
THEY'RE LITERALLY EVERYWHERE IN SAN FRANCISCO RIGHT NOW
AND VIRTUALLY NO ONE CARES ABOUT THEM.
SMALL CELLS ARE A SPECTACULAR SOLUTION NOT JUST FOR DIMOND
HEIGHTS BUT ANY RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN FRANCISCO.
COMMUNITY IMPACT IS EXTREMELY LOW BUT STILL IT UNLOCKS
LUCRATIVE BUSINESS OPPORTUNITIES FOR AT&T
AND OTHER WIRELESS CARRIERS. MOREOVER, THEY AVOID THE
HEADACHE OF COMMUNITY OPPOSITION AND APPEALS AGAINST
MONOPOLES THAT EVERY SINGLE DISTRICT SUPERVISOR IN THIS
ROOM IS GOING TO HAVE TO CONTEND WITH IN THEIR OWN
DISTRICTS. IF AT&T IS ABLE TO BUILD THEIR
TOWER IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS THERE ARE ALTERNATIVES THAT ARE
TECHNICALLY FEASIBLE, ECONOMICALLY VIABLE, LEGALLY
PERMISSIBLE AND ACTIVE. TODAY YOU HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY
TO DRIVE INNOVATIVE NEARLY INVISIBLE SOLUTIONS HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND SET THE TONE FOR DECADES TO COME.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, DANIEL SHERK FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
I'M BETSY EDDY, FORMER PRESIDENT OF THE DIAMOND
HEIGHTS COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION AND I'M SPEAKING ON THE FIRE
DANGER THAT IS IMPLICIT IN THIS PROPOSED CELL PHONE TOWER.
AT&T IS LATE SUBMITTAL DISPARAGES SUSAN FOSTER BY
SAYING SHE PROVIDES NO EVIDENCE THAT SHE IS A FIRE EXPERT.
MISS FOSTER HAS BEEN A NOTED FIRE CONSULTANT FOR 20 YEARS
RECENTLY. >> SHE WROTE THE NEW FIRE
REGULATIONS FOR LOS ANGELES AFTER THE PALISADES FIRE.
>> AT&T SUBMITTED OTHER INACCURACIES.
>> FIRE INSPECTOR ALDRIDGE STATES THAT MISS FOSTER'S
DESCRIPTION OF FIRES QUOTE HIGH WINDS AND NEARBY RECEPTIVE
CITATION WERE THE CONTRIBUTING FIRES IN THOSE FIRES THAT SHE
DESCRIBED, BOTH OF WHICH OCCURRED IN CONDITIONS THAT DO
NOT OCCUR IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> MR. ALDRIDGE IS UNFAMILIAR
WITH THE PROPOSED SITE WHERE WINDS ARE REGULARLY 20 TO 40MPH
AND REACH 80 MILES PER HOUR IN FIERCE STORMS.
>> THE PROPOSED LOCATION WOULD SIT VERY CLOSE TO A GROVE OF
COMBUSTIBLE EUCALYPTUS TREE. >> AT&T STATES AS WELL A FIRE
INVOLVING A CELL TOWER IS NOT A FREQUENT OR REQUESTED
OCCURRENCE. >> AS THE FOUNDER OF RESILIENT
DIAMOND HEIGHTS THAT HAS BEEN WORKING FOR 18 YEARS TO PREPARE
DIAMOND HEIGHTS FOR ALL TYPES OF EMERGENCIES, I STRONGLY
DISAGREE. >> IN YOUR BOARD PACKET THERE
IS A LINK THAT SHOWS MULTIPLE FIRES IN CALIFORNIA AND ACROSS
UNITED STATES THAT WERE STARTED IN TELECOM COMMUNITIES.
>> WE ARE ALREADY FEARFUL OF A FIRE IN GLEN CANYON PARK BY
FIREWORKS AND CIGARET CIGARET OR AN UNHOUSED PERSON'S CAMPING
FIRE. >> AND WE FEEL THAT A OH A
BRANCH COULD I THANK YOU BETSY EDDY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
OKAY. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> MY NAME IS HOLLY NEWMARK. I'M READING THIS LETTER FROM
EVELYN ROSE, FOUNDER OF GLEN PARK NEIGHBORHOOD'S HISTORY
PROJECT WHO COULD NOT BE HERE TODAY.
DEAR HONORABLE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
DIAMOND HEIGHTS AMIDST 20TH CENTURY REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT
WAS INTENTIONALLY DESIGNED BY LANDSCAPE ARCHITECT VERNON
DEMERS. WITH A LOW PROFILE FOOTPRINT
THAT IS ESTHETICALLY SYNCHRONIZED WITH THE
SURROUNDING LANDSCAPE, THE 360 DEGREE VISIBILITY OF THE AT&T
100 AND FOUR FOOT MACRO TOWER IS EXPECTED TO HAVE A NEGATIVE
IMPACT ON THE INTENTIONAL LOW PROFILE OF CONTOURS AND UNIQUE
HISTORY OF DIAMOND HEIGHTS. YET AT&T AND THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT HAVE FAILED TO ADDRESS WHAT IMPACT
INSTALLATION WILL HAVE ON THE HISTORIC BUILT ENVIRONMENT.
>> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S OWN CITYWIDE CULTURAL RESOURCES
SURVEY IS CURRENTLY IDENTIFYING SITES THAT ARE ELIGIBLE FOR THE
ARTICLE TEN LANDMARKS WORK PROGRAM AND OTHER HISTORIC
PRESERVATION PROTECTIONS AND INCENTIVES.
DIAMOND HEIGHTS RESIDENTS DESERVE EQUITABLE OPPORTUNITY
TO ACCESS ARTICLE TEN PROTECTIONS AND OTHER BENEFITS.
INSTALLATION OF THE AT&T MACRO TELECOMMUNICATIONS TOWER HAS
POTENTIAL TO EXCLUDE DIAMOND HEIGHTS RESIDENT FROM ANY
FUTURE CONSIDERATION. I THEREFORE STRONGLY URGE THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO OVERTURN THIS SECRET EXEMPTION
FOR AT&T 100 FOOT MACRO TOWER TO ENABLE A PROPER EVALUATION
OF THE POTENTIAL IMPACT ON THE HISTORICAL AND ACTIVE GRITTY OF
DIAMOND HEIGHTS. >> SINCERELY ALAN ROSE.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU EVELYN NEWMARK FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS KEVIN O'CONNOR AND I
LIVE IN MIRA LOMA PARK, A NEIGHBORHOOD OF 2200 HOMES
LOCATED ALONG MT. DAVIDSON ON THE WEST SIDE OF GLEN CANYON
JUST ACROSS FROM THE DIAMOND HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD.
I'M SPEAKING TODAY ON BEHALF OF THE MERRILL LYNCH PARK
IMPROVEMENT CLUB, A NONPROFIT SERVING OUR NEIGHBORHOOD SINCE
1934. AND FOR NEARLY 90 YEARS WE'VE
WORKED CLOSELY WITH THE CITY AGENCIES ON PLANNING, PUBLIC
SAFETY, RESILIENCE AND COMMUNITY WELL-BEING.
WE SUPPORT THE APPEALS OF BOTH THE SECRET EXCEPTION AND THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION. THIS MASSIVE TOWER DOES NOT
MEET SECRET GUIDELINES NOR PLANNING'S SITING GUIDELINES.
>> THIS IS THE FIRST MASSIVE TOWER EXEMPTED BY PLANNING IN A
RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD BORDERING TWO PARKS.
>> THIS APPROVAL SETS A DANGEROUS PRECEDENT FOR MACRO
TOWERS TO PROLIFERATE IN RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS
CITYWIDE. >> AT&T SAYS THIS MACRO TOWER
IS NECESSARY, DESIRABLE AND COMPATIBLE WITH THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> WE DISAGREE.
ALLOWING THE EXEMPTION SETS A DANGEROUS PRECEDENT FOR ALL
NEIGHBORHOODS. >> THIS MASSIVE TOWER IS NOT A
SMALL ADDITION TO AN EXISTING STRUCTURE.
IT'S 12 BULKY ANTENNAS TOWERING 20FT ABOVE TREES ATOP A 104
FOOT POLE VISIBLE THROUGHOUT THE NEIGHBORHOOD OVERLOOKING
CHRISTOPHER PARK AND GLEN CANYON.
THERE ARE NO FREESTANDING TOWERS OF THIS HEIGHT EXISTING
IN RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS NEXT TO PARKS.
>> THE PLANNING COMMISSION APPROVED THIS TOWER FOR
PUBLICLY USE STRUCTURES LIKE POLICE STATIONS AND UTILITY
BUILDINGS. >> HOWEVER, THIS NEW TOWER IS
BEHIND THE POLICE ACADEMY. >> MASSIVE TOWERS DON'T BELONG
ADJACENT TO PARKS, PLAYGROUNDS AND HOMES.
WE URGE THE BOARD TO GRANT THE SQUARE APPEAL AND REQUIRE A
FULL ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW AND GRANT THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION APPEAL. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION. THANK YOU KEVIN O'CONNOR FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
I'M DEBORAH MURPHY, PRESIDENT OF THE COALITION FOR SAN
FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOODS. >> AND IT'S A TOUGH ACT TO
FOLLOW WITH KATHARINE'S WONDERFUL SPEECH.
MY ONLY CRITICISM IS SHE COVERED ALL THE POINTS I WANTED
TO MAKE BUT I'M GOING TO EMPHASIZE A FEW THINGS.
>> THERE'S KEY SAFETY ISSUES IN THIS LOCATION.
THE FIRE RISK SEISMIC LANDSLIDE RISK, NATURAL RESOURCES THE
APPROVAL MADE BASED ON MISLEADING CLAIMS.
FOR THESE REASONS THIS PROJECT DOES NOT QUALIFY FOR A SECRET
EXEMPTION. >> THE TOWER WOULD ONLY HELP
AT&T CUSTOMERS. T-MOBILE AND VERIZON HAVE GOOD
CELL PHONE COVERAGE IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS WITHOUT THE TEN STORY
TOWERS. AT&T REFUSED TO CONSIDER OTHER
ALTERNATIVES. I DON'T GIVE IN TO CORPORATE
GREED AND LET AT&T HAVE THIS TOWER.
I WAS AT THAT MEETING WHEN FIRE CHIEF CHRIS SMITH SAID THEY
DIDN'T NEED IT. >> SO PLEASE LISTEN TO YOUR
CONSTITUENTS. LOOK AT ALL THE PEOPLE WHO COME
OUT HERE ON A COLD RAINY DAY TO BECAUSE THEY'RE OPPOSED TO WHAT
AT&T WANTS TO DESTROY THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS VLADIMIR COSTA OF AND I'M A LONG TIME SAN
FRANCISCO RESIDENT. CAME HERE IN 2013 FOR THE JOB
AND STAYED FOR THE CITY THAT I NOW PROUDLY CALL MY HOME.
MY FAMILY PURCHASED THEIR FIRST HOUSE LAST YEAR AND DIAMOND
HEIGHTS ON AMBER DRIVE JUST A FEW FEET AWAY FROM THE PROPOSED
PROJECT SITE. THE PLACE SEEMED PERFECT TO
RAISE OUR KID IN. IT'S A LOT OF PARKS AROUND.
IT'S VERY SAFE. IT'S VERY QUIET NOW THE
PROPOSED PROJECT IF BUILD WILL HAVE A LONG LASTING EFFECT ON
INSURANCE COSTS, PROPERTY VALUES AND SAFETY.
I'M UNFORTUNATELY NO LONGER SURE THAT WOULD BE THE RIGHT
PLACE TO RAISE OUR KID IN MY COMMUNITY HAS BEEN VOICING
THEIR CONCERNS ABOUT THIS PROJECT VERY STRONGLY AND VERY
CONSISTENTLY. MORE THAN 80 LETTERS SUBMITTED
IN OPPOSITION TO THE PUBLIC COMMISSION MORE THAN 20 PEOPLE
STAYED IN LINE TO SPEAK THEIR HEARTS AGAINST THIS PROJECT
DURING THE PLANNING COMMISSION HEARING.
BUT WE WEREN'T HURT AND NOW WE'RE HERE TODAY OUR LAST
CHANCE TO SPEAK OUR HEARTS IN FRONT OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. WE'RE HOPING YOU HEAR US
AND SUPPORT OUR APPEAL AND REQUIRE CORPORATIONS TO
BUILD SOMETHING THAT MAKES OUR PARKS NICER NOT WORSE.
WE ALL LIVE IN A CITY THAT'S VERY EXPENSIVE.
SAN FRANCISCO IS PRICEY. EVERYBODY KNOWS THAT WE ALL
PAID THE PREMIUM FOR THAT. WHY DON'T WE REQUIRE
CORPORATIONS TO DO THE SAME AND BUILD SOMETHING THAT'S NOT
A GIANT CORDONED OFF MONOPOLE IN FRONT OF OUR PARKS BUT DO
SOMETHING THAT MAKES IT NICER. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THINKS YOU WILL SPEAK. >> THANK YOU.
VLADIMIR COSTA CALL FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS TIM WILFRED. I'M A 40 YEAR RESIDENT OF
DIMOND HEIGHTS AND A FORMER TRUSTEE AT CITY COLLEGE OF SAN
FRANCISCO. I BELIEVE REJECTING OUR APPEAL
SETS A DANGEROUS PRECEDENT FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS ASSERTED I THINK MISTAKENLY
THAT THE THREE TOWERS APPROVED IN THIS LAST YEAR WITH A SECURE
EXEMPTION ARE COMPARABLE TO AND SET A PRECEDENT FOR THE
PLANNED ONE IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS. WE DON'T BELIEVE THEY DO.
THE FIRST EXAMPLE OF THE THREE IS A 40 FOOT TOWER TO BE
INSTALLED AT 1475 25TH STREET. IT'S SITED ON A HILLTOP
OVERLOOKING A LARGE INDUSTRIAL AREA BETWEEN HIGHWAYS 101
AND 280. NO TREES VERY FEW RESIDENTS
NEARBY. THE SECOND EXAMPLE THEY RAISE
IS A 60 FOOT TOWER ADJACENT TO THE ATHLETIC FIELDS AT THE WEST
END OF GOLDEN GATE PARK. NO HOMES NEARBY.
THE THIRD EXAMPLE OF OUR PRECEDENT THEY ASSERT IS A 90
FOOT TOWER IN THE PALACE OF FINE ARTS PARKING LOT WHICH IS
SURROUNDED BY WAREHOUSES AND HIGHWAY 101.
>> NONE OF THESE LOCATIONS MATCH 352 AMBER.
THE NEW TOWER AT OUR ON AMBER STREET WILL BE THE FIRST TEN
STOREY TOWER IN A RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD AND RIGHT ABOVE
TWO PARKS ONLY FOUR MAKRO TOWERS MAKRO TOWERS THIS SIZE
ARE TALLER. EXIST IN SAN FRANCISCO AT THIS
POINT. TWO ARE ATTACHED TO DOWNTOWN
BUILDINGS. ONE IS IN THE PRESIDIO SPORTS
BASEMENT PARKING LOT AND THE FOURTH IS AT THE BALBOA PARK
BART STATION. >> IF THESE APPEALS ARE DENIED,
THE NEW GIANT MAGNA TOWER WILL BE A PRECEDENT CITED WHEN AT&T
SEEKS APPROVAL FOR TOWERS IN OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS.
>> WE BRING IT TO OUR BENEFIT AND THOSE NEIGHBORS BENEFITS.
WE ASK THAT YOU ACCEPT OUR APPEALS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, TRUSTEE WILFRED FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS DR. CANDACE LOWE. I HAVE A PH.D. IN ECOLOGY
AND EVOLUTION. I'M ALSO A NATIVE SAN
FRANCISCAN CURRENTLY. I'M IN THE I'M LIVING IN THE
NOTORIOUS D FOR BUT I'M HERE AS AN ECOLOGIST AND I WANT TO TALK
ABOUT MY EXPERIENCE IN GLEN CANYON PARK AND THE IMPORTANCE
OF PRESERVING THAT ENTIRE AREA .
>> WHAT I WANT TO ADDRESS IS THE WHAT PLANNING THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND AT&T DID IN TERMS OF MEASURING THE
DISTANCE OF THE PROPOSED 104 FOOT TOWER TO THE MAPPED
HABITATS THAT ARE REALLY EFFECTIVELY AN INTACT ECOSYSTEM
BECAUSE IT'S PART OF OUR NATIVE SIGNIFICANT NATURAL AREAS OF
SAN FRANCISCO AND SHOULD BE WELL PROTECTED.
>> SO MY BASIC PROBLEM WITH THAT PREMISE AND THAT FACT IS
THAT THE ORGANISMS THAT YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT IN GLEN CANYON
ARE NOT CONSERVED TO A TWO DIMENSIONAL SPACE.
>> AND SO WHEN YOU MEASURE ON A MAP HUNDRED AND 50 FOOT SPACE
YOU'RE MEASURING A BOUNDARY THAT'S ON A PIECE OF PAPER
ESSENTIALLY. >> SO MY POINT IS THAT THAT
FACT IN ITSELF IS ON ITS FACE PROOF THAT WE NEED MORE
RESEARCH AND MORE ASSESSMENT BEFORE GOING FORWARD.
>> SO SO YEAH SO ESSENTIALLY I THINK IT IS A FALSE PREMISE TO
ASSERT THAT ANIMALS AND BIRDS IGNORE FENCES AND THEY MAY BE
TRAPPED BY THE FENCES BUT THEY'RE NOT IGNORING IT.
AND THEN WHAT IS BEING IGNORED IS ACTUALLY THE TOWER ITSELF
AND THE IMPACTS AND NEGATIVE IMPACTS OF THE TOWER.
IT'S GOING TO GO BEYOND THE FENCES SO IT'S NOT GOING TO
PROTECT THE THE COMMUNITY, THE NATURAL COMMUNITY THAT WE AIM
TO PROTECT. >> SO IN MY SCIENTIFIC OPINION,
THE STATEMENTS FROM THE PLANNING FROM PLANNING AND AT&T
ARE NOT CREDIBLE. THEIR RESPONSES DEMONSTRATE
EXACTLY WHY THIS EXEMPTION APPEAL MUST BE APPROVED AND A
FULL ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT IS REQUIRED.
>> THANK YOU DR. CANDACE LOWE. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. MY NAME IS MAGGIE HOPPY AND I'M
A LONG TIME RESIDENT ON DIAMOND STREET.
I'M SPEAKING TODAY ABOUT THE DANGER TO TREES AND GLEN PARK
FOR THE PROPOSED CELL TOWER LOCATION.
I WILL READ FROM MY WORDS AND THOSE SUBMITTED BY JOCELYN
COHEN, A QUALIFIED IAC CERTIFIED ARBORIST AND ARBOR
ECOLOGIST EPA CERTIFIED ESTHETIC PRUNER AND A TREE RISK
ASSESSMENT QUALIFIED CERTIFICATE IN PERSON.
>> THE LOCATION FOR THE PROPOSED MERCATO WAS SURROUNDED
BY TALL TREES THIS ONE HUNDRED FOOT TALL TOWER WILL WEIGH MANY
TONS AND WILL REQUIRE DIGGING MOST LIKELY BETWEEN 30 AND 90FT
TO FIND BEDROCK TO STABILIZE THE STRUCTURE.
DIGGING AND DRILLING TO THESE DEPTHS IS NOT ONLY NOT THE ONLY
CONCERN FOR THE TREES IT IS ADDITIONALLY HAZARDOUS TO THE
SURROUNDING LANDSCAPE WHICH WILL FOREVER BE DEVASTATED
IN OUR LIFETIME AND FOR HUNDREDS OF YEARS BEYOND HEAVY
EQUIPMENT USED IN ROOT PROTECTION ZONE IS A DEATH
SENTENCE TO TREES AND THE TRICKY THING ABOUT ROOT
DISTURBANCE IS THE EFFECTS DO NOT SOMETIMES SHOW UP FOR AS
LONG AS A DECADE AND BY THEN PEOPLE HAVE FORGOTTEN WHO WAS
RESPONSIBLE FOR THE LOSS OF A NATURAL ECOSYSTEM IN AN URBAN
AREA EVEN VIBRATION STRUCTURES FROM THE HIGH WINDS WHICH IS
UNKNOWN WHETHER EVENT IN GLEN PARK WILL DISTURB THE SOIL
AND THE TREE ROOT SYSTEMS. PUTTING A CELL TOWER AMID
SIGNIFICANT HABITAT AREA IS IRREVERSIBLE.
IRREVERSIBLE MISTAKE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU MAGGIE HOPPY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS LESLIE TATIANA. I'M A DISTRICT THREE RESIDENT.
I'M HERE TO ASK YOU TO IMAGINE WHAT SAN FRANCISCO WILL LOOK
LIKE IF THESE APPEALS ARE DENIED BECAUSE THE CONSEQUENCES
EXTEND FAR BEYOND 350 AMBER DRIVE AND DIAMOND HEIGHTS.
THIS WILL BE THE FIRST MACRO TOWER OF THIS HEIGHT AND MASS
IN A RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD BORDERING TWO PARKS AT&T
OPERATES ON PRESIDENT. WHEN THEY GET THIS APPROVAL FOR
A MAGICAL TOWER AT A RESIDENTIAL PARK BORDER USING
FLAWED ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW, THEY WILL REPLICATE THIS
CITYWIDE. LET ME BE SPECIFIC.
EDGE OF STERN GROVE OUR H ONE HOMES MOUNT DAVIDSON
RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS NATURAL AREA DESIGNATION
MCLAREN PARK BORDER NEAR VISITATION VALLEY RICHMOND
AND MARINA DISTRICTS ALONG GOLDEN GATE PARK'S EDGES.
EVERY SINGLE ONE BECOMES A LIKELY MACRO TOWER LOCATION
USING THE EXACT RATIONALE PLANNING USED HERE.
>> THIS ISN'T SPECULATION IT'S AT&T BUSINESS MODEL TO IDENTIFY
THEIR MACRO TERROR NETWORK. THEY PREFER CITY OWNED LAND
BECAUSE IT'S CHEAPER AND THEY'VE DISCOVERED PLANNING
WILL APPROVE RESIDENTIAL AND PARK BORDERS WITHOUT
SERIOUS SCRUTINY. >> THE SECRET VIOLATIONS HERE
ARE PARTICULARLY DANGEROUS AS PRESIDENT PLANNING APPROVED A
CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION FOR A STRUCTURE OF FIVE TIMES TALLER
THAN SURROUNDING HOMES. IGNORE RING MIGRATORY BIRD
COLLISIONS 24 SEVEN TRANSFORMER NOISE HEARD ACROSS THE STREET
AND CONDUCTING ZERO ALTERNATIVE ANALYSIS.
THAT SAME EXEMPTION CLAIM CAN NOW BE COPIED AND PASTED INTO
APPLICATIONS CITYWIDE. >> BY GRANTING THESE APPEALS
YOU STOP THIS CASCADE BEFORE IT STARTS.
REQUIRE PLANNING TO FOLLOW THE CITY'S WIRELESS SITTING
GUIDELINES. >> CONDUCT PROPER ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEWS AND DEMAND REAL ALTERNATIVES ANALYSIS.
>> PROTECT SAN FRANCISCO'S RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS
AND PARK BORDERS CITYWIDE. >> GRANT THE APPEALS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU, LESLIE TO DIA DE LA
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS JAY WAGNER.
AT&T CLAIMS THAT THERE'S NO PROOF THAT CELL TOWERS REDUCE
PROPERTY VALUES. >> BUT THE EVIDENCE IS CLEAR.
CALIFORNIA LAW RECOGNIZES CELL TOWERS AS A RISK.
THE CALIFORNIA ASSOCIATION OF REALTORS DISCLOSURE FORM LISTS
THEM AS NEIGHBORHOOD NUISANCES THAT SELLERS MUST REPORT.
STUDIES CONFIRM THIS IMPACT. A UNIVERSITY OF KENTUCKY STUDY
FOUND HOMES WITHIN 1000FT OF A TOWER SOLD FOR NEARLY 2% LESS
THAN A PARABLE PROPERTIES FARTHER AWAY.
A UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH ALABAMA STUDY OF OVER 23,000 HOME SALES
FOUND VALUES DROPPED 2.65% WITHIN 0.72KM AND 9.78% IF THE
TOWER WAS VISIBLE TO SELLER'S PROPERTY.
FEDERAL AUTHORITIES TREAT TOWERS AS HAZARDS.
>> HUD REQUIRES APPRAISERS TO FLAG NEARBY PROPERTIES, REPORT
ON MARKETABILITY AND CHECK THE TOWERS FALL DISTANCE.
GOVERNMENT AGENCIES INCLUDING MARYLAND'S PROPERTY TAX
ASSESSMENT APPEAL BOARD HAVE FORMALLY REDUCED HOME VALUES
DUE TO NEARBY TOWERS. >> FOR NEARBY NEIGHBORS THIS
TOWER THREATENS REAL FINANCIAL HARM.
HOMES WILL BE HARDER TO SELL AND WORTHLESS WHILE AT&T
PROFITS. THE HOMEOWNERS LOSE EQUITY.
>> ALSO I WANTED IT IF YOU COULD PLEASE JUST IMAGINE
WAKING UP IN THE MORNING AND GO IN YOUR WINDOW AND LOOKING
ACROSS THE STREET AND SEEING THIS 100 FOOT EYESORE AND LOOK
AND IT'S LOOKING BACK AT YOU AND I DON'T THINK IT'S A GOOD
FEELING AND I HOPE YOU REMEMBER THAT WHEN YOU VOTE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, JILL WAGNER FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
>> MY NAME IS BETTY PESKIN AND I'VE CALLED DIAMOND HEIGHTS
MY HOME WHERE I SERVE ON THE BOARD OF THE COMMUNITY
ASSOCIATION. 34 YEARS AGO MY SPOUSE AND I
MOVED FROM NEUE VALLEY TO THE 800 BLOCK OF DUNCAN STREET JUST
ONE BLOCK FROM THIS PROPOSED TOWER BECAUSE WE WERE SEEKING
MORE OPEN SPACE PUBLIC PARKS AND THE NATURAL BEAUTY OF GLEN
CANYON PARK HEIGHTS. AS YOU KNOW, IS ALSO KNOWN FOR
ITS STRONG PERSISTENT WINDS WHICH MAKE FIRE SAFETY A
CRITICAL CONCERN. >> INTRODUCING A 104 FOOT TOWER
AND ITS FUEL TANKS TO THE EDGE OF A WOODED PARK RAISES SERIOUS
SAFETY RISKS RISKS THAT SHOULD NOT BE IGNORED.
AS A RETIRED SCHOOLTEACHER WITH A 44 YEAR CAREER, HOME
OWNERSHIP WAS A HARD EARNED DREAM.
>> AFTER MORE THAN 20 YEARS OF RENTING IN NOVI VALLEY, WE WERE
ABLE TO PURCHASE A HOME. AND LIKE MANY OTHER RESIDENTS
WE ARE STILL PAYING FOR IT. THE POSSIBILITY THAT THIS TOWER
BUILT AS PROPOSED COULD SIGNIFICANTLY LEE ERODE THE
VALUE OF OUR HOME, THREATENS OUR FINANCIAL SECURITY
AND RETIREMENT STABILITY. EACH OF YOU HAS RECEIVED
LETTERS FROM SIX LICENSED REAL ESTATE PROFESSIONALS WHO HAVE
ALL WARNED OF THE FINANCIAL CONSEQUENCES TO THE VALUE OF
NEARBY HOMES. ALL OF THEM HAVE OPPOSED THIS
TOWER. >> ONE REALTOR WITH 50 YEARS OF
EXPERIENCE INSIDE STATES THAT HOMES NEAR CELL TOWERS CAN LOSE
UP TO 10% OF THEIR VALUE WHILE THE OTHERS HAVE STATED THEY
COULD LOSE BETWEEN 8 AND 12%. PEOPLE DON'T WANT TO LIVE NEAR
THEM BY PLACING THAT HUGE MACRO TOWER IN A RESIDENTIAL VIEW CAR
CORRIDOR WITH SIGNAL A SHIFT AWAY FROM THE THOUGHTFUL
PLANNING AND ENVIRONMENTAL SENSITIVITY THAT MAKES DIAMOND
HEIGHTS SO LIVABLE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU BETTY PASKIN FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME'S SHAYNA. I WAS BORN AND RAISED IN THE
INNER SUNSET AND NOW LIVE IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS.
I ASK YOU TO IMAGINE THIS DECISION NOT AS A POLICY
QUESTION BUT AS A PERSONAL ONE. IMAGINE A TEN STOREY INDUSTRIAL
TOWER RISING BESIDE YOUR HOME ABOVE YOUR TREES, YOUR VIEWS
AND THE PLACE WHERE YOUR FAMILY FEELS SAFE.
>> THIS IS WHAT'S BEING PROPOSED FOR OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
DIAMOND HEIGHTS IS A QUIET, NATURE FILLED RESIDENTIAL
COMMUNITY. >> THE MONOPOLE WOULD BE PLACED
IN A WINDY GRASSY CANYON IN A WILDFIRE PRONE IN SIZE A
SEISMIC ACTIVE AREA WITH A DIESEL FUEL TANK AT ITS BASE.
THAT COMBINATION RAISES REAL SAFETY CONCERNS FOR THE
FAMILIES AND SENIORS THAT LIVE NEARBY.
>> THIS PROJECT WOULD ALSO SIGNIFICANTLY IMPACT PROPERTY
VALUES FOR MANY OF US. OUR HOMES REPRESENT OUR LIFE
SAVINGS AN INDUSTRIAL TOWER OF THIS SCALE NEXT TO RESIDENTIAL
HOMES. >> WOULD INEVITABLY REDUCE HOME
VALUES AND MAKE IT HARDER FOR FAMILIES TO SELL OR INVEST
IN THEIR FUTURE. WE ARE NOT OPPOSED TO
CONNECTIVITY. WE'RE ASKING FOR A RESPONSIBLE
PLACEMENT AND CONSIDERATION OF LESS HARMFUL ALTERNATIVES.
PLEASE UPHOLD THE APPEAL AND DON'T ALLOW A PROJECT
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD THAT YOU WOULD NEVER ACCEPT IN YOUR OWN.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND SERVICE.
THANK YOU SHANA FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ROBERT OREN.
I'M A 50 YEAR RESIDENT OF SAN FRANCISCO AND HAVE RESIDED AT
266 AMBER DRIVE FOR THE PAST 20 YEARS.
I URGE YOU TO GRANT BOTH APPEALS.
DENYING THEM SETS A DANGEROUS PRECEDENT BY ALLOWING THE
PLANNING COMMISSION TO RELY ON FINDINGS SHAPED BY AT&T WITHOUT
THE COMMUNITY INPUT REQUIRED UNDER SAN FRANCISCO'S 2011
PERSONAL WIRELESS SERVICE FACILITY ORDINANCE.
UPHELD BY THE CALIFORNIA SUPREME COURT.
AT&T JUSTIFIED THIS TOWER BY INVOKING EMERGENCY
COMMUNICATIONS AND FIRST NET YET FIRSTNET IS CURRENTLY USED
BY ICE ICE THROUGH AN AT&T CONTRACT.
AND ALL FOUR COMMISSIONERS WHO VOTED IN FAVOR RELIED ON THIS
CLAIM WHILE IGNORING THREE CRITICAL FACTS.
A TOWER OF THIS SIZE IS NOT NECESSARY TO IMPROVE AT&T
COVERAGE. BOOSTERS ARE AVAILABLE FOR
FIRSTNET AND THE FIRE CHIEF AND INGLESIDE CAPTAIN CONFIRMED
THAT FIRSTNET IS OPTIONAL AND THAT 911 CALLS CONNECT TO
THE NEAREST CARRIER REGARDLESS ,THIS APPROVAL IS BASED ON
FLAWED ANALYSIS THAT AT&T CAN NOW REPLICATE CITYWIDE PLANNING
IN AT&T POINT TO SIMILAR TOWERS BUT NONE ARE LOCATED WITHIN
RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS AND NO APPROVED PARK TOWERS
REACH 100FT NEAR HOMES. PLANNING IMPROPERLY USED A
CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION TO BYPASS SECURE DESPITE CLEAR
ENVIRONMENTAL AND WILDFIRE RISKS IN A WILDFIRE URBAN
INTERFACE AREA. THIS APPROVAL SETS NO
MEANINGFUL LIMITS AND AT&T CAN EXPAND WITH MINIMAL OVERSIGHT
HARMING NEIGHBORHOOD CHARACTER AND EXPOSING THE NEARBY SNOWY
VALLEY NURSERY SCHOOL TO ROUTINE DIESEL GENERATOR
TESTING. GRANTING THESE APPEALS AFFIRMS
SAN FRANCISCO'S LAWS AND ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTIONS
LESS INTRUSIVE ALTERNATIVES EXIST.
>> OTHER CARRIERS DO NOT REQUIRE MACRO TOWERS HERE.
PLEASE PLEASE STOP A PRECEDENT THAT TURNS RESIDENTIAL PARK
EDGES INTO INDUSTRIAL ZONES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, ROBERT ORIN FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS GERALD PORTER AND I
LIVE AT 266 EMBER. I'D LIKE TO URGE YOU TO GRANT
BOTH APPEALS BECAUSE THIS IS NOT JUST ABOUT ONE TOWER.
RATHER IT'S ABOUT WHETHER SAN FRANCISCO KEEPS ANY LEGAL
AUTHORITY TO GUIDE WHERE THE WIRELESS INFRASTRUCTURE GOES
INTO RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS AND ALONG PARK BORDERS.
RIGHT NOW THE CITY HAS CLEAR LEGAL TOOLS.
OUR WIRELESS SITING GUIDELINES DESIGNATE ARE EACH ONE AREAS AS
DISAVOWED LOCATIONS. SEQUA REQUIRES ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW AND PROJECTS MAY HAVE IMPACTS PLANNING CODE SECTION
3O2 REQUIRES FINDINGS THAT PROJECTS WILL NOT HARM THE
NEIGHBORHOOD CHARACTER PUBLIC HEALTH ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY
AND SPECIFICALLY PROTECTS NATURE.
IF THESE APPEALS ARE DENIED YOU VALIDATE PLANNING'S DECISION TO
IGNORE THE PROTECTIONS. AT&T WILL CITE THIS APPROVAL
IN FUTURE CASES ARGUING THAT THE BOARD ALREADY DETERMINED
THAT EACH ONE NEIGHBORHOODS AND PARK EDGES ARE NOT
DISFAVORED AND EXEMPTIONS ARE APPROPRIATE REGARDLESS OF SCALE
OR LOCATION. FEDERAL LAW DOES NOT PROHIBIT
REQUIRING ALTERNATE TO ANALYSIS ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW OR
COMPLIANCE WITH LOCAL SETTINGS. THOSE ARE THE TOOLS THAT ALLOW
THE CITY TO STEAL STEER THE FACILITIES TOWARD APPROPRIATE
LOCATIONS LIKE INDUSTRIAL AREAS, COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS
AND EXISTING UTILITY SITES. SAN FRANCISCO HAS SUCCESSFULLY
DEFENDED THESE TOOLS BEFORE. OUR WIRELESS ORDINANCE WAS
UPHELD UNANIMOUSLY BY THE COURT SUPREME COURT IN 2018.
IT IS NOW A NATIONAL MODEL. GETTING THESE APPEALS TO
PRESERVE THE CITY'S AUTHORITY AFFIRMS THAT OUR GUIDELINES
AND PROTECTS CITY NEIGHBORHOODS AND RESIDENTS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, JOE, FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS AND STAFF.
MY NAME IS BART FISHER AND I'VE LIVED IN DIMOND HEIGHTS FOR
OVER A QUARTER CENTURY. DURING THAT TIME I DON'T
BELIEVE ANY ISSUE HAS GALVANIZED OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
AND GOTTEN US AS UPSET AS THE PLAN TO BUILD THIS 100 FOOT
MONSTROSITY IN THE MIDDLE OF OUR BEAUTIFUL AND HISTORIC
COMMUNITY. >> I BELIEVE THE FOUR PLANNING
COMMISSIONERS WHO VOTED FOR THIS WERE NEGLIGENT
IN UPHOLDING THEIR DUTIES TO OUR LAWS MEANT TO PROTECT OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS FROM SUCH DETRIMENTAL CHANGES.
AT THIS HEARING NOT A SINGLE RESIDENT SPOKE IN FAVOR OF THIS
AT&T HANDOUT WHILE THERE WERE DOZENS IN ATTENDANCE WHO SPOKE
AGAINST IT. >> I ASK EACH OF YOU TO REFLECT
IN YOUR HEART HOW YOU WOULD FEEL ABOUT HAVING A TEN STORY
CELL TOWER BEING INSTALLED THIS IN THE CENTER OF YOUR
COMMUNITY. IMAGINE THE TALL UGLY EYESORE
LOOMING OVER YOUR NEIGHBORHOOD VISIBLE FROM ALMOST EVERYWHERE
INDUCING ADDITIONAL POTENTIAL DANGERS AND BEING BUILT RIGHT
NEXT TO THE PARK WHERE YOUR LOCAL CHILDREN PLAY.
I BELIEVE IF YOU ARE HONEST WITH YOURSELF YOU WOULD BEHAVE
EXACTLY LIKE ME AND MY NEIGHBORS AND DO EVERYTHING YOU
COULD TO STOP IT FROM BEING BUILT.
>> YOU WOULD BE PRAYING THAT THOSE YOU'VE ELECTED WILL FIND
THE COURAGE TO DO THE RIGHT THING AND STAND WITH YOU BY
STOPPING THE PROJECT. >> SINCE THIS SINCE ONCE THIS
IS DONE THERE'S LIKELY NO GOING BACK.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU BART FISHER FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> I USED TO PROVIDE. CAN YOU GRAB THAT MICROPHONE
REALLY CLOSE SO WE CAN HEAR YOU BEST?
>> THANK YOU. >> SORRY I'M ONLY FIVE FOR ONE.
HI, MY NAME IS ELENA. I CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 2003
. I CAME FOR NURSING SCHOOL.
I'M A NURSE. I'M A MOM.
AND AFTER I FINISHED MY EDUCATION I THOUGHT I'D LIKE TO
SEE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> I'D LIKE TO GIVE BACK TO THE
CITY THAT EDUCATED ME. >> AND SINCE THEN THERE THERE
ARE A LOT OF REASONS TO LEAVE SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE ALL KNOW IT'S IN THE DOOM LOOP.
>> BUT WHEN THERE ARE A MILLION REASONS TO GO FOR FAMILIES
ANOTHER ONE IS JUST ANOTHER STRAW ON THE CAMEL'S BACK.
TO LEAVE AND IF WE WANT TO MAKE A CITY THAT FEELS MORE
INCLUSIVE OF FAMILIES OF LITTLE ONES OF PEOPLE STAYING I THINK
LISTENING TO THE RESIDENTS IS A GOOD WAY TO DO THAT.
MY DAUGHTER LOVES THAT PARK. SORRY THIS YEAH THAT'S THAT'S
HER GO TO. AND IT JUST SO HAPPENS TO BE
WITHIN WALKING DISTANCE OF A PROPERTY THAT I WAS LUCKY
ENOUGH TO GET WHEN I WHEN DURING THE PANDEMIC.
>> SO TO HAVE A PLACE OF MY OWN FOR HER MY KID TO GROW UP
IN AND JUST TO HAVE ANOTHER ONE MORE REASON TO YOU KNOW LEAVE
OR SORRY. >> UM I JUST THINK IT'S
UNFORTUNATE AND I REALLY HOPE THAT THE SUPERVISORS TODAY
WOULD REALLY, REALLY LISTEN. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU ELEANOR. PONCY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI THERE.
MY NAME IS THEA SELBY. I AM A CO-FOUNDER OF THE LOWER
HAIGHT MERCHANT AND NEIGHBOR ASSOCIATION.
I HAVE A SMALL BUSINESS A BLOCK AWAY FROM UNION SQUARE.
>> I AM A FORMER TRUSTEE OF THE BOARD OF OF SAN FRANCISCO CITY
COLLEGE. >> I AM ALSO A CO-FOUNDER OF
SAN FRANCISCANS FOR LOCAL CONTROL AND WHAT SAN
FRANCISCANS FOR LOCAL CONTROL WAS ABOUT WAS URGING OUR BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS OURS TO TAKE THE VERY LITTLE POWER YOU HAVE VERY
LITTLE POWER ON THIS PARTICULAR THING AND I HAPPEN TO KNOW
THAT. >> BUT TO TAKE THE VERY LITTLE
POWER THAT YOU HAVE AND USE IT FOR THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO
IN 2010, JOHN AVALOS INTRODUCED THE PERSONAL WIRELESS SERVICE
FACILITY SITE PERMITS ORDINANCE REQUIRING ANTENNA APPLICANTS TO
CONSIDER THE VISUAL IMPACT. >> THIS IS ABOUT THE ONLY POWER
YOU HAVE OF ANY NEW INSTALLATION CITING THE NEED TO
REGULATE PLACEMENT THAT WILL DIMINISH THE CITY'S BEAUTY.
>> SOME PEOPLE SAY THE CITY IS ABOUT TECH, OTHERS GOVERNMENT.
I WOULD SAY TOURISM IS VERY HIGH ON THE LIST.
THE ORDINANCE WAS CHALLENGED IN COURT AND IT WAS UPHELD
AND IT'S STILL IN EFFECT TODAY IN 2025 JOHN AVALOS WROTE THE
PLANNING COMMISSION AND URGED THEM TO REJECT THE CELL PHONE
STRUCTURE BECAUSE IT WOULD DRAMATICALLY CHANGE THE STATIC
CHARACTER WHICH IS ABOUT ALL YOU GOT GUYS OF THE
NEIGHBORHOOD INCLUDING GLEN CANYON PARK AND GEORGE
CHRISTOPHER PLAYGROUND. >> THIS PROPOSED FACILITY WILL
RUIN VISTAS. >> YOU'VE HEARD THAT OVER
AND OVER AND THIS IS ONE OF THE THINGS THAT YOU HAVE THE
CONTROL TO DECIDE THAT YOU WILL NOT ALLOW AT&T AND OTHERS TO DO
SO. >> HE STATED THAT APPROVING THE
SEQUOIA APPEAL IS A MUST. >> THE PROJECT FAILS THE CORE
METRICS REQUIRED. IT IS NOT DESIRABLE.
IT IS NOT NECESSARY. IT IS NOT COMPATIBLE WITH
NEIGHBORHOOD CHARACTER AND FUNDAMENTALLY INCONSISTENT
WITH THE GENERAL PLAN AND THE INTENT OF THE OPEN SPACE
DESIGNATION. >> PLEASE USE THE POWER YOU
HAVE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU TRUSTEE SELBY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. HI I'M CHANDA WILLIAMS.
I'VE LIVED IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS FOR 25 YEARS AND I JUST HAVE A
MORE EMOTIONAL PILL. >> THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE ON
MY STREET WHO COULDN'T BE HERE TODAY THAT WOULD LIKE TO BE
BECAUSE THEY'RE AT WORK OR THEY HAVE KIDS THEY HAVE TO PICK UP
AT THIS HOUR OR WHATEVER ELSE. BUT WE'RE ALL SCARED.
WE'RE REALLY FRIGHTENED. I'M NOT THE ONLY ONE.
THERE ARE SEVERAL PEOPLE IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD WHO'VE BEEN
EVACUATED FROM FIRES. I WAS EVACUATED FROM THE
PALISADES FIRE LAST YEAR. >> THESE FIRES GO FAST.
THE WINDS AND DIAMOND HEIGHTS AND ALL OF OUR WOOD HOUSES
BOARDED UP AGAINST EACH OTHER AND ALL THAT BRUSH DOWN IN THE
PARK. >> IT'S SCARY.
>> IT'S REALLY SCARY TO US. SO PLEASE CONSIDER PROTECTING
THE SAFETY OF YOUR CONSTITUENTS RATHER THAN LINING THE POCKETS
OF A MULTIBILLION DOLLAR CORPORATION.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ARE THERE OTHER SPEAKERS IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL OR
AGAINST THE PROJECT? THIS IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO
PROVIDE COMMENT. >> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED AND NOW WE WILL HEAR FOR UP TO
TEN MINUTES FROM REPRESENTATIVES OF THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT. >> CAN WE GO TO THE SIDES
PLEASE? >> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT
MELMAN AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS JOSH POLLACK, PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF.
JOINING ME TODAY ARE JOY NAVARETTE AND ELIZABETH GORDON.
JUNK CARE. THE ITEM BEFORE YOU IS THE
APPEAL OF A CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION ISSUED BY THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR THE 350 AMBER DRIVE PROJECT PURSUANT TO
THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT OR SEQUA OUR
DECEMBER 1ST APPEAL RESPONSE IS INCLUDED IN THE BOARD'S PACKET
. IN THIS PRESENTATION I WILL
HIGHLIGHT THE DEPARTMENT'S MAIN RESPONSES TO THE APPEAL.
BUT FIRST I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE TESTIMONY TODAY FROM THE
SPEAKERS AND SUPPLEMENTAL CORRESPONDENCE RECEIVED FROM
THOSE WHO ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THE POTENTIAL ENVIRONMENTAL
IMPACTS OF THE PROJECT. THESE ISSUES HAVE BEEN
ADDRESSED IN THE DEPARTMENT'S APPEAL RESPONSE.
>> THE PROJECT IS LOCATED AT 350 AMBER DRIVE WITH FRONTAGE
ALONG AMBER DRIVE TO THE NORTHWEST TURQUOISE WAY TO THE
WEST AND DUNCAN STREET TO THE NORTH.
THE PROPERTY IS OWNED BY THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND IS UNDER THE JURISDICTION OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT OR SFPD.
THE TOTAL LOT AREA IS ABOUT 195,000FT2 OR ROUGHLY FOUR
AND A HALF ACRES AND CONTAINS 322122 STORY BUILDINGS
CURRENTLY OCCUPIED AND USED BY THE S.F. PD AS ITS POLICE
ACADEMY. THE PARCEL IS ADJACENT TO GLEN
CANYON PARK AND CHRISTOPHER PARK.
>> THE PROPOSED PROJECT WILL CONSTRUCT A NEW AT&T MACRO
WIRELESS TELECOMMUNICATIONS FACILITY ON A NEW APPROXIMATELY
104 FOOT TALL MONOPOLE LOCATED AT THE REAR OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE ACADEMY OVER A PAVED PARKING AREA WITH A
FOOTPRINT OF APPROXIMATELY 550FT2.
>> THE NEW FACILITY WOULD CONSIST OF 12 ANTENNAS NINE
REMOTE RADIO UNITS, THREE TOWER MOUNTED SURGE SUPPRESSORS, ONE
GLOBAL POSITIONING SYSTEM UNIT MOUNTED ON A PROPOSED OUTDOOR
EQUIPMENT CABINET, ONE WALKUP CABINET AND ONE 30 KILOWATT
DIRECT CURRENT BACKUP GENERATOR WITH 190 GALLON DIESEL FUEL
TANK ON A CONCRETE PAD. THE ANCILLARY EQUIPMENT WOULD
BE SURROUNDED BY AN EIGHT FOOT TALL CHAIN LINK FENCE.
>> THE PROJECT MEETS THE DEFINITION OF A CLASS THREE
INFILL EXEMPTION AS IT MEETS ALL CRITERIA IDENTIFIED ON THIS
SLIDE. IN ADDITION, NONE OF THE
EXCEPTIONS TO THE CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION APPLY INCLUDING
SIGNIFICANT EFFECTS DUE TO UNUSUAL UNUSUAL CIRCUMSTANCES.
THE APPELLANTS ALLEGE THAT THE PROPOSED PROJECT WOULD HAVE
SUBSTANTIAL IMPACTS WITH RESPECT TO SEISMIC HAZARDS,
FIRE RISK, AIR QUALITY AND BIOLOGICAL RESOURCES.
THIS IS NOT THE CASE AS I WILL ADDRESS FOR INFORMATIONAL
PURPOSES. >> THE PROJECT SITE IS NOT IN A
SEISMIC HAZARD ZONE FOR LANDSLIDES.
RATHER IT IS LOCATED APPROXIMATELY 50FT FROM AN AREA
THAT IS DEEMED A SEISMIC HAZARD FOR LANDSLIDES.
>> THE PROJECT WOULD NOT RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS RELATED
TO FIRE RISK DUE TO ACCIDENTAL FIRES OR WILDFIRES.
SAN FRANCISCO IS NOT LOCATED IN A WILDFIRE HAZARD ZONE AS
SHOWN IN THE FIRE HAZARD SEVERITY ZONES MAP WHICH IS
MAPPED BY CAL FIRE. PER MANDATES UNDER THE
CALIFORNIA PUBLIC RESOURCES CODE THE PROJECT WOULD NOT
RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT AIR QUALITY IMPACTS.
THERE ARE NO UNUSUAL CIRCUMSTANCES SURROUNDING THE
PROJECT RELATED TO AIR QUALITY IMPACTS.
ALL OF THE MONOPOLE FACILITIES IN SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDE DIESEL
POWERED BACKUP GENERATORS SIMILAR TO THE PROPOSED PROJECT
. THE PROPOSED PROJECT WOULD
UTILIZE A 30 KILOWATT DIESEL POWERED BACKUP GENERATOR WHICH
DOES NOT REQUIRE A PERMIT FROM THE BAY AREA AIR DISTRICT.
>> THE APPELLANT CLAIMS THAT FUEL TANKS ARE KNOWN TO LEAK
AIR POLLUTANTS AND THAT THE PROJECT WOULD CREATE EXPOSURE
TO AIR POLLUTION BUT DOES NOT PROVIDE SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE TO
SUPPORT THIS ASSERTION. >> THE PROJECT WOULD NOT RESULT
IN SIGNIFICANT BIOLOGICAL RESOURCES IMPACTS.
THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT PREVIOUSLY COMPLETED
AN ASSESSMENT OF SIGNIFICANT NATURAL RESOURCES WHICH
INCLUDED A DETAIL EVALUATION OF GLEN CANYON PARK.
THE ASSESSMENT FOUND THAT THE INTERIOR PORTIONS OF THE
ADJACENT PARK SUPPORT SENSITIVE SPECIES.
HOWEVER, IN EVALUATING THE ASSESSMENT OF THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT FOUND THAT THE NATURAL AREA BOUNDARY AND REC
PARK'S EVALUATION IS OVER 100FT AWAY FROM THE PROJECT SITE.
IN ADDITION, THE AREA CLOSEST TO THE PROJECT SITE FALLS UNDER
LEASE SENSITIVE MANAGEMENT AREA DUE TO THE DISTANCE FROM ANY
SENSITIVE AREAS BIOLOGICAL RESOURCES IN THE PARK COULD NOT
BE REASONABLY AFFECTED BY CONSTRUCTION OR OPERATION OF
THE PROPOSED PROJECT. THEREFORE THE PROJECT WOULD NOT
RESULT IN ANY SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS RELATED TO BIOLOGICAL
RESOURCES. >> IN CLOSING, THE DEPARTMENT
HAS SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT THE DETERMINATION THAT
THE PROJECT QUALIFIES FOR CLASS THREE CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION
AND NO EXCEPTIONS APPLY. THE APPELLANT'S ARGUMENTS DO
NOT MEET THE LEGAL BURDEN OF PROOF TO DEMONSTRATE OTHERWISE
. THERE IS NO BASIS FOR REQUIRING
PREPARATION OF A MITIGATED NEGATIVE DECLARATION OR
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT. THEREFORE WE ASK THAT YOU
UPHOLD THE CLASS THREE CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION AND DENY
THE APPEAL. >> THANK YOU.
THIS CONCLUDES MY PRESENTATION .
ELIZABETH GORDON JOHN CARE WILL NOW ADDRESS THE CONDITIONAL USE
APPEAL. >> THANK YOU JOSH AND GOOD
AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS ELIZABETH JONG CARE OF PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF
AND I WILL VERY BRIEFLY ADDRESS THE SECOND APPEAL BEFORE YOU.
THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S APPROVAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FOR THE WIRELESS FACILITY AT 350 AND FOR DRIVE
IN SEPTEMBER 20TH. ON SEPTEMBER 25TH, 2025, THE
COMMISSION CONDUCTED A PUBLIC HEARING AND VOTED 4 TO 3 TO
APPROVE THE PROJECT UNDER CONDITIONAL USE.
IN THEIR MOTION 21 A 25 ALL CONDITIONAL USE FINDINGS WERE
MADE IN THE AFFIRMATIVE. AS PART OF THE COMMISSION'S
DELIBERATION THE COMMISSIONERS REFERENCED THE NEED FOR
ADDITIONAL COVERAGE PROVIDED BY THE PROJECT AND THE BENEFIT TO
EMERGENCY SERVICES. MY COLLEAGUE JOSH HAS
ADEQUATELY DESCRIBED THE LOCATION AND THE FACILITY
ITSELF AND MANY OF THE CONCURRENT ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH
AND SAFETY ARGUMENTS THAT ARE SIMILAR IN THE CONDITIONAL USE
APPEAL. >> SO I WILL NOT ADDRESS THOSE
AT PRESENT ASIDE FROM STATING THAT AS PART OF THE PERMITTING
PROCESS THE PROJECT WILL BE REQUIRED TO MEET RIGOROUS STATE
AND LOCAL FIRE CODES AND CONDITIONS AND THE BUILDING
PERMIT APPLICATION WOULD BE REVIEWED PURSUANT TO STATE
AND LOCAL BUILDING CODES. >> ALSO IN ITS DELIBERATION THE
COMMISSION FOUND THE PROJECT CONSISTENT WITH THE RECREATION
OPEN SPACE AND SAFETY AND RESILIENCE ELEMENTS OF THE
GENERAL PLAN INDICATING THAT IMPROVED CELLULAR COVERAGE
WOULD BE NECESSARY AND DESIRABLE TO THE COMMUNITY
AND GREATER CITY AND ALLOW FOR BETTER UTILIZATION OF THE
PLAYGROUNDS AND PARKS. BECAUSE THE PROPOSED PROJECT IS
IN AN EXISTING PARKING LOT AND ZONED PUBLIC AT THE REAR OF
THE EXISTING SAN FRANCISCO POLICE ACADEMY, IT IS NOT
ACCESSIBLE TO THE PUBLIC OR RESIDENTS.
IT IS NOT LOCATED ON RECORD AND PARK DEPARTMENT LAND.
IT IS NOT IDENTIFIED AS EXISTING OR PROPOSED OPEN SPACE
IN THE GENERAL PLAN. IT IS IDENTIFIED AS A
PREFERENCE ONE WIRELESS LOCATION.
THE JUNE NINTH, 2025 REC AND PARK COMMISSION HEARING PER
RESOLUTION CONFIRMED THAT THE NET NEW SHADOW CAST BY THE
PROPOSED PROPOSED PROJECT WAS LIMITED.
>> FINALLY, IF THE PROPOSAL IS CONSISTENT WITH THE SAFETY
AND RESILIENCE ELEMENT WHICH SPECIFICALLY STATES THAT
PRIVATE COMMUNICATION SYSTEMS ARE CRITICAL FACILITIES AND THE
CITY'S COMMUNICATION SYSTEM AND REDUNDANT NETWORKS WILL
HELP ENSURE THAT INCIDENTAL FAILURES DO NOT HAVE GRAVE
IMPACTS. >> IN CONCLUSION, THE
DEPARTMENT RECOMMENDS THAT THE BOARD UPHOLD THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S APPROVAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE.
THIS CONCLUDES THE DEPARTMENT PRESENTATION.
MY COLLEAGUES FROM THE DEPARTMENT AND I ARE AVAILABLE
TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
I HAVE QUESTIONS BUT IT'S LIKE A FIRST.
OKAY. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAMP.
>> LET'S START WITH THE SECURE MR..
MR. PARK. >> SO I HAVE TWO THOUGHTS ABOUT
THE THE SECURE APPEAL. ON THE ONE HAND THE APPELLANTS
ARE ARGUING THAT THIS PROJECT SHOULD BE SUBJECT TO AN
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT WHICH STRIKES ME AS ODD.
I MEAN THAT WOULD BE MANY HUNDREDS OF PAGES WITH YOU KNOW
LOTS AND LOTS AND LOTS OF ANALYSIS OF ALL SORTS OF
THINGS. SO I I'M SYMPATHETIC TO THE TO
THE DEPARTMENT'S FEELING THAT THAT'S NOT APPROPRIATE FOR A
PROJECT LIKE THIS. AND I UNDERSTAND RELYING ON THE
SEQUOIA EXEMPTION. BUT I DO WONDER I MEAN THIS IS
NOT A BIG FACILITY BUT IT IS A VERY TALL FACILITY.
>> SO HOW DO YOU THINK ABOUT HEIGHT IN WEIGHING WHETHER
SOMETHING FITS WITHIN THE SMALL FACILITY EXEMPTION?
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION. SO CONSIDERING THE HEIGHT WE
LOOKED AT THE CONTEXT THAT THE TOWER WAS IN.
>> SO THE TOWER ITSELF IS 104FT AND THE NEARBY WHICH IS TALL,
WHICH IS TEN STORIES AND THE THE TREES THAT IT WOULD STAND
ADJACENT TO ARE APPROXIMATELY 90FT.
SO CONSIDERING THE CONTEXT OF THE TOWERS AND WE WE DETERMINED
THAT IT WAS SMALL IN THAT CONTEXT.
>> IS THERE I MEAN IS WHAT WOULD MAKE IT BIG?
>> WHAT WHAT WHAT IS THERE A TELECOM FACILITY THAT WOULD NOT
FIT WITH IT WITHIN THE SMALL FACILITY EXCEPTION.
>> IF IT WAS SUBSTANTIALLY LARGER THAN THE SURROUNDINGS IF
IF THERE IF IT WAS A YOU KNOW, LARGE FACILITY WHICH THERE WAS
NOTHING OF COMPARABLE HEIGHT, I THINK WE WOULD CONSIDER THAT TO
NOT MEET THE CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION.
>> BUT GENERALLY DEPARTMENT THINKS I MEAN YOU'VE APPROVED A
BUNCH OF TALENT YOU YOU APPROVED A NUMBER OF TELECOM
FACILITIES BASED ON THIS EXEMPTION.
THE DIFFERENCE THAT I'M HEARING FROM THE APPELLANT'S IS THAT
YOU KNOW, THIS THIS IS QUITE A BIT TALLER AND THAT'S TRUE
RIGHT? >> I MEAN I THINK CONSIDERING
THE CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION THAT WAS DONE FOR THE CELL TOWER
THAT WAS ADJACENT TO THE PALACE OF FINE ARTS, YOU KNOW AROUND
THIS A SIMILAR SCALE THE YOU KNOW, 90FT IN HEIGHT.
>> SO I THINK IT'S BEEN IT'S BEEN USED IN A SIMILAR WAY
BEFORE OR THROUGH IT. YOU KNOW IN OTHER PARTS OF THE
CITY. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> I HAVE MORE QUESTIONS ABOUT THE CONDITION THE CONDITIONAL
USE AND I THINK I GUESS I AM TRYING TO UNDERSTAND AND IF YOU
HAVE SOME THOUGHTS ABOUT THE, YOU KNOW, RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN
THE TRADITIONAL CONDITIONAL USE APPROVAL STANDARD GUARDS,
WHETHER SOMETHING IS NECESSARY AND DESIRABLE AND THE ONGOING
ABILITY I GUESS OF CITIES TO APPLY THAT'S I MEAN I GUESS
UNDER THIS 2018 SUPREME COURT CASE THE ABILITY OF CITIES TO
EVALUATE AT LEAST SOME OF THE IMPACTS OF TELECOM FACILITIES
AND DECIDE DECIDING WHETHER TO APPROVE THEM OR NOT.
BUT THAT'S YOU KNOW, ON THE ONE HAND WE HAVE THAT BUT ON THE
OTHER HAND WE HAVE THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT AND CAN
YOU EXPLAIN THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE KIND OF LIMITATIONS
ON US ON A CITY'S ABILITY TO SAY NO UNDER THE TELECOMMUTING
COMMUNICATIONS ACT AND THE STANDARDS THAT EXIST FOR A
CONDITIONAL USE? >> I MEAN I CAN I CAN I ASK THE
QUESTION AGAIN IN SORT OF A DIFFERENT WAY?
I MEAN THE PUBLIC IS IN THE APPELLANTS ARE GENERALLY
ARGUING THAT THIS PROJECT IS NOT NECESSARY AND DESIRABLE
AND THAT WOULD BE THE TRADITIONAL ARGUMENT UNDER YOU
KNOW, ABOUT A CONDITIONAL USE. AND I'M GATHERING FROM THE
DOCUMENTS THAT I'M READING ABOUT THIS YOU KNOW FROM THE
ARGUMENT THAT THE APPELLANT'S AND THE CITY AND AT&T ARE
HAVING THAT THAT'S NOT THE ONLY CONVERSATION YOU HAVE WHEN YOU
HAVE A TELECOM FACILITY. YOU'RE ALSO HAVING AND HAVING
TO EVALUATE ADEQUACY OF COVERAGE, EVALUATION OF
POTENTIAL ALTERNATIVES. SO IS IT POSSIBLE THAT
SOMETHING COULD BE NOT NECESSARILY NECESSARY
AND DESIRABLE BUT THE CITY WOULD STILL HAVE TO APPROVE IT?
>> I THINK YOU SUPERVISOR OF YOUR EMERGENCY PLANNING
DEPARTMENT STAFF I THINK GENERALLY YOU ARE CORRECT THAT
THERE THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT DOES REQUIRE US TO CONSIDER
OTHER FACTORS AND IT DOES NOT NECESSARILY LIMIT BUT IT
RESHAPES WHAT WE CONSIDER TO BE DISCRETIONARY IN TERMS OF WHAT
CAN BE APPROVED AND WHAT CAN BE LIMITED WHEN IT COMES TO
TELECOMMUNICATIONS FACILITIES AND SO THEN THERE'S THIS SORT
OF TWO PRONG TEST THAT WE HAVE TO LOOK AT I THINK AND YOU
SHOULD TELL ME IF I'M GETTING THIS WRONG BUT IT SEEMS LIKE
YOU'RE THEN LOOKING AT ONE WHETHER THERE'S A GAP
IN SERVICE AND THEN IF THERE IS A GAP IN SERVICE AND THERE'S
EVIDENCE OF A GAP IN SERVICE IN THE RECORD WHETHER THAT THE
TELECOM COMPANY HAS ADEQUATELY LOOKED AT POTENTIAL
ALTERNATIVES TO DO IT IN A DIFFERENT WAY THAT WOULD BE
LESS INTRUSIVE. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT SYLVIA
JIMENEZ DEPARTMENT STAFF AND TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, IT IS A
TWO PART QUESTION. I THINK THE FIRST ONE YOU'RE
REFERRING TO IS COVERAGE MAPS AS PART OF THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION APPLICATION APPLICANTS ARE REQUIRED TO
SUBMIT DOCUMENTATION VERIFIED BY A CERTIFIED ENGINEER THAT
SHOWS THE LEVEL OF COVERAGE AND THE AREA THAT THEY'RE
PROPOSING TO INSTALL THEIR MACRO SITE IN THIS SCENARIO THE
APPLICANT DID SUBMIT SUCH COVERAGE MAPS IT SHOWS ANYTHING
FROM YOU KNOW, INADEQUACY FROM NOT BEING ABLE TO TAKE A PHONE
CALL IN A MOVING VEHICLE TO JUST NOT BEING ABLE TO MAKE A
VOICE CALL AND ALL OF THOSE THINGS COMBINED DETERMINED THAT
THERE WAS INADEQUATE COVERAGE. >> THIS INFORMATION WAS
PROVIDED. SO AGAIN, THE ONUS IS ON THE
APPLICANT TO SUBMIT THAT INFORMATION AND THEY WERE ABLE
TO DEMONSTRATE THAT AS FAR AS THE ALTERNATIVE SITE ANALYSIS
THAT IS ONLY REQUIRED FOR SITES THAT ARE CONSIDERED PREFERENCE
FIVE AND ABOVE. SO THE CITY HAS A RANKING
SYSTEM OF HIERARCHY WHEN IT COMES TO LOCATING THESE MACRO
SITES THE RATING BEING ONE THROUGH SEVEN ONE BEING A
PREFERRED SITE. TYPICALLY THOSE ARE PUBLIC USES
FIRE STATIONS, POLICE STATIONS ,AREAS OF THAT NATURE AND A
PREFERENCE SEVEN BEING A DISFAVORED SITE MOSTLY
RESIDENTIAL AREAS WHICH I KNOW THERE'S A LITTLE BIT OF AN
ARGUMENT THAT THIS IS THIS IS A RESIDENTIAL AREA BUT THE ACTUAL
SITE ITSELF IS A PUBLIC USE THEREFORE BECAUSE IT IS
CONSIDERED A PREFERENCE ONE SITE AND ALTERNATIVE ANALYSIS
WAS NOT REQUIRED. >> HOWEVER THE APPLICANT CHOSE
TO CONDUCT AN ALTERNATIVE ANALYSIS AND PRESENTED AT THE
PLANNING COMMISSION FOR DISCUSSION AND REVIEW AS A
VOLUNTARY WAY OF RESPONDING TO THE NEIGHBORS CONCERNS.
>> OKAY, SO LET'S TALK A LITTLE MORE ABOUT EACH OF THOSE TWO
BECAUSE THERE'S AN ARGUMENT IN THE DOCUMENTS BETWEEN THE
APPELLANT'S AND THE PROJECT SPONSOR IN THE CITY ABOUT ABOUT
WHAT KIND WHAT IS A GAP AND I THINK ALTHOUGH WE'RE GONNA HEAR
FROM THE APPELLANT'S ON REBUTTAL BUT I THINK THAT THE
APPELLANTS ARE SAYING THAT BECAUSE AT&T HAS NOT SHOWN THAT
THERE IS A COMPLETE GAP IN SERVICE THAT THERE IS A SPOT
WHERE YOU CANNOT GET COVERAGE, YOU CANNOT GET GET CELL SERVICE
EVER THAT THAT DOESN'T ADEQUATELY DEMONSTRATE THAT
DOESN'T ADEQUATELY MEET THE THE SERVICE GAP PRONG AND I ASSUME
THE CITY DISAGREES. AND I'M CURIOUS IF YOU WANT TO
EXPLAIN WHY YOU THINK WEAK COVERAGE IS ENOUGH TO JUSTIFY A
TELECOM COMPANY BEING ABLE TO PUT IN A FACILITY EVEN WERE IT
OTHERWISE NOT NECESSARY AND DESIRABLE?
YES, I THINK A DEPARTMENT POLICY HAS ALWAYS BEEN TO
DETERMINE NOT JUST NON-EXISTING COVERAGE BUT YOU KNOW, THE
QUALITY OF THE COVERAGE IS IMPORTANT AS WELL.
>> AND I THINK SOME OF THE EXAMPLES THAT WERE GIVEN AT THE
PLANNING COMMISSION, YOU KNOW, AFTER BEING PROMPTED BY SOME OF
THE COMMISSIONERS WAS YOU KNOW, IN CASE OF AN EMERGENCY, WOULD
SOMEBODY BE ABLE TO JUST USE THEIR PHONE AND CALL EMERGENCY
SERVICES WHETHER IT WOULD BE, YOU KNOW, BEING ATTACKED AT THE
PARK OR YOU KNOW, IN AN EMERGENCY SCENARIO SUCH AS AN
EARTHQUAKE AND WE DETERMINE AT LEAST OUR DEPARTMENT POLICY IS
UNLESS YOU KNOW, WE'RE GIVEN DIFFERENT DIRECTION IS THAT
INADEQUATE SERVICE IS CONSIDERED A COVERAGE GAP.
>> I MEAN THE TROUBLE WITH THAT ANSWER IS THEN YOU'RE SAYING
IT'S UP TO THE CITY AND THE KIND OF STANDARDS WE ARE
LOCALLY SETTING AROUND THIS AND THAT AND THIS HAPPENED
IN THE PLANNING COMMISSION PRESENTED ATIONS THAT THERE WAS
THIS SORT OF CENTERING OF THIS ARGUMENT ABOUT WHETHER THERE
WAS A DANGER IN AN EMERGENCY IN THE IN THE CANYON.
I'M NOT SURE ABOUT THIS BUT I ACTUALLY THINK THAT THIS
AND THE APPELLANT'S ARE WELCOME TO ARGUE WITH ME ABOUT THIS
AND I'M CURIOUS IF THIS IS THE POSITION OF THE CITY.
I THINK THAT THE STANDARD IS BASICALLY IF THEY'RE NOT ABLE
TO PROVIDE THE SERVICE THAT THEY THINK THEY SHOULD BE ABLE
TO PROVIDE THEY HAVE AND THEY CAN DEMONSTRATE THAT THAT'S NOT
GOOD SERVICE BASICALLY THAT THEY'VE MET THAT FIRST PRONG.
>> THAT IS CORRECT. THAT'S THE CITY I MEAN THAT'S
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENTS VIEW OF THIS.
>> OKAY. OKAY.
AND THEN SO THEN THERE'S THE SECOND QUESTION BECAUSE EVEN IF
THEY COULD MEET THAT THEY WOULD STILL BE OUT OF LUCK IF THEY
WEREN'T DOING AN ADEQUATE I MEAN WE'D BE BACK INTO LOOKING
AT WHETHER THINGS ARE NECESSARY AND DESIRABLE AND THAT KIND OF
WEIGHING WHERE I THINK THE NEIGHBORS HAVE A MUCH STRONGER
CASE IF THEY WEREN'T GETTING IF THEY WEREN'T LOOKING AT LESS
INTRUSIVE WAYS TO DO THIS. AND THERE'S AND I THINK AT&T
THEY'VE GONE AHEAD THEY'VE DONE THAT ANALYSIS OF AND THEY HAVE
A STORY ABOUT HOW THEY'VE LOOKED AT ALL THESE OTHER SITES
AND THERE'S NOT THE OTHER SITES AND THEY'VE TRIED AND REALLY
THE ONLY WAY FOR THEM TO DO THIS THIS TYPE OF FACILITY IS
TO BUILD THIS TYPE OF HUNDRED FOOT TOWER WHICH MAY OR MAY NOT
BE A SMALL FACILITY BUT YOU KNOW, IF IT IS A SMALL FACILITY
EXEMPT FROM THE EQUIPMENT THAT THEY HAVE TO DO WITH THIS TOWER
IN THIS WAY BECAUSE THAT'S THE ONLY WAY TO DO THAT KIND OF
FACILITY AND I THINK THEY COULD PROBABLY SUPPORT THAT IF THEY
IF WE FORCE THEM TO LITIGATE IT .
>> SO BUT THERE SEEMS TO BE A DIFFERENT ARGUMENT COMING FROM
THE NEIGHBOR OF THE APPELLANT'S WHICH IS BUT YOU ALSO HAVE TO
LOOK AT ALTERNATIVE TECHNOLOGIES AND THEY HAVEN'T
LOOKED AT ALTERNATIVE TECHNOLOGIES AND AND MY
QUESTION IS WHETHER THAT IS SOMETHING THAT'S BEEN LITIGATED
OR THAT WE HAVE A SENSE OF WHETHER WE CAN TELL THEM THAT
THEY HAVE TO LOOK AT, FOR EXAMPLE, DISTRIBUTED ANTENNA
SYSTEMS RATHER THAN THIS TYPE OF FACILITY THE WAY THAT THE
ALTERNATIVE ANALYSIS REQUIREMENT IS CURRENTLY
WRITTEN IT SPEAKS TO LOCATION. SO EXPLORING OTHER TYPES OF
TECHNOLOGY THAT COULD ACHIEVE THE SAME AMOUNT OF COVERAGE IS
CURRENTLY NOT SOMETHING WE REQUIRE ESPECIALLY NOT FOR A
PREFERENCE. ONE SITE BE GREAT TO KNOW
WHETHER THAT'S BECAUSE WE CAN'T.
>> IT COULD BE I MEAN I WOULD HAVE TO CONSULT WITH OUR
WIRELESS ATTORNEYS I THINK WHY DON'T YOU ALL CHAT AMONGST
YOURSELVES? >> OKAY.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN I JUST KIND
OF CURIOUS A PROJECT OF THIS SIZE WITH THE FOOTPRINT OF
550FT2 BUT ALSO HAS A BACKUP GENERATOR AND 190 GALLON DIESEL
TANK HE SAYS IS THIS SOMETHING THAT WE HAVE SEEN BEFORE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE SIZE THREE CHATTING ABOUT MY QUESTION OF
THE IT'S THE SECRET PEOPLE ARE STILL THERE.
SO SO THE QUESTION THE QUESTION FROM SUPERVISOR CHAN WAS
RELATED TO THE GENERATOR AND THE FIRE FIRE RISK I THINK
RIGHT GENERATOR LIKE THERE'S A BACKUP GENERATOR AND THEN YOU
ALSO HAVE LIKE 192 GALLONS WELL ,THERE'S SOME DISCREPANCY.
I THINK THE AT&T SAY IT'S 150 GALLONS BUT ACCORDING TO
PLANNING DEPARTMENT IT SAYS 190 GALLONS OR UP TO 200 GALLONS OF
DIESEL TANK AND THEN YOU ALSO HAVE A BASE THOUGH THE BASE IS
LOOKS LIKE IT'S A FOOTPRINT OF 550FT2.
SO THE QUESTION IS HAVE WE SEEN A SIZE OF THIS TYPE TWO ANTENNA
FROM 284 ANY ACTUALLY JUST AT&T.
BUT FOR NOW FOR AT&T ANYWHERE IN THE CITY AT THE MOMENT HAVE
HAVE THIS BEEN DONE BEFORE? >> YEAH.
THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION SUPERVISOR SO MY UNDERSTANDING
IS THAT THE THE PROPOSED FACILITY THAT'S ADJACENT TO THE
PALACE OF FINE ARTS IS COMPARABLE IN TERMS OF
FOOTPRINT AND HEIGHT AND THAT IT'S STANDARD PRACTICE FOR
SIMILAR SIZED MONOPOLES TO INCLUDE A BACKUP GENERATOR OR
IN THE CASE OF EMERGENCY EVENTS.
SO THE ANTENNA COULD CONTINUE TO PROVIDE SERVICE.
>> WHAT IS THE SIZE OF THE PALACE OF FIRE NOT HERE I'M
LOOKING I DON'T KNOW IF THIS IS THE ACCURATE INFORMATION I'M
LOOKING AT. IT SAYS IT'S ABOUT 78FT
AND INTERESTINGLY SO THAT SOMEHOW IT'S A LIKE A FAKE
EUCALYPTUS TREE LIKE SOUTH TOWER LOOKING.
>> MY UNDERSTANDING IS IT'S APPROXIMATELY 90FT TALL.
I'M NOT SURE ON WHAT THE THE FOOTPRINT IS ON THE GROUND BUT
I THINK IT WOULD BE APPROXIMATELY SIMILAR TO WHAT'S
BEING PROPOSED HERE. BUT I DON'T KNOW IF MY
COLLEAGUES HAVE ANY SPECIFIC RECOLLECTIONS ABOUT THAT
PROJECT SO TELL US THE PALESTINE NORTHWEST.
>> YEAH, YEAH. YES.
>> I MEAN APOLOGIES. SORRY HERE IT SAYS IT'S LIKE
924 SQUARE FOOT CONCRETE PARAPET.
GO AHEAD. >> PLEASE CONTINUE.
WE WILL WE WILL ENDEAVOR TO GET THE ANSWER ON THE SIZE OF THE
CONCRETE PAD FOR THE PRESIDIO SITE.
>> NO PROBLEM I JUST A FEW MINUTES THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
THANK YOU BUT BUT THAT RIGHT NOW SO THERE WE HAVE NOW ONE
IN PALACE OF FINE ART AND THEN THIS IS THE SECOND ONE THAT
IT'S PROPOSED BY AT&T. YES THAT'S CORRECT.
>> SUPERVISOR THANK YOU. AND THEN I THINK I DO HAVE THAT
QUESTION TOO LIKE ABOUT THE SECURE EXEMPTION.
>> SO CLEARLY YOU HAVE A PRECEDENT ABOUT BEFORE THAT YOU
ISSUE A SECRET EXEMPTION FOR THE ONE PALACE OF FINE ART.
SEEMS LIKE IT IS SIMILARLY ALSO HAVE I I'M JUST KIND OF CURIOUS
HAVING A DIESEL TANK WHICH IS PERMANENT AND A BACKUP
GENERATOR ALSO PERMANENT ONCE IS THERE BUT THEY DON'T BUT
THEY CAN RECEIVE A SECURE EXEMPTION.
I AM THINK YES THAT'S CORRECT SO THE BAY AREA AIR QUALITY
MANAGEMENT DISTRICT IS THE AGENCY THAT'S RESPONSIBLE FOR
PERMITTING THE BACKUP GENERATORS AND IF A GENERATOR
IS LESS THAN 50 HORSEPOWER WHICH IT IS IN THIS CASE IT
DOES NOT REQUIRE A PERMIT BECAUSE THE AIR DISTRICT HAS
DETERMINED THAT GENERATORS THAT SIZE DO NOT HAVE SIGNIFICANT
AIR QUALITY IMPACTS. THANK YOU.
AND AGAIN I DO NOT SEE ANY OTHER COLLEAGUES IN THE QUEUE
AND SO I'M GOING TO INVITE THE PROJECT SPONSOR AT&T UP TO
SPEAK FOR UP TO TEN MINUTES. OKAY.
I WAS GOING TO DO A POWERPOINT BUT I'M INSTEAD GETTING THE
OVERHEAD PROJECTOR. CAN YOU SEE THAT THAT OKAY
CAMMIE BLACKSTONE HELLO SUPERVISORS AND PRESIDENT
MANDEL I'M CAMMY FROM AT&T AND I'M GOING TO BE JOINED
TODAY BY AMANDA MANN CHAMP WHO IS OUR LEGAL COUNSEL.
I JUST WANT TO KIND OF SPEAK TO WHY WE NEED THIS SITE SO THIS
CURRENTLY IS OUR COVERAGE IN THE AREA.
>> SO WHAT THIS MEANS IS ALL OF THE BLUE AND THE YELLOW MEANS
THAT IT'S LIKE GOOD COVERAGE OUTSIDE SOMETIMES INCONSISTENT
BUT NO INDOOR AND THEN THESE WHITE AREAS THERE'S NO COVERAGE
WHATSOEVER AND AT&T IS COMMITTED TO DELIVERING
RELIABLE HIGH QUALITY COVERAGE TO ALL OUR CUSTOMERS,
ESPECIALLY OUR FIRST RESPONDERS WHO DEPEND ON FIRSTNET.
BUT IN ADDITION TO THAT, THERE IS AN EXPECTATION IN SAN
FRANCISCO TO HAVE INDOOR COVERAGE LIKE YOUR DRIVING HOME
FROM WORK YOU'RE ON A CALL OR YOU'RE WALKING FROM THE BUS
STOP, YOU'RE ON A CALL AND YOU EXPECT TO KIND OF HAVE IT
INDOORS. >> IN ADDITION TO THAT, 25% OF
THE HOMES IN DIAMOND HEIGHTS ARE BMR RESIDENCES AND A LOT OF
PEOPLE ACTUALLY USE THEIR PHONES AND DEPEND ON THAT
WIRELESS COVERAGE FOR THEIR INTERNET SEARCHES WHETHER IT IS
FINDING OUT WHAT THEIR ASSIGNMENT IS FOR SCHOOL THE
NEXT DAY OR APPLYING FOR JOBS OR CHECKING THEIR BANK BALANCES
EVERYTHING THAT YOU WOULD DO ON A COMPUTER.
>> SO THIS IS HOW IT IS NOW ALL NO INDOOR COVERAGE EXCEPT FOR
OVER HERE WHICH IS OUR OTHER SITE THAT'S A MILE OR SO AWAY.
>> SO ONCE WE DO BUILD THIS SITE, IF WE GET TO BUILD THIS
SITE THIS WOULD BE THE COVERAGE ALL OF THAT GREEN WOULD BE
EXCELLENT INDOOR AND OUTDOOR COVERAGE.
OF COURSE THERE'S TO BE SOME YELLOW THERE WHICH MEANS GOOD
OUTDOORS BUT NOT NOT RELIABLE INDOORS SO THAT'S KIND OF THE
COVERAGE ARGUMENT THERE. >> I DO WANT TO SAY THAT
ALTHOUGH THE FIRST RESPONDERS ARE NOT MANDATED TO HAVE
FIRSTNET, THEY DO HAVE IT. IN FACT, 99% OF OUR POLICE
OFFICERS WITH THE SPEEDS FIRSTNET EVERY SINGLE FIRE
TRUCK IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS A SIM FOR FIRSTNET AND OUR
DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT USES FIRSTNET AS
THEIR PRIMARY CARRIER. IN ADDITION TO THAT, WE HAVE
BEEN LOOKING FOR TEN YEARS FOR A SITE IN THIS AREA TO COVER
THIS AREA AND ADDRESS THIS COVERAGE GAP.
>> WE'VE APPROACHED MANY BUILDINGS INCLUDING THE TWO
CHURCHES THAT CONTINUALLY COME UP SAINT AIDAN'S AND SAINT
NICHOLAS AND NOBODY HAS BUT WE HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO FIND A
SUITABLE SITE OR A WILLING LANDLORD.
SO THIS IS KIND OF OUR LAST HURRAH.
THIS IS THE LAST SITE AND WE CAME TO THIS SITE BECAUSE THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT CAPTAIN FELLS ON AT THE TIME HE WAS THE
CAPTAIN AT THE ACADEMY BEGGED US TO COME TAKE A LOOK AT THIS
SITE. IT'S A PREFERENCE ONE WE
THOUGHT IT WOULD BE GOOD WE DID EVERYTHING WE WERE SUPPOSED TO
DO WITH THIS PLANNING APPLICATION.
WE DID HAVE A COMMUNITY MEETING .
I DID EXCHANGE MANY EMAILS WITH DIFFERENT NEIGHBORS FROM THE
DIAMOND INCLUDING FOLKS FROM THE DIAMOND HEIGHTS COMMUNITY
ASSOCIATION AND THEN WE MET OF COURSE SUPERVISOR HANDELMAN
WITH YOU IN YOUR OFFICE TRYING TO KIND OF COME TO AN
AGREEMENT. SO AT&T IN OUR APPLICATION WE
DID EVERYTHING THAT WAS REQUIRED BY THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND WE INTEND TO DO EVERYTHING THAT'S REQUIRED BY
THE BUILDING DEPARTMENT AS FAR AS WORKING WITH EVERY RELEVANT
AGENCY AND ABIDING BY EVERY CITY REGULATION OR ANYTHING
ELSE. >> SO THIS IS AN IMPORTANT
SITE. I WANT TO TURN IT OVER TO
AMANDA IT IS A VERY IMPORTANT SITE AND I REALLY HOPE THAT YOU
WILL SUPPORT IT AND I WILL LET AMANDA RESPOND TO THE
APPELLANT'S BRIEF. >> GOOD AFTERNOON AND THANK YOU
FOR YOUR TIME. CERTAINLY.
HERE WE GO. >> HI.
SO I'M GOING TO ADDRESS SOME OF THE SPECIFIC QUESTIONS YOU ALL
ASKED AS WELL AS SPECIFIC COMMENTS MADE TODAY BY THE
APPELLANTS. >> SO TO GET RIGHT TO THE
LETTER THAT WAS FILED YESTERDAY BY THE APPELLANTS, THEY CITED
TWO CASES AND I JUST WANT TO BRIEFLY ADDRESS THEM.
NEITHER OF THEM ARE PUBLISHED CASES WHICH IN CALIFORNIA LAW
MEANS THEY ARE BASICALLY NONEXISTENT.
THEY ARE NOT PART OF THE BODY OF SCHOOL LAW.
BUT I JUST WANT TO ADDRESS THAT THEY ARE FACTUALLY ALSO
DISTINGUISHABLE AND DIFFERENT FROM THE SITE THAT'S BEFORE YOU
TODAY. THE ONLY PUBLISHED CASE THAT
ADDRESSES STANDALONE WIRELESS FACILITIES IS CITED IN OUR
LETTER. IT'S CALLED DON'T TELL OUR
PARKS. THAT IS A STANDALONE FACILITY
THAT IS IN A RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD IN A PARK IN A
CANYON, A VEGETATED CANYON VERY MUCH ON POINT.
THE CASES THEY TALK ABOUT ARE LIGHT STANDARDS SEVERAL OF THEM
NOT JUST A SINGLE SITE. AND THE OTHER IS A UNPUBLISHED
TRIAL CASE. THOSE BASED ON A VERY DIFFERENT
RECORD. I WAS INVOLVED IN THAT.
SO VERY DIFFERENT CASES ALSO NOT PART OF THE ACTUAL BODY OF
SCHOOL CASE LAW. >> YOU RAISED A CONCERN ABOUT
THE HEIGHT. SO THE EXEMPTION DOES NOT SPEAK
TO HEIGHT. IT SPEAKS TO SQUARE FOOTAGE.
SO WHEN YOU LOOK AT THE MASS OF A BUILDING THAT WOULD BE A
10,000 SQUARE FOOT BUILDING WHICH IS THE SIZE OF A BUILDING
THEY CAN USE THE SMALL FACILITY EXEMPTION.
IF YOU COMPARE THE MASS OF A 550 SQUARE FOOT WIRELESS SITE,
EVEN AT ITS HEIGHT IT'S ABOUT 5% OF THE MASS THAT COULD BE
EXEMPTED WITH A 10,000 SQUARE FOOT BUILDING.
SO IT DOESN'T SPEAK TO HEIGHT. IT DOESN'T GIVE ANY PARAMETERS
AROUND WHAT IS SMALL. BUT WHEN YOU LOOK AT THE SIZE
AND SCALE OF THE BUILDING OR THE SIZE AND SCALE OF A
WIRELESS FACILITY, THIS FALLS WITHIN WHAT IS A SMALL
FACILITY. I ALSO JUST WANT TO BRIEFLY
ADDRESS BECAUSE I JUST FEEL BAD.
SOMEONE MENTIONED THAT AT&T WAS UNTOWARD IN PROVIDING DRAFT
FINDINGS TO PLANNING STAFF THAT IT'S PART OF AN APPLICATION
THAT'S COMMON, THAT IS NOT UNTOWARD OF OF PLANNING STAFF
TO ASK FOR THAT OR RECEIVE THAT FROM AT&T.
IT'S PART OF THE APPLICATION. >> SO AS TO THE SPECIFIC ISSUES
THAT HAVE BEEN RAISED TODAY, NO ONE REALLY SPOKE ABOUT
GEOLOGICAL ISSUES. IT WAS DISCUSSED PREVIOUSLY
IN A BUNCH OF LETTERS. THE SITE WHERE IT'S LOCATED IS
OUTSIDE THE LANDSLIDE ZONE. WE HAVE AN EXPERT GEOLOGICAL
ENGINEER THAT EXPLAINED THAT THERE WILL NOT BE IMPACTS TO
STABILITY, GROUNDWATER OR FILL SOILS.
>> HISTORICALLY RESOURCES THE NEARBY CHURCH IS NOT A HISTORIC
RESOURCE. THE NEIGHBORHOOD IS NOT A
DESIGNATED HISTORIC RESOURCE EITHER.
TODAY A LOT OF CONCERN WAS RAISED ABOUT BIOLOGICAL ISSUES.
JOSH HARDY EXPLAINED THERE'S NO SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE OF AN
IMPACT TO BIOLOGICAL RESOURCES .
THE PROJECT SITE IS NOT IN THE MAY 3RD AREA OF GLEN CANYON
PARK. EVEN IF IT WAS, WE CONTEND THAT
AN MAY THREE AREA IS NOT AN AREA OF CRITICAL CONCERN WHICH
IS THE LANGUAGE THAT PRECLUDES THE EXEMPTION OR SEQUA.
THERE'S ALSO JUST A DISCUSSION THAT ANIMALS DON'T KNOW WHERE
ZONES GO. THEY COULD BE OUTSIDE OF THE
ZONE. THAT'S TRUE.
BUT THAT THE ONLY REASON YOU CAN'T APPLY AN EXEMPTION IS IF
YOU'RE WITHIN A DESIGNATED AREA OF CRITICAL BIOLOGICAL CONCERN
WHICH AGAIN THIS SITE IS NOT AS TO CONCERN ABOUT THE TREES.
WE HAVE A CERTIFIED EXPERT ARBORIST WHO LOOKED AT THE
IMPACT OF THE SITE INCLUDING THE CONSTRUCTION INCLUDING THE
USE OF CONSTRUCTION EQUIPMENT AND CONCLUDED THAT THERE'S ONLY
ONE TREE CLOSE ENOUGH TO MAYBE BE AFFECTED AND THAT TREES ROOT
STRUCTURE WILL NOT BE ADVERSELY AFFECTED BY CONSTRUCTION OF THE
SITE. >> SOME OTHER ISSUES THAT
RECENTLY CAME UP THE GENERAL PLAN TALKING ABOUT THE POLICE
ACADEMY MOVING. THERE'S NO SPECIFIC PLAN FOR
THE POLICE ACADEMY TO MOVE. >> THERE IS A DISCUSSION ABOUT
THE IMPACT ON PARKS. THE SITE IS NOT IN A PARK.
IT'S IN A PUBLIC FACILITY BUT NOT IN A PARK.
THERE ARE MULTIPLE OTHER INSTANCE IS OF WIRELESS
FACILITIES NEAR RESIDENCES NEAR PARKS.
TWO OF THOSE THAT THEY CITE. ONE IN GOLDEN GATE PARK, ONE
NEAR THE PALACE OF FINE ARTS THAT'S BEEN DISCUSSED WHICH I
BELIEVE ONE FACILITY IS 80FT TALL AND ONE IS 130FT TALL.
>> THERE ARE OTHER EXAMPLES OF SIMILAR SITING THAT HAVE
ALREADY OCCURRED AND LIKE THAT DON'T SELL A PARK IN OTHER
AREAS OF CALIFORNIA AS WELL. >> MOREOVER, RESIDENTIAL AREAS
COMMONLY HAVE WIRELESS FACILITIES IN THEM.
SAN FRANCISCO IS NOT ALONE IN PERMITTING WILDLIFE WIRELESS
FACILITIES IN RESIDENTIAL AREAS.
>> JUST TO GIVE YOU TWO EXAMPLES TO HAVE THEM IN THE
RECORD 2919 SOUTH KING STREET IN SAN JOSE IS AN EXAMPLE
AND TWO 3 OR 500 CRISTO DEL REY IN CUPERTINO IS ANOTHER
EXAMPLE. >> WE AGREE WITH PLANNING STAFF
THAT THIS IS A CATEGORY ONE SITE.
WE DID GO AHEAD AND PRODUCE IN ALTERNATIVES ANALYSIS THAT
WAS ALREADY DISCUSSED. >> SO THIS IS IN FACT NECESSARY
TECHNOLOGY. YOU ALL RELY ON WIRELESS
FACILITIES. IT IS NECESSARY AND DESIRABLE
TO HAVE WIRELESS SERVICE AS TO FIRE.
AS THE APPELLANT'S LETTER ADMITS, THIS IS NOT IN A
WILDLAND WILDFIRE URBAN INTERFACE AREA.
>> AS TO FIRE INVESTIGATOR OR ALL DAGS DECLARATION THAT WAS
SUBMITTED HIS POINT WAS NOT THAT SAN FRANCISCO WAS NOT
WINDY. HIS POINT WAS THAT THE WIND
IN THOSE OTHER FIRES THAT THE APPELLANT'S HAD CITED IS VERY
DIFFERENT. THOSE WERE DRY HOT SANTA ANA
WINDS. SAN FRANCISCO EXPERIENCES VERY
COLD WET COASTAL WINDS. I LIVE SIX BLOCKS AWAY FROM THE
SITE. I WILL ATTEST VERY COLD, VERY
WINDY. >> WHAT HE WAS ALSO EXPLAINING
IS THAT THE REASON THOSE FIRES STARTED HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH
WIRELESS EQUIPMENT. IN EACH OF THOSE CASES IT WAS
EITHER EDISON OR OTHER POWER PROVIDER.
THEIR WIRES EITHER SPARKING DRY GRASS, OTHER POLES, OTHER LOOSE
WIRES IN EVERY SINGLE ONE. THERE WAS NO EQUIPMENT OF A
FIRM TELECOMMUNICATION PROVIDER INVOLVED.
LASTLY, BECAUSE I THINK I'M GOING TO GET CUT OFF THE
CONCERN ABOUT THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT THAT YOU
GUYS HAVE RAISED THE STANDARD IS IN TERMS OF A GAP IN SERVICE
IF THERE IS RELIABLE IN-BUILDING SERVICE.
THAT IS WHAT FEDERAL COURTS RECOGNIZE AS A GAP IN SERVICE.
IT'S NOT A COMPLETE LACK OF SERVICE.
IT'S NOT IF YOU HAVE A WEAK SERVICE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
COULD DON'T GO AWAY. >> ALTHOUGH THIS MIGHT BE THIS
COULD BE A CAMMY QUESTION. BUT THIS QUESTION I WAS GOING
BACK AND FORTH WHY DOESN'T YOUR DOESN'T AT&T ALTERNATIVE
ANALYSIS WILL ALSO LOOK AT ALTERNATIVE TECHNOLOGIES.
>> SO UNDER FEDERAL LAW ALTERNATIVE TECHNOLOGIES IS NOT
AN ALTERNATIVE THAT THE AGENCY CAN REQUIRE BE CONSIDERED.
>> BUT THE OTHER REASON HERE IS BECAUSE YOU CAN'T USE DAS
TECHNOLOGY DISTRIBUTED ANTENNA SYSTEMS FOR FIRSTNET AND AT&T
DOES HAVE A MANDATE TO PROVIDE FOR A SELECTED FIRSTNET
TECHNOLOGY WHICH I KNOW THERE'S BEEN DEBATE AS TO WHETHER IT'S
USED OR NOT. IT IS USED I THINK THERE'S
SOMEONE FROM FIRSTNET WHO WILL SPEAK TO THAT BUT THAT IS ONE
OF THE MAIN REASONS YOU CANNOT USE THAT AND PROVIDE FIRSTNET.
>> AND THIS MIGHT BE MORE OF A QUESTION FOR BLACKSTONE BUT
I'VE HEARD THERE'S VERY OBVIOUS LARGE FACILITIES GENERALLY
IN THE NEIGHBOR. I MEAN THERE'S SUTRO, THERE'S
CHRISTMAS TREE POINT. WHY ARE THOSE NOT ADEQUATE TO
REACH THESE AREAS? >> EITHER THEY'RE NOT AVAILABLE
BECAUSE WE HAVE BEEN LOOKING FOR TEN YEARS AND IF THAT WERE
POSSIBLE WE DEFINITELY WOULD HAVE CONSIDERED IT.
I WILL SAY THE AREAS THAT WE NEED TO COVER I DON'T KNOW THAT
I KNOW I DON'T THINK THAT SUTRO WOULD BUT I DON'T KNOW
CHRISTMAS TREE POINT THAT I'M SORRY I CAN'T HELP YOU THERE
BUT THIS WAS THE ONLY SITE THAT WE COULD FIND WHERE WE HAD
SOMEBODY WHO NOT ONLY ENCOURAGED US TO SITE THERE BUT
WOULD ALLOW IT AVAILABLE INCLUDES WHETHER OR NOT IT CAN
BE LEASED AND WE DO PAY AND THE CITY IS A VERY EXPENSIVE
LANDLORD. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. WE WILL I DON'T THINK I HAVE
ANY OTHER COLLEAGUES IN THE QUEUE.
>> SO IF THERE ARE MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
SPEAK IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL, PLEASE LINE UP OVER AT
YOUR RIGHT MY LEFT AND NOT ON CLERK LET'S START PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
IF YOU COME UP TO THE PODIUM YOU WILL SEE THAT THERE IS A
TIMER ON THE PODIUM TO HELP YOU.
THE FIRST BELL WILL LET YOU KNOW YOU HAVE 30S TO WRAP UP
YOUR COMMENTS AND THEN THE FINAL BELL WILL RING.
PLEASE KEEP YOUR COMMENTS WITHIN THAT TWO MINUTE TIME
FRAME. HATE TO INTERRUPT YOU BUT WE
WILL. AND AGAIN AS THE PRESIDENT
SPOKE THIS IS FOR THOSE WHO ARE IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL OR
IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT. THIS IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO
PROVIDE COMMENT TO THE BOARD. WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER.
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS CHRIS DEMARCO.
I REPRESENT FIRST NET FOR THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA.
I'M HERE IN FRONT OF YOU TODAY IN SUPPORT OF THIS TOWER
BECAUSE PUBLIC SAFETY HAS ASKED ME AND I'M RESPONSIBLE TO MAKE
SURE THAT THEY HAVE THE COVERAGE THEY NEED WHEN THEY
RESPOND TO DISASTERS IN THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA IN THIS
PARTICULAR AREA HAS BEEN A KNOWN GAP FOR PUBLIC SAFETY.
AS YOU'RE PROBABLY AWARE, FIRSTNET IS THE ONLY PUBLIC
PRIVATE PARTNERSHIP APP THE ONLY PUBLIC SAFETY NETWORK
IN THE UNITED STATES WHICH IS CODIFIED BY LAW.
IT IS NOT BEST FOR IT IS NOT A COMMERCIAL NETWORK.
FIRSTNET IS PART OF AT&T BUT ONCE AGAIN IT'S THE ONLY PUBLIC
SAFETY NETWORK IN THE NATION. WITH THAT BEING SAID IN THIS
AREA, SEVERAL LIVE FIRE EMS CURRENTLY DO NOT HAVE THE
RESOURCES THEY NEED TO PERFORM THEIR JOB DUTIES IN A DISASTER
OR A SIMPLE 911 CALL. SO I'M HERE TO ASK YOU TO
SUPPORT THE TOWER MOVING FORWARD.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> KRISTINE MERCADO. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
>> HELLO. GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS MR. VAN HORN AND I'M A LOCAL RESIDENT AND AN
ENGINEER. I WANT TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF
THE PROPOSED AT&T INSTALLATION AT 350 AMBER STREET.
FROM A RELIABILITY AND PUBLIC SAFETY PERSPECTIVE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WE'VE ALL SEEN SITUATIONS WHERE POWER OUTAGES
OR GRID DISRUPTIONS HAPPEN. AND WHEN THESE SITUATIONS
OCCUR, WHETHER THAT BE DUE TO WEATHER OR MAINTENANCE ISSUES,
COMMUNICATION SYSTEMS BECOME EVEN MORE CRITICAL.
CELLULAR NETWORKS ARE OFTEN THE ONLY WAY PEOPLE CAN RECEIVE
EMERGENCY SERVICE, RECEIVE ALERTS OR COORDINATE WITH
FAMILY AND NEIGHBORS. FROM AN ENGINEERING STANDPOINT,
MODERN WIRELESS SITES ARE DESIGNED WITH BACKUP POWER
AND REDUNDANCY SO THEY CAN CONTINUE OPERATING WHEN THE
ELECTRIC GRID DISTRESSED. IN AN AREA LIKE DIAMOND HEIGHTS
FILLING COVERAGE GAPS MAKES THE ENTIRE NETWORK EVEN MORE
RESILIENT. THIS PROJECT ISN'T JUST ABOUT
CONVENIENCE. IT'S ABOUT ENSURING OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD STAYS CONNECTED WHEN IT MATTERS MOST.
I ENCOURAGE THE BOARD TO REJECT THE APPEALS AND APPROVE THE 350
NUMBER APPLICATION. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HI ALL MY NAME IS MIKE
WALDMAN AND I'M A PROUD SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT.
>> I'M HERE IN SUPPORT OF THE AT&T INSTALLATION AT 350 AMBER
STREET BECAUSE RELIABLE WIRELESS SERVICE BECAUSE
RELIABLE WIRELESS SERVICE HAS BECOME AN ESSENTIAL UTILITY
ESPECIALLY AT TIMES WHEN OTHER SYSTEMS AREN'T ALWAYS
DEPENDABLE. >> THANKS, JEANIE.
WHEN THERE ARE POWER OUTAGES OR GRID ISSUES PEOPLE STILL NEED
TO COMMUNICATE TO ACCESS EMERGENCY INFORMATION, MANAGE
PAYMENTS, COORDINATE TRANSPORTATION OR SIMPLY CHECK
ON LOVED ONES. >> STRONG SO CELLULAR
INFRASTRUCTURE HELPS ENSURE THAT ONE SYSTEM DOESN'T FEEL
JUST BECAUSE ANOTHER ONE DOES. >> FOR A MODERN CITY, RESILIENT
COMMUNICATIONS ARE A MATTER OF EQUITY AND PREPAREDNESS.
>> THIS PROPOSAL IS A PRACTICAL STEP TOWARD KEEPING DIAMOND
HEIGHTS AND THE SURROUNDING NEIGHBORHOODS CONNECTED
AND FUNCTIONAL EVEN DURING DISRUPTIONS.
>> I URGE THE CITY TO MOVE THIS FORWARD.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MAYOR WALTMAN FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. JUST WANT TO REMIND THE PUBLIC
THERE ARE NO OUTBURSTS PLEASE THAT WOULD PUT YOU OUT OF ORDER
. >> WELCOME, SIR, AND GOOD
AFTERNOON TO BARRISTERS. MY NAME IS RICARDO SUAREZ, SAN
FRANCISCO RESIDENT FOR THE LAST 50 YEARS DAMON HEIGHTS RESIDENT
FOR THE LAST 24 YEARS. I LOVE OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
THE ONLY PROBLEM IS THAT WE HAVE THE WORST CELLULAR
COVERAGE ANYWHERE. I'M A LONGTIME AT&T SUBSCRIBER
AND I'M VERY EXCITED THAT WE'LL BE GETTING A WIRELESS SITE
SERVER AREA. SO I'M HERE TODAY IN STRONG
SUPPORT OF THIS NEW INFRASTRUCTURE.
MY APARTMENT COMPLEX IS A FEW BLOCKS FROM THE PLAN SITE AND I
COULDN'T BE MORE EXCITED ABOUT FINALLY GETTING SERVICE AROUND
THE SAFEWAY STORE ON DIAMOND HEIGHTS BOULEVARD.
NOT ONLY IS IT PROBLEMATIC SOMETIMES ON UBER AND LYFT
DRIVERS LOSE THEIR COVERAGE AND THEY CAN'T FIND USER GPS
BUT IT'S ALSO A HUGE PUBLIC SAFETY ISSUE.
>> WE HAVE A NUMBER OF SCHOOLS DAYCARE CENTERS, RETAIL SPACES
AND CHURCHES IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
WE NEED TO HAVE RELIABLE CELL PHONE COVERAGE IN THE EVENT OF
EMERGENCY WHICH IS CURRENTLY NOT THE CASE.
I URGE YOU TO SUPPORT THIS WIRELESS SITE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
NICASIO SUAREZ. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE. >> >> GOOD AFTERNOON, EVERYONE
. >> MY NAME IS STEVE.
I AM A 40 PLUS 40 YEAR PLUS RESIDENT IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I
SUPPORT THIS PROJECT FOR MANY REASONS BOTH PROFESSIONALLY
AND PERSONALLY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC HERE TO PROVIDE COMMENT TO THE BOARD
IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL OR IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT?
NOW'S YOUR OPPORTUNITY. >> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED AND WE WILL INVITE THE APPELLANT TO
PRESENT A REBUTTAL ARGUMENT. >> YOU HAVE UP TO THREE MINUTES
. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
CATHERINE DODD AGAIN AND DIAMOND HEIGHTS COMMUNITY
ASSOCIATION. LET ME ADDRESS SOME OF THE
ISSUES THAT WERE RAISED. THE THE SITE OF THE PAD THAT
IT'S ON IS NOT THE ISSUE. THE SITE OF THE GIANT ANTENNA
STRUCTURE ABOVE IT IS CURRENTLY AT 700 CUBIC FEET SITTING 20FT
ABOVE THE TREES. >> YOU CAN'T IGNORE THAT SITE.
AT&T IN THEIR PLANS TURNED IN ON FEBRUARY 2ND.
>> LOOKS LIKE THEY INTEND TO ADD A SECOND ANTENNA STRUCTURE
THAT WOULD DOUBLE THAT BULKY SITE.
>> SO THE. SO THAT'S ONE THING IN TERMS OF
THE NATURAL RESOURCES. >> WE SUBMITTED TO NATURALISTS
TODAY YOU HEARD FROM A PREPARED ECOLOGIST AND BIOLOGIST BIRD IS
FLY AND LIVE IN THOSE BUSHES. >> NO, THEY DON'T NECESSARILY
LIVE WITHIN THAT BOUNDARY AREA BUT THOSE TREES SURROUND THE
POLICE ACADEMY AND AND BIRD COLLISIONS ARE A SERIOUS
PROBLEM THERE DOCUMENTED IN THE LITERATURE.
>> THE QUESTIONS ABOUT SIMILAR TOWERS OF THIS SIZE THE TOWER
THAT WAS JUST APPROVED AT PALACE OF FINE ARTS IS IN THE
PARKING LOT BEHIND IT YOU'LL SEE IT.
>> YOU CAN'T EVEN SEE IT AS YOU DRIVE TOWARD THE GOLDEN GATE
BRIDGE. >> IT'S NOT ON THE RESIDENTIAL
SIDE. IT'S IN THE PARKING LOT SIDE.
IT'S NOT NEAR RESIDENCES AND FRANKLY THE PALACE OF FINE
ARTS IS SURROUNDED BY A LAKE. SO THIS IS NOT IT'S NOT A
COMPARABLE COMPARISON. THE OTHER SITE THAT WAS
IDENTIFIED WAS THE GOLDEN GATE PARK NEAR THE SOCCER FIELDS.
AGAIN, NO RESIDENCES NEARBY. >> SO WHICH IS WHY YOU HEAR
SOME SO MUCH FROM THE RESIDENCES THAT SITE THAT WAS
BROUGHT UP BY THE ATTORNEY SAID THAT THEY PRESENTED A SAN DIEGO
CASE THAT'S A 40 FOOT POLE ON A ON A CANYON BUT IT'S A 40 FOOT
POLE COVERED IN PLASTIC FAKE TREE NOT COMPARABLE TO 104 FOOT
POLE ABOVE OUR PARKS. >> THE ALTERNATIVE ANALYSIS
THEY DIDN'T CONSIDER THE CORPORATION YARD ACROSS THE
CANYON AT THE END OF THE PARKING LOT FOR THE FOR THE
ATHLETIC FIELDS WERE THERE NO WHERE THERE'S LOTS OF ROOM, NO
TREES, THERE'S NO ONE LIVING ABOVE IT.
IT'S NOT NEAR ANY PEOPLE OR STRUCTURES OR CHILDREN.
>> THEY DIDN'T CONSIDER LOOKING AT THE BEHIND THE JUVENILE
JUSTICE SYSTEM WHERE THERE'S A LOT OF PUBLIC SPACE.
THE IDEA THAT WE'RE GETTING A LOT OF MONEY FROM AT&T.
THE AVERAGE RENT IS ABOUT $31,000 A YEAR JUST IMAGINE HOW
MUCH MONEY THEY'RE GOING TO MAKE.
I'M GOING TO LIMIT MY COMMENTS ON ON THE ON THE OTHER THINGS
AT THIS POINT I THINK THE MAP YOU SAW HAS THOSE BLUE AREAS
THE MAJORITY OF THOSE ARE GLEN CANYON AND CHRISTOPHER PARK.
>> WE DON'T NEED INDOOR CELL COVERAGE IN GLEN CANYON
AND CHRISTOPHER PARK. >> YOU'RE NOT LOOKING AT THE
MAPS. YOU'RE BEING AGAIN MISLED BY
AT&T PROPAGATED MAPS COMPLAINING ABOUT COMPLAINING
ABOUT COVERAGE NEAR THE CHURCH AND SAFEWAY.
THEY DECLINE BOTH SAFEWAY AND BOTH CHURCHES DECLINED
HAVING AN ANTENNA SO THEY'RE OBVIOUSLY NOT WORRIED ABOUT IT.
>> SO LET ME JUST SAY THIS AS VOLUNTEERS AND AS NEIGHBORS WE
HAVE WORKED TO SPEAK TRUTH TO CORPORATE POWER AND MISLEADING
INFORMATION. >> WE THE WHOLE ISSUE OF
FIRSTNET FIRSTNET SELLS BOOSTERS FOR RURAL AREAS.
THEY DON'T HAVE MACRA TOWERS IN ALL RURAL AREAS.
>> THEY SELL BOOSTERS. WE DON'T NEED A MACRO TOWER TO
GET FIRSTNET WHICH IS PART OF AT&T BUSINESS PLAN THAT THE
PLANNING COMMISSIONERS WERE MISLED ABOUT FIRST.
NOW THEY WERE MISLED ABOUT 911. VERIZON AND T-MOBILE MANAGED TO
HAVE COVERAGE WITHOUT GIANT MACRO TOWERS SAID IT 28
SECONDS. OKAY LET ME JUST END BY SAYING
THEY ACCEPTED AT&T STATEMENT AS THEY'VE EXHAUSTED EVERYTHING WE
CAN. WE RELY ON OUR ELECTED
OFFICIALS FOR MORE THE BOARD THE BOARD HAS A CLEAR AUTHORITY
AND AND DISCRETION TO REVERSE THE PROJECTS AND THE PROJECT
PROJECTS AND GRANT THE APPEALS APPEALS AND OUR GROUP'S APPEALS
AND PREVENTING MACRO TOWER DENSIFICATION THROUGHOUT THE
CITY. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU. >> MS. DOT, BEFORE YOU RUN OFF
I THINK YOU HEARD SORT OF THE TENOR OF MY QUESTIONS TO
PLANNING STAFF AND SO I THINK PROBABLY HAVE A SENSE OF WHERE
I'M INCLINED TO GO WITH THIS. I DON'T THINK THIS IS AS I'VE
SAID EXACTLY YET TRADITIONAL CONDITIONAL USE NECESSARY
AND DESIRABLE QUESTION I THINK IT REALLY IS I THINK WE ARE
IN TELECOMMUNICATION TELECOM ACTS LAND AND SO I DO THINK
THAT THESE TWO QUESTIONS THAT I'M SORT OF ASKING ABOUT OUR
KIND ARE LIKE PROBABLY THE CORE OF WHETHER WE WOULD HAVE ANY
SHOT IN DEFENDING THIS IN A LAWSUIT WHICH WOULD BE LIKELY I
THINK. AND SO SO THE FIRST OF THEM,
YOU KNOW, IS THIS QUESTION OF THE GAP IN COVERAGE AND I DON'T
THINK IT QUITE SATISFIES THAT TO SAY THE GAP IN COVERAGE
ISN'T ISN'T THAT GREAT OR IT'S ONLY IN THESE PARTICULAR AREAS
OR IT'S WORSE THAN THAT IN THE SAFE WAY PARKING LOT AND THEY
SORT OF DESERVE IT BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT YOU KNOW YOU KNOW
THEY'RE NOT ALLOWING I MEAN I THINK THE TEST FROM FROM THAT A
COURT I MEAN I'M NOT A JUDGE I DON'T KNOW BUT I THINK THAT
WHAT AT&T WOULD BE ASKED WOULD BE TO DID THEY IN THE RECORD
SHOW THAT THERE IS AN ACTUAL GAP IN THE AREAS THAT THEY'RE
TRYING TO COVER AND IT SEEMS TO ME LIKE LIKE THEY'VE SHOWN THAT
AND BEFORE YOU RESPOND TO THAT ON THE OTHER PRONG, THEN THEY
HAVE TO SHOW WHETHER THEY'VE LOOKED AT ALTERNATIVES AND THEY
DEFINITELY HAVE SHOWN IN THE RECORD THAT THEY'VE LOOKED AT
ALTERNATIVES, THEY'VE LOOKED AT OTHER SITES AND THEY'VE GOTTEN
A LOT OF NO'S. THERE SEEMS TO BE SOME
SUGGESTION I THINK FROM FROM THE APPELLANTS THAT THEY SHOULD
HAVE LOOKED AT ALTERNATIVE TECHNOLOGIES.
WE'VE HEARD TWO THINGS ABOUT THAT.
ONE WE'VE HEARD FROM AT&T IS LAWYER THAT NO, WE DON'T NEED
TO LOOK AT ALTERNATIVE TECHNOLOGIES.
THAT'S NOT THE TEST. THE TEST IS LOCATION AND WE'VE
ALSO HEARD FROM THEM AND FROM FIRSTNET THAT NO, THEY THEY
CAN'T DO WHAT THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO DO USING SAY DISTRIBUTED
ANTENNA SYSTEMS. THAT'S NOT VIABLE.
THEY HAVE TO DO IT THIS WAY IF THEY'RE GOING TO MEET THEIR
OBLIGATIONS UNDER THE UNDER THEIR FIRSTNET AS A AS A
FIRSTNET PROVIDER. SO I GUESS I JUST TO ME THOSE
ARE PRETTY COMPELLING AND IS SORT OF I MEAN I JUST WANTED TO
GIVE YOU THE OPPORTUNITY IF YOU WANT TO TRY TO ADDRESS EITHER
OF THOSE TWO THINGS THAT SEEM PRETTY IMPORTANT TO ME.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MAILMAN FIRST OF ALL, THE
ALTERNATIVE ANALYSIS THEY LOOKED AT PRIVATE SITES
AND PRIVATE THEY GOT TURNED DOWN BY PRIVATE OWNERS.
>> THEY DID NOT LOOK AT ALL THE PUBLIC SITE THAT WAS AVAILABLE.
I JUST CITED ONE ACROSS ON O'SHAUGHNESSY IN THE AREA ABOVE
THE JUVENILE JUSTICE SYSTEM REGARDING FIRSTNET FIRSTNET ON
THEIR WEB SITE YOU CAN BUY A BOOSTER FOR YOUR FIRSTNET
PRODUCT SO IT IT DOESN'T REQUIRE FOR A TEN STORY MACRO
TOWER AND NEXT ON THAT LITERALLY ON THE FENCE LINE OF
TWO PARKS IT'S NOT WE'RE NOT TALKING IN A PARK IN THE
PARKING LOT. WE'RE TALKING IN PARKING SPACES
BEHIND THE POLICE ACADEMY ON THE FENCE LINE AND THE BORDER
OF THE PARKS. >> I'M FORGETTING THE OTHER
QUESTION. I APOLOGIZE.
>> IT WAS GAP IN COVERAGE GAP IN COVERAGE.
SO WE IDENTIFIED THAT, NELSON SAID THEY DID A DRIVE TEST
BECAUSE I DON'T BELIEVE THE COMPUTER TABULATED MAPS BECAUSE
IF YOU LOOK AT THE WEBSITES FOR AT&T, FOR VERIZON, YOU LOOK AT
WHAT AT&T SUBMITS TO FCC, THEY ALL SAY THERE'S 100% COVERAGE
AND THEN AT&T SAYS OH WELL THAT'S THAT'S JUST WHAT WE
SUBMIT. >> THAT'S WHAT THEY SAID IN THE
PLANNING COMMISSION MEANING THAT THE AND I'VE BEEN TOLD
THAT THE COURT WILL UPHOLD THAT A VERY RELATIVELY WEAK SIGNAL
WHICH IS WHAT HAMMON EDISON IDENTIFIED IN SOME AREAS IS
CONSIDERED A GAP IN COVERAGE. THERE ARE OTHER WAYS TO BOOST
THAT GAP IN COVERAGE. THE POLICE ACADEMY BEGGED US TO
COME. WELL, THE POLICE ACADEMY IS
IN THE SHADOW IT THE POLICE ACADEMY COULD HAVE PUT A COULD
HAVE PUT A BOOSTER INSIDE THE POLICE ACADEMY YEARS AGO THAT
WOULD HAVE IMPROVED THEIR SERVICE.
SO THIS IS NOT THE ONLY WAY TO DO THIS.
>> AND I JUST I JUST FEEL LIKE THE THE CAN I ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION? LET ME IN TERMS OF LAWSUITS,
THIS DECISION SHOULD NOT BE MADE ON WE'RE AFRAID THAT WE'RE
GOING TO GET SUED. SAN FRANCISCO GOT SUED BY THE
TOBACCO INDUSTRY. WE GOT SUED BY THE ALCOHOL
INDUSTRY. >> WE GOT WE'VE BEEN SUED.
WE GOT SUED BY THE PLASTIC BAG INDUSTRY.
>> WE'RE LIKELY TO HAVE TO FIGHT THE ULTRA PROCESSED FOOD
INDUSTRY. >> WE'RE WE'RE A CITY THAT
STANDS UP FOR PEOPLE FOR THEIR HEALTH AND WELFARE
AND WELL-BEING. >> WE ARE NOT SUPPOSED TO BEND
OVER AND SAY OH NO, NO, PRESIDENT TRUMP, PLEASE DON'T
SUE ME THIS IS A WE NEED TO STAND UP FOR THE NEIGHBORS.
>> WE ELECTED YOU. >> YOU'RE SWORN TO DEFEND US
AND YOU'RE NOT SWORN TO DEFEND CORPORATE TELECOM.
>> THANKS. ALL RIGHT.
ACURA SIDE. >> ALL RIGHT.
UNLESS COLLEAGUES HAVE ANY FURTHER QUESTIONS.
JENS, I'M I'M INCLINED TO CLOSE THE HEARING TO SAY CLOSED
HEARING OR DO YOU WANT TO LEAVE?
DID YOU WANT TO MAKE YOUR COMMENTS THAN SAY YOUR THINGS
DURING THE HEARING OR DO YOU SAY CLOSE THE HEARING AND THEN
WE'LL TALK EITHER WAY. LET'S LET'S LET'S SAY THAT
THESE HEARINGS HAVE BEEN HELD AND ARE NOW FILED.
>> I SURE. OKAY.
ALL RIGHT. >> SUPERVISOR JAN, YOU KNOW, I
JUST WANTED TO SAY I DO UNDERSTAND THE DILEMMA HERE.
CLEARLY WE HAVE WHEN I FIRST TOOK OFFICE WE HAD NEIGHBORS
IN REALITY HAVING AT&T WANT TO INSTALL A ANTENNA IN THE IN A
PRIVATE RESIDENCE WITH THE AGREEMENT THAT IT WAS ACTUALLY
WITH A PRIVATE PROPERTY OWNER AND WE THROUGH THE SAME PROCESS
THAT THE NEIGHBORS, YOU KNOW, APPEALED THIS AND I WAS
IN SUPPORTIVE OF THE CONSTITUENTS WHO DID THAT
BECAUSE IT WAS A PRIVATE RESIDENCE TOO.
AND SO I I THINK THAT I AM I'M SENSITIVE TO THE COMMUNITY
INPUT BUT I DO I RECOGNIZE WHAT PRESIDENT AND MADAM AND YOU
INDICATED IT IS RESULTS IN THE SETTLEMENT BUT IT DID ALSO
RESULT IT THAT THAT VERY ANTENNA IS STILL NOT INSTALLED
I JUST WANT TO SAY YOU KNOW WHILE THAT AT&T PROBABLY WAS
PERMITTED TO DO SO, IT NO LONGER SEEMS TO IN EXPRESS OR
MOVING FORWARD WITH THE INSTALLATION.
SO I JUST WANT TO PUT IT OUT THERE THAT I AM ALWAYS INCLINED
TO FIGHT AND PUSH BACK IN THIS INSTANCE TO ALLOW THE
OPPORTUNITY TO SORT OF HAVE THOSE CONVERSATIONS.
>> SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN I
WANT TO ASK PLANNING IF YOU WANTED TO SAY ANYTHING MORE
ABOUT ANY OF THE THINGS THAT I ASKED ABOUT.
THANK YOU PRESIDENT WHEN WE DO HAVE AN ANSWER TO SUPERVISOR
CHAN'S QUESTION ON THE SIZE OF THE PAD FOR THE PRESIDIO SITE
IT'S APPROXIMATELY 600FT2. >> 600FT2 IS A FOOTPRINT IS OLD
TANK. >> YES, THAT'S CORRECT.
YES. >> AND THEN WE DO HAVE CITY
ATTORNEY BRAD RAZZI AVAILABLE IF YOU HAD FURTHER QUESTIONS ON
THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT, DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSSI
I DON'T THE LAWYER FOR THE PROJECT SPONSOR I ANSWERED YOUR
QUESTION AND ABOUT THE ABILITY TO REQUIRE THEM TO LOOK AT
DIFFERENT TYPES OF TYPES OF TECHNOLOGY AND I AGREE WITH
THAT ANSWER YOU AGREE WITH THEIR ANSWER?
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
I DON'T SEE ANYONE ELSE IN THE QUEUE.
>> UH, ALL RIGHT. SO I MEAN I THINK I'VE SORT OF
INDICATED HOW I'M THINKING ABOUT THIS.
I DID VOTE ALONG WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THAT TO
GRANT THAT APPEAL AND THAT'S THAT NEAR THAT STORY HAS
ACTUALLY INFLUENCED MY MY THINKING.
I DID NOT REALIZE UNTIL THIS MOMENT THAT IT STILL HASN'T
BEEN INSTALLED. >> BUT I DO KNOW THAT THE THAT
AT&T NOTWITHSTANDING OUR VOTING TO GRANT THE APPEAL A YEAR
LATER WE APPROVED A SETTLEMENT GIVING THEM THE ABILITY TO DO
WHAT THEY HAD BEEN TRYING TO DO IN AN APPEAL PRETTY MUCH LIKE
THIS. SO I, I DO THINK THAT
ULTIMATELY I MEAN AT&T MAY CHOOSE NOT TO INSTALL THAT THEY
MAY FIND THAT THIS THAT THIS FACILITY IS TOO EXPENSIVE OR
THEY RUN INTO TOO MANY PROBLEMS ALONG THE WAY INSTALLING THIS.
BUT I, I DO THINK IT IS QUITE HARD UNDER THE
TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT TO SAY TO TO EFFECTIVELY PROHIBIT AT&T
OR ANY OTHER TELECOM PROVIDER FROM FROM PUTTING IN TELECOM
FACILITIES. >> I THINK IF WE WERE JUST
HAVING A WELL THERE'S DIFFERENT ISSUES HERE.
>> THERE'S A SECURE APPEAL ON THE SEQUEL APPEAL AND I SAID
THIS EARLIER THE NOTION THAT THIS PROJECT SHOULD REQUIRE AN
AIR IS SEEMS REALLY WEIRD AND NOT CORRECT TO ME.
AND SO I YOU KNOW, I CAN'T REALLY ACCEPT THAT, YOU KNOW,
WHETHER IT FALLS WITHIN THIS EXEMPTION EXACTLY.
I TEND TO BELIEVE THAT OUR PLANNING STAFF DO A PRETTY GOOD
JOB ON THEIR CQ ANALYSIS AND THEY'RE BEING ADVISED BY
GOOD LAWYERS IT IS TALL AND I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, MAYBE
REQUIRES LIKE A SLIGHTLY HEIGHTENED LEVEL OF ANALYSIS
BUT EVEN WITH THAT I THINK I CAN ACCEPT THAT THIS IS YOU
KNOW STILL FALLS WITHIN THAT EXEMPT EXEMPTION SO I'M NOT
INCLINED AT LEAST FOR MYSELF TO SAY THAT WE SHOULD OVERTURN THE
SECRET DETERMINATION HERE. I THINK THE Q IS A MUCH MORE
COMPLICATED AND HARDER QUESTION AND I THINK IF IT WEREN'T FOR
THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT I ACTUALLY STILL I STILL THINK IT
WOULD BE A HARD QUESTION BECAUSE I DO THINK THAT THERE'S
A I THINK IT IS A KNOWN THING THAT SERVICE IN THE HILLS ABOVE
SNOWY VALLEY AND THE CASTRO IS PRETTY BAD AND I HEAR FROM A
LOT OF CONSTITUENTS WHO EXPRESSED FRUSTRATION ABOUT THE
DIFFICULTY OF KEEPING CELL SERVICE AS THEY'RE EITHER
DRIVING AROUND THERE OR IN THEIR HOMES AND THAT IS IT.
>> THAT'S JUST A THING THAT COMES UP.
SO I'M I THINK ARGUING THAT THERE AREN'T GAPS IN COVERAGE
IS SORT OF FLIES IN THE FACE OF LIKE THE LIVED EXPERIENCE OF A
LOT OF MY CONSTITUENTS. AND I THINK THAT THE RECORD,
YOU KNOW, PROBABLY MEETS ANY KIND OF REQUIREMENT THAT AT&T
WOULD HAVE TO MAKE TO SHOW THAT THEY'VE THAT THERE IS THAT
THERE IS A GAP EVEN SO THERE'S A SIGNAL THERE IS AN IMPACT.
>> I DON'T KNOW IF IT'S I DON'T THINK IT'S A SIGNIFICANT
THERE'S THERE IS AN IMPACT A VISUAL MAINLY I THINK VISUAL
AND ESTHETIC IMPACT FOR PARTICULARLY FOR PEOPLE WHO
LIVE UP AROUND AROUND THE FACILITY AND I THINK IT'S
TOTALLY LEGITIMATE AND REASONABLE FOR PEOPLE TO BE
OBJECTING TO THIS. BUT THAT WOULD BE THE
TRADITIONAL BALANCING THAT WE WOULD BE DOING UNDER A REGULAR
OLD Q THE GREATER NEGATIVE IMPACT ON PEOPLE CLOSER THE
BROADER BENEFIT TO A LARGER COMMUNITY FURTHER AWAY THAT
WOULD BE BENEFITED FROM THE IMPROVED CELLULAR SERVICE?
I DON'T THINK WE EVEN GET NECESSARILY TO THAT QUESTION
BECAUSE I THINK THE TELECOM TEST FOR ME PROBABLY SETTLES
THIS PRETTY MUCH IN AT&T IS FAVOR NOW I HAVE LOOKED AT THIS
LOOKED AT THIS WITH PLANNING AND WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY
AND TRIED TO FIGURE OUT WHETHER, YOU KNOW, WITHOUT
REJECTING THE AT&T PROJECT IF THERE WERE ANY WAYS TO ADDRESS
ANY OF THE OTHER ISSUES THAT HAVE COME UP IN THIS APPEAL.
AND I GUESS I WOULD ASK THAT OUR SERGEANT AT ARMS HANDOUT
SOME PROPOSED ADDITIONAL CONDITIONS THAT COULD BE PUT ON
THIS PROJECT. I'M GOING TO ASK THAT MY
COLLEAGUES GRANT THE CONDITIONAL GRANT THE APPEAL I
GUESS BUT ONLY FOR THE PURPOSES OF MAKING THE AMENDMENT TO ADD
THESE ADDITIONAL CONDITIONS. ONE RELATED TO ADDITIONAL FIRE
DEPARTMENT INSPECTION AND REQUIRING THAT THEY INSPECT
THE PROJECT AND THAT THE THAT THE APPLICANT COMPLETE ANY
REASONABLE FIRE SAFETY RELATED RECOMMENDATIONS.
THE FIRE DEPARTMENTS AND RESTATING THAT THE PROJECT
INCLUDING POWERS TO THE POWER SOURCE AND COOLING FACILITY BE
OPERATED AT ALL TIMES WITHIN STATE AND LOCAL FIRE CODES
INCLUDING THE SPECIFIC REQUIREMENTS FOR CELLULAR
ANTENNA SITES AND PLACEMENT OF DIESEL GENERATOR GENERATORS.
I FEEL LIKE THAT'S ABOUT AS BELT AND SUSPENDERS AS WE CAN
GET TO PUT A FIRE CODE AND FIRE SAFETY PROVISION INTO THE
PLANNING CONDITIONS OF APPROVAL .
I'M ALSO GOING TO ASK THAT THE PROJECT SPONSOR HIRE AN
ARBORIST WHO'S TO TO PREPARE A TREE PROTECTION PLAN THAT
INCLUDES BEST MANAGEMENT PRACTICES AND THAT THERE BE A
THEY SAY THERE WILL BE NO TREES REMOVED.
WE'RE GOING TO ASK THAT AND THEY SHOULD BE HELD TO THAT
IF SOMEHOW IT TURNS OUT THAT A TREE IS REMOVED IT WOULD HAVE
TO BE WERE REPLACED THREE TO ONE WITH NEW TREES AS YOU KNOW
AS REQUIRED AND THE ARBORIST WOULD SORT OF I THINK PROVIDE
RECOMMENDATIONS ON HOW TO IMPLEMENT THAT.
AND THEN LASTLY WERE I'M GOING TO ASK MY COLLEAGUES TO REQUIRE
THAT THE PROJECT INCLUDING THE POWER SOURCE AND COOLING FOR
COOLING FACILITY BE OPERATING OPERATED AT ALL TIMES WITHIN
THE LIMITS OF SAN FRANCISCO'S NOISE CONTROL ORDINANCE SO THAT
ANY NOISE HEAR THAT IT IS ALSO A CONDITION OF THIS APPROVAL
THAT THEY THAT THEY MEET THE NOISE STANDARDS THAT WOULD
APPLY ANYWAY BUT AGAIN IT'S SORT OF A BELT AND SYSTEM
SUSPENDERS TO MAKE SURE THAT THAT WOULD APPLY.
I THOUGHT FOR A LONG TIME ABOUT TRYING TO INCLUDE SOME SORT OF
ESTHETICS REQUIREMENT AND ROUND AND AROUND AND AROUND WITH
PLANNING AND AT&T ABOUT WHETHER THIS IS REALLY THE BEST THAT
CAN BE DONE IN TERMS OF IN TERMS OF MAKING THIS AS NON
OBNOXIOUS AS POSSIBLE THE PLANNING SEEMS TO BELIEVE THAT
THE TREE IDEA AND YOU KNOW HIDING THIS WITH A TREE IS A
BAD IDEA. I'M I HAVE NO BASIS TO ARGUE
WITH THAT. THEY'VE ALSO REQUIRED THAT THIS
BE PAINTED BROWN AND THAT THAT WOULD BE POTENTIALLY LESS
INTRUSIVE THAN A WHITE OR A POLE AND THAT SEEMS REASONABLE.
AT&T I HAD ASKED ABOUT ALTERNATIVES FOR THE ANTENNA
THE THE SORT OF FACILITIES THEMSELVES AND WHETHER YOU
KNOW, THERE COULD BE FILM THAT WAS PUT ON THEM THAT WOULD MAKE
THEM LESS VISIBLE OR WOULD BE OTHER COLORS.
THEY SUBMITTED A PROPOSAL FOR THAT YESTERDAY TO PLANNING.
WE COULD REQUIRE IT HERE BUT I DON'T REALLY WANT TO DO THAT
WITHOUT CONSULTATION FROM THE YOU KNOW WITH IMPACT NEIGHBORS.
SO I'M NOT GOING TO PUT IN AN ESTHETICS REQUIREMENT BUT I
WOULD ASK ACTUALLY IF SOMEONE FROM AT&T COULD COME FORWARD
IT'S PROBABLY IN THIS BLACKSTONE YES.
>> SUPERVISOR YEAH. SO I MEAN UNTIL THIS POINT
AND IT MAY BE GOING FORWARD BECAUSE THERE ARE OTHER
POTENTIAL OTHER APPEAL OPPORTUNITIES I THINK YOU KNOW
APPELLANTS THE NEIGHBORS WHO OPPOSE THIS HAVE BEEN MOSTLY
FOCUSED ON TRYING TO KILL THIS PROJECT AND SO A CONVERSATION
ABOUT LIKE HOW TO MAKE THE POLE AS NON OBNOXIOUS AS POSSIBLE
HAS NOT BEEN ONE THAT I THINK MIGHT HAVE GONE VERY FAR.
I WOULD LIKE A COMMITMENT FROM YOU THAT IF THAT IS A
CONVERSATION THAT NEIGHBORS WANT TO HAVE THAT YOU WOULD BE
WILLING TO YOU AND AT&T WOULD BE WILLING TO HAVE THAT
CONVERSATION WITH ME IN MY OFFICE AND THE NEIGHBORS GOING
FORWARD TO LOOK AT THE OTHER POTENTIAL ALTERNATIVES AROUND
THINGS LIKE FILM AND CODING THAT COULD BE PUT OVER THE
FACILITIES AROUND THE COLOR OF THE POLE AROUND ANY OF THAT
STUFF. TO THE EXTENT THAT THE
NEIGHBORS HAVE A A CONSENSUS POSITION ON IT.
>> YEAH, ABSOLUTELY. WE'RE WILLING TO DISCUSS ANY
OPTIONS THAT YOU KNOW THAT WE COULD THAT WON'T HINDER OUR OUR
FOCUS WHICH IS TO GET THE SIGNAL OUT BUT WE'RE HAPPY TO
WORK WITH THEM ON PAINT COLOR FILM WHATEVER WE CAN DO TO MAKE
IT LESS OFFENSIVE TO THEM. >> OKAY.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU FOR THAT.
ALL RIGHT. >> SO THE FIRST THING THAT I
THINK I NEED TO DO AND I'M WILLING TO THE CITY ATTORNEY TO
MAKE SURE I GET THIS RIGHT IS I THINK I NEED TO AMEND ITEM 25
OF THE IS THAT RIGHT? 2025 DISAPPROVING CONDITIONAL
USE AUTHORIZATION. I THINK I NEED TO AMEND THAT
IN THE FORM THAT I HAVE HANDED OUT TO INCLUDE THESE ADDITIONAL
CONDITIONS. SO I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A
MOTION TO AMEND IT IN THAT YOU KNOW I'D LIKE I WOULD LIKE TO
MOVE TO MAKE THAT AMENDMENT AND I WOULD SEEK A SECOND
SECONDED BY DORSEY CAN WE TAKE THAT IN MOTION WITHOUT
OBJECTION COLLEAGUES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION TO AMEND
PASSES. >> OKAY.
AND THEN I WOULD LIKE TO UP MR. SC DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD
RUSSELL YEAH. I THINK YOU SHOULD DISPOSE OF
THE SEQUOIA APPEAL FIRST BEFORE ISSUING THE FINAL PERMIT.
BRILLIANT. THANK YOU SO ALL RIGHT.
>> SO ON THE SEQUEL APPEAL I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO
AFFIRM THE CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION DETERMINATION BY
APPROVING ITEMS 20 AND TABLING ITEMS 21 AND 22.
>> IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY CHAN?
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THAT MOTION ON THE
MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM 20 AND TABLE ITEMS 21 AND 22.
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO
WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN VOTING NO ALL RIGHT ITEM 20 IS APPROVED
AND ITEMS 21 AND 22 ARE TABLED AND THEN THAT BRINGS US BACK TO
2526 AND 2425 AND 2625 HAS BEEN AMENDED AND SO I WOULD LIKE TO
MAKE A MOTION TO PASS ITEM TO APPROVE ITEM 25 AS AMENDED
AND AND 26 AND TABLE 24. IS THERE A SECOND FOR THAT
SECONDED BY DORSEY MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON THAT MOTION ON THE MOTION TO TABLE ITEM 24 AND APPROVE ITEM
25 AS AMENDED AND 26 SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR OF FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
I WHAT I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT MANDEL MAN I
SUPERVISOR MILKER MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION ITEM 24 IS TABLED
ITEM AND ITEM 25 AS AMENDED AND ITEM 26 ARE PASSED.
ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM 12.
ITEM 12. MR. PRESIDENT IS THE RESET ITEM
SUPERVISOR FIELDER AND MR. PRESIDENT, I SHOULD SAY THERE
IS A MOTION ON THE FLOOR SECOND MADE MY SUPERVISOR FILNER
SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHEN THANKS, PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> I HAD SOME QUESTIONS FOR THE
SHERIFF OR WHOEVER IS PRESENT. >> THE SHERIFF IS PRESENT
CORRECT. HELLO?
I'M SORRY. WHAT WAS THE QUESTION AGAIN?
SUPERVISOR SHERIFF, I WILL HAVE A SERIES OF QUESTIONS SO THANK
YOU IN ADVANCE. SO FIRST OFF, WHAT KIND OF
INTOXICATED INDIVIDUALS WILL BE TAKEN TO THIS SITE?
IS IT PEOPLE INTOXICATED WITH ALCOHOL OR OPIOIDS OR SOMETHING
ELSE AND ASSESSMENT WILL BE MADE BY THE OFFICERS OR
DEPUTIES THAT ENCOUNTER THE INDIVIDUAL.
USUALLY IF THEY EXHIBIT SIGNS OF BEING UNDER THE INFLUENCE OF
EITHER ALCOHOL OR DRUGS, THERE'S A SERIES OF TESTS THAT
WE CONDUCT. THERE'S FIELD SOBRIETY TESTS.
THERE'S 11 550 WHICH REFERENCES THE HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE
SERIES OF TESTS WHICH YOU LOOK AT THE NYSTAGMUS IN AN
INDIVIDUAL'S EYES. THERE'S A SEVEN PART TEST THAT
IS CONDUCTED TO DETERMINE WHETHER OR NOT SOMEBODY IS
UNDER THE INFLUENCE CURRENTLY. IT'S NOT LIKE A MEASUREMENT OF
HOW MUCH IS IN THEIR SYSTEM. IT'S JUST AN ASSESSMENT OF
THEIR CURRENT STATE AND THEIR BEHAVIORS.
>> SO INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE INTOXICATED IN ANY WHICH WAY
THAT SHERIFFS DEEM THE ARREST YEAH, THE LAW ENFORCEMENT
OFFICER ON THE STREET. YES.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
WILL ARRESTEES BE DETAINED AT THIS FACILITY?
>> SO THE FACILITY IS DESIGNED SO THERE'S NO DOORS BARS HOLDS
THE DEPUTIES ARE ACTUALLY OUTSIDE THE FACILITY ONCE THEY
TAKE THE INDIVIDUAL FROM THE POLICE, THEY AREN'T PRESENT
INSIDE. THAT'S THE PURVIEW OF THE
ACTUAL CAREGIVERS AND THE PEOPLE THAT ARE MONITORING
THEIR CONDITIONS AS THEY ARE ALLOWED TO SOBER UP FROM THEIR
STATE. OKAY.
SO ARRESTEES WILL BE HELD AGAINST THEIR OWN WILL HERE ARE
NOT. SO THE CONCEPT IS THAT AN
INDIVIDUAL IS INTOXICATED OR UNDER THE INFLUENCE THEY'RE
BEING DETAINED UNDER THAT THEY'RE BEING TAKEN INTO
CUSTODY UNDER THAT ARE ARRESTED UNDER EITHER 647 F OR ANY OF
THE 11 UNDER TWO. THESE CHARGES THAT PERTAIN TO
SOMEBODY UNDER THE INFLUENCE IN THE PUBLIC, THEY'RE BROUGHT
TO THE FACILITY. THERE'S A TRIAGE DONE IN TERMS
OF THEIR CONDITION TO MAKE SURE THAT THEY WOULD BE ABLE TO
ENTER INTO THE FACILITY TO SOBER UP.
AND ONCE THAT IS DONE, THE OFFICERS ARE ALLOWED TO GO BACK
ON THEIR WAY. THEY'RE NOT BOOKED INTO
CUSTODY. THEY'RE HANDED OFF TO THE
CAREGIVERS AND THE HEALTH PROFESSIONALS AND THEY'RE
PLACED IN THE RECLINING CHAIRS UNTIL THEY CAN SOBER UP.
ONE THING WE DO IN THIS PROCESS IS SOMETHING CALLED THE 849 B
USUALLY WHEN AN INDIVIDUAL TAKES ABOUT FOUR HOURS OR SO TO
BECOME A LITTLE MORE LUCID AND SOBER, WE ISSUE WHAT IS
CALLED A CERTIFICATE OF RELEASE 849 B AND THAT ALLOWS THE
INDIVIDUAL TO LEAVE IN THIS PARTICULAR CASE WHEN THE
INDIVIDUAL IS BROUGHT THERE AND THEY ARE SOBERED UP,
THEY'RE NOT IN A JAIL, THEY ARE NOT BOOKED IN, THEY ARE NOT
BEHIND WALLS OR DOORS OR KEYS AND THEY'RE ALLOWED TO LEAVE OF
THEIR OWN FREE WILL ONCE THEY'VE BEEN 849 B THEY'RE
THERE VOLUNTARILY IF THEY CHOOSE NOT TO AND THEY LEAVE
THEN THEY LEAVE. THERE'S NO COMPULSION ONCE
THEY'RE BROUGHT TO THE CENTER OF KEEPING THEM THEY'RE
IN VOLUNTARILY. THANK YOU.
AT WHAT POINT WILL THEY RECEIVE AN 849 B AND THAT'S STILL
IN DISCUSSION BECAUSE IT DEPENDS ON THE STATE OF THE
INDIVIDUAL IF THEY ARE NOT CAPABLE OF UNDERSTANDING THAT
THEY'RE BEING RELEASED BECAUSE THEY'RE UNDER THE INFLUENCE,
THAT'S WHY WE USUALLY LET THEM SOBER UP FIRST OR HAVE TIME TO
REST AND THEN REPRESENT TO THEM IN THE JAILS.
IT'S VERY SPECIFIC TO A TIME FRAME WHEN WE KEEP CHECKING ON
THEM HERE THERE WOULD BE CONSTANT ATTENTION GIVEN TO
THEM WHICH WOULD MAKE THIS DYNAMICS SLIGHTLY DIFFERENT
THAN WHAT WE SEE IN THE JAILS RIGHT NOW.
>> THANK YOU. THAT LEADS TO MY NEXT QUESTION
WILL THERE BE LICENSE METAL CORE PROFESSIONALS AT THIS
FACILITY LIKE NURSES, DOCTORS WHO'S MAKING THIS ASSESSMENT?
I BELIEVE THAT THERE ARE GOING TO BE INDIVIDUALS LET ME BRING
MY UNDERSHERIFF UP SO SHE CAN GIVE YOU A BETTER UNDERSTANDING
OF WHAT THE STAFFING PLAN IS FOR THE CONTRACT OF PROVIDERS.
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS KATHERINE JOHNSON. I'M THE UNDERSHERIFF.
ONE OF THE REQUIREMENTS OF THE CONTRACT WAS THAT THERE WOULD
BE A LICENSE R.N. IN THE FACILITY 24 HOURS A DAY, SEVEN
DAYS A WEEK. THAT WAS ONE OF THE DETERMINING
FACTORS OF THIS ISSUE AND THE STAKEHOLDERS FROM THE VARIOUS
DEPARTMENTS TALKED ABOUT IT AND IT'S REALLY BASED ON THE
ASSESSMENT SKILLS THAT OUR INS HAVE THAT OTHER MEDICAL
PROFESSIONALS DO NOT. SO EVERY TWO HOURS WILL HAPPEN
BY AN R.N. WHO'S IN THE SOBERING CENTER THE ENTIRE TIME
24 HOURS A DAY, SEVEN DAYS A WEEK.
>> THERE'S OTHER CARE CASE MANAGERS.
>> THEIR PEER SPECIALIST IS WHAT THEY'RE CALLING THEM
AND THEN THERE'S SOME MEDICAL OVERSIGHT BY OKAY, SO ONE ONE
HOUR END AND THEN OTHER CASE MANAGERS.
>> ABSOLUTELY. AND PEER SPECIALIST
AND SHERIFF'S DEPUTIES WILL BE OUTSIDE OF THIS FACILITY THERE
THEY HAVE WHAT'S CALLED AN AREA OF RESPONSIBILITY, PART OF IT
IS TO CONDUCT ALSO GOOD NEIGHBOR POLICY SO THEY'LL BE
DOING FOOT PATROLS IN THE SURROUNDING AREA.
THEY WILL BE INTERIOR TO THE POINT WHERE THE INDIVIDUAL
COMES IN TO ASSURE THAT THEY'RE SAFE DURING TRIAGE AND THEN TO
ISSUE THE 849 BE AT WHATEVER POINT THAT HAPPENS WHEN THE
PERSON IS ABLE TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES AND THEIR PRIMARY
ROLE IS THE SAFETY OF THE STAFF ,THE CONNECTION STAFF AND THEN
THE FOOT PATROLS IN THE AREA. >> OKAY.
>> SO WILL THE NURSE PRACTITIONER THE REGISTERED
NURSE BE MAKING THE A 49 B ASSESSMENT?
>> THE MEDICAL PROVIDER WILL ASSESS WHEN THE PERSON IS ABLE
TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES. YES.
OKAY, GREAT. AND THEN THEY WILL RELAY THAT
TO THE SHERIFF. CORRECT?
>> GOT IT. HOW MANY PEOPLE ARE ENVISION
BEING IN THE CENTER AT ANY ONE POINT?
>> THE CENTER HAS A MAXIMUM CAPACITY OF 25.
>> OKAY. 25 PEOPLE FOR ONE HOUR AND AND
HOW MANY CASE MANAGERS THERE WILL BE SIX STAFF ALL TOGETHER.
>> SIX MEDICAL PROFESSIONALS, SIX MEDICAL PROFESSIONALS WILL
SIX CASE MANAGERS THAT ARE THAT WORK UNDER THE UMBRELLA OF THE
CONNECTIONS HOUSE. >> A CASE MANAGER IS NOT
NECESSARILY A MEDICAL PROFESSIONAL.
THAT'S CORRECT. ONE HOUR IN WHICH I WOULD
CONSIDER THE MEDICAL PROFESSIONAL, THE LICENSED
MEDICAL PROFESSIONAL AND SIX CASE MANAGERS MAXIMUM 25 PEOPLE
MAXIMUM UNDERSTOOD. >> IS THIS AN AUTHORIZED
SOBERING FACILITY? IT IS A NON LICENSED SOBERING
FACILITY. >> OKAY.
AND I JUST WALK ME THROUGH WHY WE WOULD OPERATE AS AN
UNLICENSED SOBERING FACILITY. SO THIS IS NOT A LOCAL
DETENTION FACILITY NOR IS IT A TEMPORARY HOLDING FACILITY.
THIS IS AN ALTERNATIVE TO JAIL OR AN ALTERNATIVE TO AN ED
VISIT. IT'S THE ABILITY TO PROVIDE
LINKAGES TO PEOPLE WHO DESPERATELY NEED THEM AND TO
HAVE DIRECT INTERVENTION. >> OKAY.
IT SOUNDS TO ME LIKE A SOBERING FACILITY.
>> WHY WOULDN'T WE OPERATE AS A SOBERING FACILITY?
AS I MENTIONED EARLIER, SUPERVISOR THE GROUNDS FOR
WHICH WE WOULD TAKE AN INDIVIDUAL INTO OUR CARE
AND BRING THEM TO THIS LOCATION WOULD NORMALLY BE A DELIVERY TO
THE JAIL ITSELF. WE ARE TRYING TO CREATE AN
OPTION THAT IS NOT JAIL FOR US TO BRING SOMEONE TO GET MORE
CARE FOR THEIR CURRENT CONDITION BECAUSE THEY'RE UNDER
THE INFLUENCE, BRING THEM OUT OF A PUBLIC SPACE WHERE THEY
MAY NOT BE ABLE TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES AND IT'S A COMPELLED
SITUATION. THEY'RE BEING ARRESTED.
THEY'RE BEING TAKEN INTO CUSTODY BUT INSTEAD OF BRINGING
THEM TO JAIL, WE'RE BRINGING THEM TO THIS CENTER AND IT'S
NOT A MEDICAL CARE FACILITY THAT WE'RE BRINGING THEM TO.
THIS IS A CENTER THAT IS GOING TO PROVIDE THE ABILITY TO HAVE
A SPACE TO SOBER UP UNDER CONSTANT SUPERVISION OF BOTH
THE MEDICAL STAFF MENTIONED THE NURSE AS WELL AS THE CASE
MANAGERS AND THE OTHER INDIVIDUALS ASSOCIATED WITH THE
SERVICES PROVIDED. WE'VE TRIED VERY HARD TO CREATE
A SITUATION WHERE DEPUTIES LAW ENFORCEMENT AREN'T A PART OF
THAT ENVIRONMENT SO THAT THEY DON'T FEEL THAT WE'RE THERE TO
KEEP THEM THERE ONCE THEY ARE 849 BE THEY'RE FREE TO LEAVE.
OUR HOPE OUR HOPE FOR THIS IS THAT AN INDIVIDUAL WHEN RESTING
AWAKENS FINDS HIMSELF IN THIS PLACE AND INSTEAD OF DECIDING
TO LEAVE DECIDES TO STAY A LITTLE LONGER AND REST A LITTLE
MORE AND MAYBE START TO BECOME MORE COGNIZANT OF SOME OF THE
SERVICES THAT ARE AVAILABLE, WE'RE TRYING TO CREATE THAT
KIND OF ENVIRONMENT INSTEAD OF WHAT WE DO CURRENTLY RIGHT NOW
WHICH IS WHEN SOMEONE'S INTOXICATED AND ARE BROUGHT TO
JAIL THEY'RE PLACED IN THE HOLDING CELL.
THEY'RE STILL CARED FOR IN TERMS OF SUPERVISION, MAKING
SURE THAT THEY'RE OKAY. BUT THERE'S NOT THE FOCUSED,
DETAILED, VERY INTENTIONAL SUPERVISION OF THAT INDIVIDUAL
AND THEN WHEN THEY'RE RELEASED THEY'RE RELEASED OFF ON THE
TASK RELEASED WHERE? INTO THE COMMUNITY THEY'RE JUST
RELEASED. OKAY.
WHEN THEY THIS IS WHAT USED TO BE CALLED SUPERVISOR AT THE
DRUNK TANK RIGHT WHERE SOMEBODY GOES STAYS FOR FOUR HOURS UP TO
EIGHT HOURS AND THEN THEY'RE RELEASED AND THEY'RE LITERALLY
GIVEN ALL THEIR PROPERTY BACK AND SENT OUT THE DOOR.
>> RIGHT. AND I'M HEARING THAT THIS IS A
PLACE TO CONNECT PEOPLE TO SERVICES BUT I'M NOT HEARING
THAT PEOPLE ARE GOING TO GET CONNECTED TO SERVICES.
I'M HEARING THAT THEY'RE GOING TO GET RETURNED TO THE STREET.
NO, OUR HOPE IS TO MAKE SURE THAT THEY CONNECT TO SERVICES
AND I BELIEVE THERE'S A WHOLE INFRASTRUCTURE THAT WE'RE GOING
TO HAVE AVAILABLE IN ORDER FOR THEM TO BE TRANSPORTED TO OTHER
PLACES, TRANSPORTED TO THINGS. ONE OF THE THINGS THAT WE'VE
STAFFED FOR IS MAKING SURE THAT THERE'S SOME SORT OF TRANSPORT
AVAILABLE TO MOVE THEM TO A SERVICE WHETHER IT'S A
RESIDENTIAL TREATMENT SERVICE, WHETHER IT'S A CLINIC, WHETHER
IT'S SOME OTHER SPACE THAT THEY CAN GO TO FOR ADDITIONAL CAN I
YEAH GO AHEAD AND SUPERVISOR IF I COULD JUST ADD WE'RE WORKING
ON THE CONNECTIONS NOW IN TERMS OF LINKAGES ONCE SOMEONE'S
RELEASED AND WHERE THEY WOULD GO AND WE'RE LOOKING AT
IDENTIFYING VERY SPECIFIC NEEDS THAT FIT THE INDIVIDUAL BECAUSE
NOT EVERYBODY IS PREPARED TO CONNECT TO A LINKAGE.
IT JUST DEPENDS ON THAT INDIVIDUAL ASSESSMENT.
SO THAT'S KEY IN THIS AND EVERY INDIVIDUAL WILL BE ASSESSED.
I JUST WANT TO GO BACK FOR A MINUTE TO YOUR QUESTION ABOUT
THE SOBERING CENTER. SO IT IS IN FACT A SOBERING
CENTER THAT'S NON-LICENSED BUT OTHER SOBERING CENTERS IN THE
CITIES ARE NON LICENSED. SOBERING CENTERS ARE NOT A
LICENSE FACILITY. IT'S A PLACE TO TAKE AN
INDIVIDUAL TO ALLOW AND THE TIME TO BECOME SOBER TO THE
POINT WHERE THEY CAN CARE FOR THEMSELVES BECAUSE THAT IS WHAT
THE LAW REQUIRES WHERE WE TAKE THE INDIVIDUAL REALLY DEPENDS
ON THE AVAILABILITY OF RESOURCES IN THE CITY AND SO
THIS IS JUST ONE MORE PLACE THAT WE'RE ABLE TO TAKE AN
INDIVIDUAL WHERE THEY COULD SOBER UP TO THE POINT WHERE
THEY'RE ABLE TO CARE FOR THEMSELVES AND WE CAN TRY
AND CONNECT THEM TO SOME LINKAGES WHICH IS A GAP A
SERVICE GAP THAT'S MISSING FROM THE JAIL.
>> MM HMM. UNDERSTOOD.
UNDERSTOOD THE CONCEPT OF SOBERING UP FROM THE
UNDERSTANDING OF ALCOHOL. BUT WHEN IT COMES TO FENTANYL
BEING SOBER FROM FENTANYL IS A COMPLETELY DIFFERENT THING THAN
BEING SOBER. BOTH HAVE WITHDRAWALS, SYMPTOMS
AND WITHDRAWING FROM OPIOIDS, BENZOS, WHATEVER YOU WHATEVER
HAS ALSO LIFE THREATENING CONSEQUENCES.
SO I'M JUST I'M I'M WANTING TO MY QUESTIONS ARE ALL ABOUT
WANTING TO MAKE SURE THAT PEOPLE HAVE THE CARE AND ARE
THEN NOT PUT BACK ONTO THE STREET AND INDEED ARE CONNECTED
TO THE HEALTH CARE SYSTEM IN SOME WAY.
>> ABSOLUTELY. AND THAT'S OUR GOAL WITH THIS
AND THE SHERIFF WANTS TO TAKE THAT QUESTION.
>> PLEASE DO. THANK YOU.
I APPRECIATE THAT BECAUSE IT IS IT IS NOT SOMETHING SIMPLE THAT
YOU CAN JUST FIX BY PUTTING SOMEBODY INTO A PLACE TO SLEEP.
SLEEP IT OFF IS WHAT THEY USED TO SAY.
RIGHT. OUR JAILS ARE DESIGNED FOR
WITHDRAWAL MANAGEMENT ALSO UNFORTUNATELY FOR THOSE THAT
STAY IN OUR CUSTODY, OUR INTENTION ISN'T TO KEEP PEOPLE
IN CUSTODY TO GO FROM SOBERING UP TO DETOXING TO WITHDRAW
MANAGEMENT. OUR INTENTION IS TO GET THEM TO
OTHER SERVICES AS THE UNDERSHERIFF MENTIONED PART OF
OUR PROCESS RIGHT NOW IS DETERMINING WHAT LIQUID
LINKAGES WOULD BEST BE SUITED FOR THE INDIVIDUAL BEYOND JUST
RESTING IN THIS PLACE FOR UP TO 24 HOURS.
IT IS NOT OUR INTENTION IF IF IT WAS CONVEYED EARLIER THAT
IT'S OUR INTENTION JUST TO RELEASE THE PERSON FROM THE
CENTER AFTER A CERTAIN AMOUNT OF TIME.
THAT'S NOT WHAT OUR INTENTION IS.
IT'S TO REALLY TRY TO CONNECT THEM TO CONTINUUM OF CARE FOR
THIS SITUATION. AND YOU'RE RIGHT FENTANYL IS
ABSOLUTELY A GAME CHANGER WHICH HAS LED TO WHY WE'RE LOOKING AT
DOING IT AT DOING SOMETHING AT CREATING A SPACE OUTSIDE OF OUR
NORMAL CONSTRUCTS OF JAILS OR HOSPITALS IN ORDER TO PROVIDE
AN EYE AN ADDITIONAL OPTION FOR THESE INDIVIDUALS.
YEAH. THANK YOU FOR THAT.
I APPRECIATE IT. I, I I'M YEAH, I'M JUST I'M
JUST TRYING TO UNDERSTAND WHAT HAPPENS TO SOMEONE AFTER THEIR
RELEASE AND I'M NOT I'M HEARING GENERAL REFERENCES TO
CONNECTING TO SERVICES. >> I DON'T KNOW AGAIN I, I
DON'T KNOW IF IS HERE TO ANSWER THE QUESTION ABOUT LIKE
SPECIFICALLY WHERE THEY WILL BE CONNECTED LIKE ONCE THE
INDIVIDUAL IS FREE TO GO THEY GET THERE THEY GET THEIR
RELEASE FORM THE EIGHT FOR NINE B THEN THEY CAN WALK OUT THEY
FEASIBLY CAN WALK OUT AT ANY TIME BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT BEING
HELD THEY'RE NOT BEING HELD AGAINST THEIR OWN WILL IN THIS
FACILITY. SO I'M JUST TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND WHAT WHAT IS THE WHAT IS THE PLAN FOR WHEN THEY
LEAVE? >> WELL, I LIKE TO THINK THAT
WE HAVE A NUMBER OF OPTIONS AVAILABLE TO US HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WITH THE GOOD WORK THAT THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH HAS DONE IN THIS SPACE. THERE'S STILL A PARTNER IN THIS
PROCESS WITH US. WE ALSO HAVE A NUMBER OF
ORGANIZATIONS AND FAMILIARITY WITH WHAT IS OUT THERE AS THE
SHERIFF'S OFFICE BECAUSE WE PROVIDE THESE LINKAGES FOR FOR
THE INCARCERATED AS THEY TRANSITION OUT AS WELL.
WE'RE HOPING TO LEVERAGE SOME OF THOSE PARTNERSHIPS AS A PART
OF WHAT WE'RE GOING TO BE ABLE TO OFFER TO INDIVIDUALS THAT
ARE GOING TO BE COMING OUT OF THIS SPACE HERE AT THE RESEARCH
CENTER. >> THANKS.
THOSE ARE MY QUESTIONS. >> CITY ATTORNEY I HAVE A
QUESTION ABOUT MY MOTION SO IF THIS IS SENT BACK TO COMMITTEE
BY NEXT WEEK, WILL WE RUN UP AGAINST A 45 DAY SHOT CLOCK?
>> DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD THE SUPERVISOR THAT'S CORRECT.
THE THIS WAS INTRODUCED UNDER THE MAYOR'S FENTANYL EMERGENCY
ORDINANCE AND THE BOARD MUST TAKE AN UP OR DOWN VOTE WITH ON
THE ITEM WITHIN 45 DAYS OR THE MAYOR HAS AUTHORITY TO
BASICALLY APPROVE THIS CONTRACT.
THE LAST DAY FOR THAT IS ON THE 20TH SO NEXT FRIDAY.
>> UNDERSTOOD. >> SEEING THAT I'M GOING TO
RESCIND MY MOTION I SO THE MOTION MADE BY SUPERVISOR
FIELDER IS RESCINDED WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN'S THE SECOND
WAS CONCURRENCE. IS THAT CORRECT?
>> OKAY GREAT. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN YOU HAVE NOT
SPOKEN TODAY. THANK YOU FOR PRESENT.
SHERIFF, I HAVE ANOTHER QUESTIONS.
>> WHAT WHAT IS THE MAXIMUM TIME THAT WE HAVE AN INDIVIDUAL
IN THE RESEARCH CENTER FOR A QUESTION UP TO 24 HOURS.
>> UP TO 24 HOURS? YES.
THANK YOU. >> ARE WE EXHAUSTED?
>> OH, WE'RE NOT SURE. JAN, THANK YOU.
I FIRST DO APPRECIATE YOU KNOW MR. ADAM TO ANSWER THAT
PROVIDING THE RESPONSE THROUGH YOUR EMAIL A RESPONSE THAT IS
FROM THE BOARD OF STATE AND COMMUNITY CORRECTIONS IS
INDICATING THAT AT THIS TIME THE CRITERIA OF A TYPE WEIGHT
TYPE ONE FACILITY OR TEMPORARY HOLDING FACILITY THAT THE
CENTER DOES NOT APPEARS TO MEET THAT CRITERIA.
IT DOES SAY THOUGH INDICATING THAT THEY WILL BE FORWARDING A
MORE FORMAL RESPONSE WHICH IS CORRELATES OR LIKE IT'S
CONSISTENT OF YOU KNOW THE INFORMATION I GOT ABOUT WE'RE
STILL WAITING FOR A FORMAL ASSESSMENT BECAUSE IT'S WAITING
FOR IT TO OPEN THIS CENTER AND TO VISIT AND THEN THEY CAN
EVALUATE THE OPERATIONS. >> I JUST HAVE A LOT OF
QUESTIONS ABOUT THE CENTER. I DO I DO ALSO THINK THAT I
HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT THE FUNDING.
IT IS MY GOAL THAT DURING THE BUDGET PROCESS THAT WE WILL
HAVE MORE OF THESE DIALOG AND THESE CONVERSATION IN EVENT
THAT WE CAN'T BE SURE. I WOULD LIKE TO AT LEAST PUT
SOME WHICH WE HAVE DONE IT BEFORE EVEN FOR DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT WHEN IT COMES TO AMBASSADOR PROGRAM WE
CAN'T BE SURE THEN WE WOULD YOU KNOW PUT CERTAIN FUNDINGS ON
RESERVE UNTIL WE CAN LEARN MORE THEN WE RELEASE THE FUNDING
ACCORDINGLY. IT'S MY GOAL TO DO THAT FOR
THIS CONTRACT BUT I AM STILL IN THAT SPACE.
I'M NOT READY TO SUPPORT IT TODAY I CAN SEE THAT THIS IS
LIKELY TO BE APPROVED BY THIS BODY TODAY BUT IT'S STILL MY
GOAL VERY MUCH THE SAME GOAL TO CONTINUE AND TO LEARN MORE
ABOUT THIS AND TO HAVE A DISCUSSION DURING BUDGET
PROCESS. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. CHAIR JAN, IF EVERYONE ELSE
SPOKEN I WILL SAY FOR ME THIS IS NOT A HARD QUESTION I BEAT
YOU ON THERE AS A CO-SPONSOR SUPERVISOR CHERYL BUT I THINK
THE CHALLENGES WE ARE SEEING ON OUR STREETS AROUND ADDICTION,
OPEN AIR DRUG USE AND SALES ARE AMONG THE MOST SIGNIFICANT
AND SERIOUS FACING OUR CITY AND FACING OUR ABILITY TO HAVE
FULL ECONOMIC RECOVERY AND ADDRESS THE CONCERNS THAT
ARE STILL EXPRESSED AROUND THE COUNTRY AND AROUND THE WORLD
ABOUT SAN FRANCISCO. THIS IS A TINY PILOTS TO TEST
WHETHER A PLACE TO TAKE PEOPLE IN VOLUNTARILY TO TO SOBER UP
MIGHT POTENTIALLY BE PART OF AN ARSENAL THAT WE COULD USE TO
IMPROVE CONDITIONS ON OUR STREETS.
I THINK THE REALITY IS NOT HAVING PLACES TO TAKE PEOPLE
RIGHT NOW IS A HUGE PROBLEM. IT PUTS OUR POLICE AND OUR
OUTREACH TEAMS AND EVEN OUR PUBLIC HEALTH PROVIDERS AT A
TREMENDOUS DISADVANTAGE. AND SO I THINK WE NEED TO MOVE
AS QUICKLY AS WE CAN ON THIS PILOT AND IF IT WORKS, DO A
WHOLE LOT MORE AND IF IT DOESN'T FIND SOMETHING ELSE.
BUT THANK YOU TO THE MAYOR AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR PUSHING
THIS. AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM AND ITEM 12 SUPERVISOR
WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
NO. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ITEM 15 ITEM
15 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO ORDER THE SUMMARY STREET
VACATION OF CITY PROPERTY ON UNIMPROVED STREET AREAS OF
MORAGA AND NORIEGA AVENUES TO FIND THE STREET VACATION AREA
IS NOT NECESSARY FOR THE CITY'S USE TO RESERVE EASEMENTS
RELATED TO SUPPORT FOR THE CITY OWNED RETAINING WALL FROM THE
STREET VACATION PROPERTIES AND TO INCLUDE OTHER CONDITIONS
TO THE STREET VACATION TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE AND THE
ZONING MAP TO REZONE THE CITY PROPERTY TO AFFIRM THE SIEGAL
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 15 SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHEN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR
I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 ITEM
16 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO EXPAND
THE BOUNDARIES OF THE CASTRO LESBIAN, GAY, BISEXUAL,
TRANSGENDER AND CULTURAL DISTRICT TO INCLUDE THE DEBARGE
TRIANGLE NEIGHBORHOOD TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> LET'S TAKE THE SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL IT M 17
ITEM 17 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT LASHAUN T WOODS TO OUR
TO THE OUR CITY OUR HOME OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE TERM ENDING
APRIL 22ND, 2027 AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED PLEASE CALL ITEM 18
ITEM 18 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT JOSEPH SAND GERARDI TO
THE SUNSHINE ORDINANCE TASK FORCE TERM ENDING APRIL 27TH,
2026 SUPERVISOR JEN MADAM QUICK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 18
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MODE MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE
MOTION IS APPROVED. ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK I THINK
WE HAVE COMMITTEE REPORTS. YES WE HAVE THREE ITEMS 31
AND 32 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY FEBRUARY 9TH, 2026
AND WERE RECOMMENDED AS COMMITTEE REPORTS FOR ITEM 31.
THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO AUTHORIZE
MOVIE THEATERS THAT ALSO OPERATE AS BONA FIDE BONA FEED
BONA FIDE EATING PLACES TO OFFER ENTERTAIN AND CULTURAL,
ARTISTIC, DRAMATIC MUSICAL OR LEISURE ACTIVITIES PERFORMED
ARTS OR EXHIBITIONS AND PERMIT ONSITE WINE, BEER AND OR LIQUOR
AND TO MAKE CONFORMING CHANGES IN THE PLANNING CODE
DEFINITIONS OF BAR AND BONA FIDE EATING PLACES USES TO
PERMIT CERTAIN MOVIE THEATERS IN THE UPPER FILLMORE
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICT TO SELL WINE AND OR
BEER WITHOUT BEING SUBJECT TO A NONRESIDENTIAL USE SIZE LIMIT
OTHERWISE APPLICABLE IN THE DISTRICT AND TO AFFIRM THE SEEK
WE DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 31 SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR OF MANAGEMENT MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN
I MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR
SUTTER SAUDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON EITHER ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT A WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 32 ITEM 32 WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED
BUT IT'S BEARING THE SAME TITLE.
THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO DECLARE THE INTENTION OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO ORDER THE VACATION OF THE DESIGNATION OF
PORTIONS OF CHRISTMAS TREE POINT ROAD AND THE EASTERN
ALIGNMENT OF TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD AS PUBLIC RIGHT OF
WAY FOR ROADWAY AND SIDEWALK PURPOSES AND TO ORDER THE
DESIGNATION OF EASTERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD AS PUBLIC RIGHT
OF WAY FOR RECREATION AND PARK PURPOSES TO FACILITATE THE
DEVELOPMENT OF THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE PROJECT AND TO SET A
HEARING DATE FOR THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO SIT AS A
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE FOR ALL PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE
PROPOSED VACATION OF SAID STREET AREAS.
>> OKAY AND MADAM CLERK, YOU WANT ME TO DO WHAT DO YOU WANT
ME TO DO ABOUT THIS TITLE? >> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
AT COMMITTEE THIS ITEM WAS AMENDED IN THE LEGAL TEXT OF
THE OF THE RESOLUTION THE TITLE ITSELF DID NOT GET AMENDED TO
INCLUDE MARCH 17TH FOR A 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
>> WE WOULD APPRECIATE THAT AMENDMENT.
>> SO YOU WOULD LIKE THAT AMENDMENT AND WE CAN TAKE THAT
WITHOUT OBJECTION. ALL RIGHT.
AND OH THERE'S CONSULTATION AND MR. DO YOU WANT A MOTION A
SECOND JUST TO NAME YOUR NAME AND ANOTHER MOVED BY MELGAR OR
SECOND AND BY WALTON THANK YOU MEMBERS THANK YOU, MR.
PRESIDENT. THANKS EVERYBODY.
AND SO ON 32 AS AMENDED ON 32 AS AMENDED I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THAT SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> THE RESOLUTION AS A AS AMENDED IS ADOPTED.
THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL ITEM 33. ITEM 30 THREE WAS CONSIDERED BY
THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY,
FEBRUARY NINTH AND WAS FORWARDED AS A COMMITTEE
REPORT. THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO PROHIBIT THE USE OF CITY
PROPERTY WITHOUT THE CITY'S AUTHORIZATION EXCEPT FOR USES
TRADITIONALLY AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC WITHOUT AUTHORIZATION TO
PROHIBIT ANY CITY OFFICIAL OR EMPLOYEE FROM AUTHORIZING THE
USE OF CITY PROPERTY IF THAT USE WOULD DISRUPT CITY
OPERATIONS OR DISCOURAGE ACCESS TO CITY SERVICES UNLESS THE USE
FURTHERS A CITY PURPOSE TO STATE THAT CIVIL IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT IS NOT A CITY PURPOSE AND TO AUTHORIZE THE
CITY ATTORNEY TO BRING A CAUSE OF ACTION AGAINST ANYONE THAT
USES CITY PROPERTY FOR AN UNLAWFUL OR UNAUTHORIZED
PURPOSE. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU
PRESIDENT. >> I'M PROUD TO BRING THIS ITEM
33 FORWARD. >> I WANT TO START BY THANKING
THE PARTNERS WHO MADE THIS WORK POSSIBLE COAUTHOR SUPERVISOR
CHEN THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC DEFENDER'S OFFICE S.F. RISING
CHINESE FOR AFFIRMATIVE ACTION THE SAN FRANCISCO LATINO PARITY
AND EQUITY COALITION, THE ARAB RESOURCE AND ORGANIZING CENTER
AND OUR LABOR AND COMMUNITY ADVOCATES THEIR EXPERTISE MADE
THIS LEGISLATION POSSIBLE AND KEPT IT GROUNDED IN THE
REALITY THAT FAMILIES ARE FACING TODAY.
>> AT ITS CORE THE ORDINANCE IS SIMPLE CITY PROPERTY SHOULD BE
USED FOR CITY PURPOSES AND OUR PUBLIC BUILDINGS MUST BE SAFE,
WELCOMING AND ACCESSIBLE TO THE PEOPLE THEY ARE MEANT TO SERVE
. >> WE KNOW WHAT HAPPENS WHEN
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT SHOWS UP AT OR NEAR PUBLIC
FACILITIES. >> PEOPLE DISAPPEAR FROM
SERVICES, APPOINTMENTS ARE CANCELED.
KIDS MISS SCHOOL FAMILIES STOP APPLYING FOR BENEFITS.
WITNESSES DON'T REPORT CRIMES WHEN FEAR DRIVES PEOPLE AWAY.
THE CITY CANNOT DO ITS JOB. IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT MAY BE
FEDERAL POLICY BUT THE FALLOUT IS LOCAL PLAYING OUT IN OUR
CLINICS, OUR CLASSROOMS AND OUR COMMUNITIES.
IN SAN FRANCISCO, THAT CHILLING EFFECT THREATENS PUBLIC HEALTH,
PUBLIC SAFETY AND ECONOMIC STABILITY.
>> WE HAVE SPENT YEARS REBUILDING TRUST IN CITY
SERVICES AND THIS LEGISLATION IS ABOUT PROTECTING THAT TRUST
. THIS MODEL HAS ALSO SPARKED
REGIONAL ALIGNMENT ACROSS THE BAY AREA WOULD SANTA CLARA
COUNTY, SAN JOSE, OAKLAND AND RICHMOND TAKING SIMILAR
STEPS THAT ALIGNMENT MATTERS BECAUSE FEAR DOESN'T STOP AT
OUR CITY'S BORDERS AND ACCESS TO SERVICES SHOULDN'T DEPEND ON
WHICH SIDE OF A COUNTY LINE SOMEONE LIVES ON.
>> ACCORDINGLY, THIS ORDINANCE SETS CLEAR GUARDRAILS NUMBER
ONE DESIGNATES THAT CITY PROPERTY MUST SERVE A CITY
PURPOSE. >> NUMBER TWO DESIGNATES THAT
ASSISTING FEDERAL FEDERAL CIVIL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT IS NOT
A CITY PURPOSE AND STAFF THAT ARE POTENTIALLY COLLABORATIVE
CAN FACE DISCIPLINARY ACTION. >> IT DESIGNATES THREE THAT USE
THAT DISRUPT CITY SERVICES OR DETERS RESIDENTS IS NOT
ALLOWED. AND FOUR AUTHORIZE THE CITY
ATTORNEY TO ACT WHEN OUR FACILITIES ARE BEING MISUSED.
>> THIS DOESN'T REGULATE THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT BUT IT DOES
GOVERN HOW WE MANAGE OUR OWN BUILDINGS WHICH IS OUR
RESPONSIBLE CITY AS A CITY UNDER THE 10TH AMENDMENT.
>> FINALLY, I'D LIKE TO THANK OUR COAUTHOR AGAIN SUPERVISOR
CHEN AND OUR CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR MELGAR SAUTER
FIELDER WALTON AND RANDLEMAN. AND A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO OUR
DRAFTING ATTORNEYS DRAFTING DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY JAYNA
CLARK, JESSICA GUTIERREZ GARCIA AND MY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM
LOGAN WHOSE HARD WORK AND EXPERTISE TO TURN THIS
POLICY INTO REALITY. COLLEAGUES, I ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL.
>> FIRST MEMBER TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR WANG
KAY. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION ON EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS AND THE
RESTORATION OF SAN FRANCISCO AS OUTDOOR PUBLIC WARNING SYSTEM.
SAN FRANCISCO FACES REAL RISK FROM EARTHQUAKES, TSUNAMIS,
EXTREME WEATHER AND POWER OUTAGES.
EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS MEANS HAVING SYSTEMS THAT WORK UNDER
THOSE CONDITIONS. RIGHT NOW WE DO NOT.
OUR OUTDOOR WARNING SIRENS AT APPROXIMATELY 119 ACROSS THE
CITY HAVE BEEN OFFLINE SINCE 2019.
FOR MORE THAN SIX YEARS SAN FRANCISCO HAS LACKED A
FUNCTIONING OUTDOOR WARNING SYSTEM TO SUPPLEMENT CELL PHONE
ALERTS DURING MAJOR EMERGENCIES .
WE HAVE SEEN THE CONSEQUENCES IN DECEMBER 2020 FOR A TSUNAMI
WARNING REQUIRED FIRST RESPONDERS TO DRIVE ALONG OCEAN
BEACH USING LOUDSPEAKERS TO WARN RESIDENTS.
IN DECEMBER 2025, A WIDESPREAD POWER OUTAGE LEFT MANY
RESIDENTS WITH ACCESS TO EMERGENCY ALERTS OR THE ABILITY
TO CONTACT 911. THESE EVENTS MAKE ONE THING
CLEAR. EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS DEPENDS
ON REDUNDANCY. CELL PHONE ALERTS ARE IMPORTANT
BUT THEY HAVE LIMITS. PHONES LOSE POWER, NETWORKS
FAIL AND ALERTS DO NOT RELIABLY REACH PEOPLE WHO ARE SLEEPING
OUTDOORS VISITING THE CITY ELDERLY UNHOUSED OR WITHOUT
SMARTPHONES. OUTDOOR WARNING SYSTEMS EXIST
TO FILL THOSE GAPS. THIS RESOLUTION CALLS ON THE
CITY TO TAKE A PRACTICAL AND PHASED APPROACH BY
IDENTIFYING FUNDING TO RESTORE SIRENS STARTING IN TSUNAMI
EVACUATION ZONES IN COASTAL AREAS AND BY PURSUING STATE
AND FEDERAL RESOURCES TO SUPPORT THAT WORK.
>> THIS IS NOT ABOUT CREATING SIMPLY SOMETHING NEW.
IT IS ABOUT RESTORING A PROVEN PUBLIC SAFETY TOOL AND CLOSING
A KNOWN GAP IN OUR EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS BEFORE THE NEXT
DISASTER. I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG.
SUPERVISOR CHEN. SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO INITIATE THE LANDMARK PROCESS FOR ENGINE
COMPANY NUMBER THREE LOCATED IN THE LAKEWAY NEIGHBORHOOD
IN DISTRICT 11. THIS FIREHOUSE WAS CONSTRUCTED
IN 1896 AND ITS AMOUNT TO OLDEST STANDING FIREHOUSES
IN SAN FRANCISCO. ENGINE COMPANY NUMBER 33 WAS
THE LAST HORSE DRAWN UNIT IN SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
DEPARTMENT. NOT CONVERTING TO USING
MOTORIZED APPARATUS UNTIL 1921. I WANT TO THANK THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT FOR THEIR WORK IN PREPARING THIS LANDMARK
AND I'M PLEASED TO GET YOUR SUPPORT FOR THE CULTURAL
AND HISTORICAL HERITAGE IN MY DISTRICT.
THANK YOU. >> THAT WAS NICE.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO ADD A COMMEMORATIVE STREET RENAMING
OF HELEN OF WILD CAUSEWAY TO JULIAN AVENUE, THE HOME OF THE
FRIENDSHIP HOUSE ASSOCIATION OF AMERICAN INDIANS.
HELEN WALL KAZOO FUND FOUNDED THE FRIENDSHIP HOUSE IN 1963
AND TRANSFORMED IT INTO NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED TREATMENT
FACILITY THAT IT IS TODAY. >> THE FRIENDSHIP HOUSE WAS ONE
OF THE FIRST PROGRAMS IN THE COUNTRY TO INTEGRATE
TRADITIONAL NATIVE HEALING PRACTICES WITH EVIDENCE BASED
TREATMENT. AS HELEN DEEPLY UNDERSTOOD THE
NEED FOR NATIVE PEOPLE STRUGGLING WITH SUBSTANCE USE
DISORDER TO HAVE A PLACE TO RECONNECT WITH THEIR CULTURE
AND JOIN A COMMUNITY OF OTHER NATIVES LOOKING FOR A PLACE TO
HEAL AND CALL HOME. >> HELEN WAS A PROUD GINNY
WOMAN WHO DEDICATED HER LIFE TO THE HEALING, EMPOWERMENT
AND VISIBILITY OF INDIGENOUS PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND ACROSS THE NATION. >> WE DON'T HAVE MANY
RESOLUTIONS BEFORE US TO HONOR NATIVE PEOPLES OR NATIVE WOMEN
FOR THAT MATTER IN THIS CHAMBER AND I AM PROUD TO SPONSOR THIS
RESOLUTION ON BEHALF OF HELEN WHILE ZOO HER FAMILY AND THE
FRIENDSHIP HOUSE AND WOULD WELCOME YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A HEARING TO
EXAMINE HOW OUR CITY PREVENTS AND RESPONDS TO YOUTH VIOLENCE
AND HOW OUR DEPARTMENTS COORDINATE WHEN YOUNG PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES ARE IMPACTED BY SERIOUS INCIDENTS.
>> BEFORE ANYTHING ELSE I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE YOUNG PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES IN OUR CITY WHO HAVE BEEN DIRECTLY AFFECTED BY
VIOLENCE IN THE WESTERN TRADITION.
JUST A FEW WEEKS AGO A SHOOTING INVOLVING SEVERAL JUVENILES
RESULTED IN THE LOSS OF A YOUNG WOMAN'S LIFE.
>> OUR HEARTS ARE WITH HER FAMILY, FRIENDS AND THE BROADER
COMMUNITY THAT IS STILL GRIEVING.
LAST FALL IN THE TENDERLOIN ANOTHER SHOOTING INVOLVING A
YOUNG RESIDENT DEEPLY IMPACTED THAT NEIGHBORHOOD AS WELL.
THESE ARE PAINFUL MOMENTS FOR OUR COMMUNITIES AND THEY STAY
WITH PEOPLE LONG AFTER THE HEADLINES FADE.
>> WHEN INCIDENTS LIKE THESE HAPPEN IT BECOMES CLEAR THAT IT
IS NOT JUST A PUBLIC SAFETY ISSUE, IT IS A PUBLIC HEALTH
ISSUE, A YOUTH DEVELOPMENT ISSUE AND A FAMILY SUPPORT
ISSUE. >> AND IT REQUIRES MORE THAN
ONE DEPARTMENT TO RESPOND EFFECTIVELY AND IN COORDINATION
. THIS HEARING IS ACCORDINGLY NOT
ABOUT JUST ANY ONE CASE. IT'S ABOUT MAKING SURE WE'RE
DOING EVERYTHING WE CAN AS A CITY TO PREVENT VIOLENCE BEFORE
IT HAPPENS AND TO SUPPORT YOUNG PEOPLE AND FAMILIES WHEN IT
DOES. I WANT US TO UNDERSTAND HOW
DEPARTMENTS COMMUNICATE AND COORDINATE IN REAL TIME HOW
PREVENTION AND INTERVENTION PROGRAMS ARE WORKING TOGETHER
WHERE GAPS OR DUPLICATION MAY EXIST AND WHETHER OUR FUNDING
AND STAFFING MATCHES THE NEEDS WE'RE SEEING IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. >> WE'VE ASKED THE OFFICE OF
VICTIMS VICTIM AND WITNESS RIGHTS, JUVENILE PROBATION, THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT INCLUDING THE STREET VIOLENCE RESPONSE TEAM,
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH INCLUDING THE STREET VIOLENCE
INTERVENTION PROGRAM, THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN, YOUTH
AND THEIR FAMILIES AND THE SCHOOL VIOLENCE INTERRUPTERS
AND THE SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT TO JOIN US
BECAUSE THESE AGENCIES ALL TOUCH THE SAME YOUNG PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES. FOR THIS WORK TO BE EFFECTIVE
THEY CAN'T OPERATE IN SILOS. THEY MUST FUNCTION AS ONE
COORDINATED SYSTEM OF SUPPORT. >> THROUGH THIS HEARING I HOPE
WE CAN BETTER UNDERSTAND HOW WE SUPPORT VICTIMS AND FAMILIES
AFTER VIOLENCE OCCURS, HOW WE IDENTIFY AND INTERVENE WITH
YOUTH BEFORE HARM HAPPENS, HOW OUR VIOLENCE INTERRUPTERS
AND OUTREACH TEAMS COLLABORATE ACROSS DEPARTMENTS AND WHAT
OUTCOMES WE'RE TRACKING AND WHAT ADDITIONAL RESOURCES
OR POLICY ADJUSTMENTS MAY BE NEEDED.
ULTIMATELY THE GOAL IS SIMPLE. FEWER YOUNG PEOPLE EXPOSED TO
VIOLENCE. MORE YOUNG PEOPLE SUPPORTED
WITH APPROPRIATE SERVICES. AND A CITY RESPONSE THAT IS
PROACTIVE, COORDINATED AND GROUNDED IN PREVENTION.
I LOOK FORWARD TO A CONSTRUCTIVE CONVERSATION
AND TO WORKING WITH OUR PARTNERS TO STRENGTHEN THIS
WORK. >> SECOND COLLEAGUES.
TODAY I WANT TO INTRODUCE AND IN MEMORIAM CELEBRATE THE
LIFE OF JOHNNY MAE BAKER, A LONGTIME SAN FRANCISCAN AND THE
SHINING EXAMPLE OF WHAT IT MEANS TO LIVE IN COMMUNITY.
>> JOHNNY WAS BORN IN FEBRUARY 6TH, 1948.
>> AND MOORINGS PORT LOSE WE LOSE DNA AND RELOCATED TO SAN
FRANCISCO AT THE AGE OF 13. >> LIKE SO MANY BLACK FAMILIES
WHO HELPED SHAPE THE CITY, SHE MADE SAN FRANCISCO HER HOME
AND BUILT A LIFE GROUNDED IN FAMILY AND SERVICE.
SHE ATTENDED BENJAMIN FRANKLIN JUNIOR HIGH PELTON JUNIOR HIGH
AND MISSION HIGH SCHOOL WHERE SHE FORMED FRIENDSHIPS THAT
WOULD LAST A LIFETIME. IN THE EARLY 90S, JOHNNY MOVED
HER FAMILY TO THE WESTERN EDITION WHERE SHE BECAME DEEPLY
WOVEN INTO THE SOCIAL AND SPIRITUAL LIFE OF THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> SHE JOINED CIVIC GROUPS,
SOCIAL GATHERINGS AND FAITH BASED ORGANIZATIONS
AND EVERYWHERE SHE WENT. >> HER WELCOMING SMILE
AND PLAYFUL SENSE OF HUMOR ENDEARED HER TO ALL.
>> JOHNNY UNDERSTOOD THAT COMMUNITY IS BUILT THROUGH
RELATIONSHIPS. >> UP UNTIL THE END OF HER LIFE
SHE MAINTAINED HER KINDNESS, GRACE AND COMPASSION, HUMOR
AND ABIDING LOVE FOR HER FAMILY AND FRIENDS.
AS THE OLDEST OF FIVE SIBLINGS SHE LED WITH EQUAL PARTS
CONVICTION AND COMPASSION FROM A YOUNG AGE.
>> JOHNNY FORGED DEEP AND SUPPORTIVE RELATIONSHIPS
THROUGH COMMUNITY AND FAITH BASED ORGANIZATIONS ACROSS
DISTRICT FIVE INCLUDING THE RAFIKI COALITION FOR HEALTH
AND WELLNESS, THE BOOKER T WASHINGTON COMMUNITY SERVICE
CENTER, THE AFRICAN AMERICAN ART AND CULTURE COMPLEX AND HER
CHURCH COMMUNITY. SHE WAS A CONSISTENT
AND DEPENDABLE PRESENCE AND SOMEONE YOU COULD ALWAYS
CALL FOR AN ENCOURAGING WORD. SHE LOVED GATHERING WITH
OTHERS. JOHNNY WAS AN ORIGINAL MEMBER
OF A NEW BEGINNING A BOOK CLUB FOUNDED IN 1999 WITH FRIENDS
JEAN KIP HOGG AND MELANIE MOORE.
WHAT BEGAN AS A WEEKLY BOOK DISCUSSION GREW INTO SHARED
MEALS, OUTINGS AND LASTING SISTERHOOD.
WITH FOOD ALWAYS AT THE CENTER, SHE WAS ALSO A BELOVED MEMBER
OF THE FRIDAY FAITH FELLOWSHIP, HOSTED EVERY FIRST FRIDAY BY
HER COUSIN JANIE WHITE WHERE HER SISTERS AND CHRIST GATHERED
FOR FOOD CONVERSATION AND BIBLICAL TEACHING.
JOHNNY WAS ESPECIALLY KNOWN FOR HER GIFT AT BIBLICAL TRIVIA.
>> IN RECENT YEARS THE BOOKER T WASHINGTON COMMUNITY SERVICE
CENTER BECAME A SECOND HOME FOR HER WHERE SHE FOUND CONNECTION
AND SUPPORT THROUGH SENIOR WELLNESS PROGRAMS AND COMMUNITY
GATHERINGS. >> PROFESSIONALLY, JOHNNY
SERVED THE PEOPLE OF CALIFORNIA AS A LEGAL SECRETARY AT THE
STATE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE.
WORKING WITH DEDICATION AND PRIDE UNTIL HER RETIREMENT
IN 2010, SHE BROUGHT THE SAME WARMTH AND INTEGRITY TO HER
WORK THAT SHE BROUGHT INTO HER COMMUNITY.
>> JOHNNY HAD A RARE GIFT FOR MAKING PEOPLE FEEL SEEN
AND APPRECIATED. SHE NEVER FORGOT A BIRTHDAY
ALWAYS SHOWED UP FOR CELEBRATIONS AND OFFERED HELP
THROUGH ACTS OF SERVICE. >> SHE WAS ESPECIALLY PROUD OF
HER CHILDREN ERICA BAKER BROOKS AND DWIGHT BAKER.
TO SO MANY JOHNNY WAS MORE THAN A FRIEND.
SHE WAS A SHELTER, A GUIDE, A STEADY SOURCE OF STRENGTH, A
FAVORITE AUNTIE AND SOMEONE WHOSE LOVE AND KINDNESS BROUGHT
OUT THE BEST IN EVERYONE. JOHNNY LOVED HER COMMUNITY
AND HER COMMUNITY LOVED HER. >> TODAY WE HONOR JOHNNY MAE
BAKER NOT ONLY FOR WHO SHE WAS BUT FOR WHAT SHE REPRESENTS.
A LEGACY OF COMPASSION AND DEEP ROOTED CARE IN DISTRICT FIVE.
MAY HER MEMORY CONTINUE TO BE A BLESSING AND MAY HER LEGACY
LIVE ON THROUGH THE COUNTLESS LIVES SHE HAS TOUCHED.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> WE HAVE A FEW ITEMS TODAY,
FOLKS. TWO HEARINGS A DRAFTING
REQUESTS A RESOLUTION. >> TWO RESOLUTIONS.
ALL RIGHT. FIRST, I AM REQUESTING A
HEARING ON THE REPORT AND RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE
PROPOSITION E COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK FORCE.
I'M ALSO SUBMITTING A DRAFTING REQUEST FOR THE CITY ATTORNEY
TO BEGIN WORKING ON A CHARTER AMENDMENT FOR CONSIDERATION BY
THIS BOARD TO IMPLEMENT ALL OR MUCH MORE LIKELY SOME OF THE
TASK FORCE'S PROPOSED CHARTER CHANGES.
ON FEBRUARY 1ST THE TASK FORCE RELEASED ITS FINAL REPORT.
THAT REPORT REFLECTS MONTHS OF WORK BY TASK FORCE MEMBERS
AND STAFF EXAMINING HOW SAN FRANCISCO'S BOARD
AND COMMISSIONS OPERATE AND HOW THEY COULD BE RESTRUCTURED TO
BEST SERVE THE PUBLIC. >> PROPOSITION E APPROVED BY
SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS IN NOVEMBER 2020 FOR
ESTABLISHMENT TASK FORCE AND CHARGED WITH REVIEWING
AND RECOMMENDING POTENTIAL CHANGES TO THE CITY'S MORE THAN
150 BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS. TASK FORCE MEMBERS WERE
APPOINTED BY THE MAYOR, THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR, THE CITY
ATTORNEY AND THE COMPTROLLER. THE TASK FORCE'S MANDATE WAS TO
IDENTIFY OPPORTUNITIES TO MODIFY, CONSOLIDATE OR
ELIMINATE PUBLIC BODIES TO IMPROVE THE ADMINISTRATION OF
CITY GOVERNMENT WHILE PRESERVING MEANINGFUL
OPPORTUNITIES FOR PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT.
OVER THE COURSE OF 2025 THE TASK FORCE WITH EXTENSIVE
SUPPORT FROM STAFF IN THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE
CONDUCTED A DETAILED REVIEW OF EACH PUBLIC BODY ONE BY ONE.
TO DATE THEY HAVE HELD 23 PUBLIC MEETINGS AND CONSIDERED
MORE THAN 1200 PIECES OF WRITTEN AND VERBAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. THEY HAVE MADE FOUR PRIMARY
RECOMMENDATIONS. FIRST, THEY RECOMMEND
STRENGTHENING PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT BY CONSOLIDATING BOARDS,
COMMISSIONS AND BODIES. THEIR PROPOSAL WOULD REDUCE THE
OVERALL NUMBER OF BODIES OF SUCH BODIES TO APPROXIMATE 88
WITH CLEARER MISSIONS AND MORE FOCUSED RESPONSIBILITIES.
SECOND, THEY RECOMMEND MOVING CERTAIN ADVISORY OR
NON-DECISION MAKING BODIES FROM THE CHARTER TO THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO ALLOW THE CITY GREATER FLEXIBILITY TO
MAKE ADJUSTMENTS OVER TIME WITHOUT REQUIRING COSTLY
AND TIME INTENSIVE CHARTER AMENDMENTS WHILE STILL
PRESERVING THE WORK AND PURPOSE OF THOSE BODIES.
THIRD, THEY RECOMMEND UPDATING COMMISSION RESPONSIBILITIES TO
CLARIFY LINES OF AUTHORITY IMPROVE ACCOUNTABILITY
AND ENSURE EACH COMMISSION IS EQUIPPED TO CARRY OUT ITS
INTENDED ROLE EFFECTIVELY. AND FOURTH, THEY RECOMMEND
ESTABLISHING MORE STANDARDIZED STRUCTURES AND MEMBERSHIP
GUIDELINES ACROSS COMMISSIONS TO AND AND OTHER BODIES TO
IMPROVE TRANSPARENCY AND CONSISTENCY IN HOW THEY
OPERATE. UNDER THE TERMS OF PROPOSITION
EITHER THIS BOARD US IS REQUIRED TO HOLD A HEARING ON
THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE TASK FORCE PRIOR TO APRIL 1ST HENCE
THIS HEARING REQUEST BY MARCH 1ST, 2026 THE TASK FORCE WILL
PROPOSE LEGISLATION TO IMPLEMENT ITS RECOMMENDATIONS
OR OR THOSE OF ITS RECOMMENDATIONS THAT INVOLVE
CHANGES TO THE ADMIN CODE. THOSE WILL BE CAPTURED IN AN
ORDINANCE THAT WILL BE PLACED DIRECTLY ON OUR AGENDA AND WILL
TAKE EFFECT WITHIN 90 DAYS UNLESS VETOED BY TWO THIRDS OF
THIS BOARD. HOWEVER, THE TASK FORCE DOES
NOT HAVE THE AUTHORITY TO MAKE CHANGES TO THE CHARTER OR TO
PLACE PROPOSED CHANGES BEFORE THE VOTERS.
TO THE EXTENT THAT THE TASK FORCE HAS RECOMMENDED CHARTER
CHANGES, THOSE CHANGES CAN ONLY BE ADVANCED EITHER BY ACTION OF
THIS BOARD OR THROUGH SIGNATURE GATHERING EFFORTS OUTSIDE CITY
HALL. ACCORDINGLY I AM ASKING I AM
SUBMITTING TO THE CITY ATTORNEY THIS CHARTER DRAFTING REQUEST
TO BEGIN A BOARD LED PROCESS TO REVIEW THE TASK FORCE'S
PROPOSED CHARTER CHANGES AND TO DEVELOP A POTENTIAL PROPOSAL
FOR VOTER CONSIDERATION IN NOVEMBER.
AT RISK OF REPEATING MYSELF AND BECAUSE I KNOW THIS IS OF
INTEREST AND CONCERN TO MANY THE BOARD IS NOT REQUIRED TO
PUT FORWARD A CHARTER AMENDMENT THAT MIRRORS THE
RECOMMENDATIONS CONTAINED IN THE TASK FORCE REPORT.
THE TASK FORCE HAS PROPOSED AND WILL DISCUSS AT ITS MEETING
TOMORROW A DRAFT CHARTER AMENDMENT TO IMPLEMENT ITS
RECOMMENDATIONS. WE CAN CONSIDER THAT DRAFT
CHARTER AMENDMENT AS WE LOOK AT ANY CHARTER AMENDMENT WE MIGHT
WANT TO PUT BEFORE THE BOARD BEFORE THE VOTERS HERE.
BUT I DO WANT TO THANK THE TASK FORCE FOR ALL OF THEIR WORK
AND ASSURE THEM THAT WE ARE GOING TO SERIOUSLY
AND THOUGHTFULLY CONSIDER WHAT THEY HAVE DONE.
MY OFFICE IS GOING TO WORK WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY TO TAKE AN
INITIAL PASS AT AT REVIEWING THE TASK FORCE'S REPORT
AND BEGINNING TO WORK WITH STAKEHOLDERS TO TRANSLATE THOSE
CONCEPTS INTO POTENTIAL LEGISLATIVE LANGUAGE.
AND I FULLY EXPECT THAT ANY SUCH CHARTER AMENDMENT WILL
EVOLVE WILL EVOLVE SIGNIFICANTLY THROUGH PUBLIC
INPUT, STAKEHOLDER ENGAGEMENT AND OF COURSE COLLABORATION
WITH YOU ALL. >> I WOULD ALSO NOTE THAT THERE
IS LIKELY TO BE SOME OVERLAP MAYBE SIGNIFICANT OVERLAP
BETWEEN THIS WORK AND SOME OF THE TOPICS CURRENTLY UNDER
CONSIDERATION BY THE CHARTER REFORM WORKING GROUP ASSEMBLED
BY THE MAYOR AND MYSELF ON WHICH SUPERVISORS MAHMUD
AND CHEN HAVE BEEN SERVING. THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE.
AS WE MOVE FORWARD IT WILL LIKELY MAKE SENSE FOR THE
CHARTER AMENDMENT I'M REQUESTING TODAY TO BE INFORMED
BY THE DELIBERATIONS OF THAT GROUP.
I WANT TO AGAIN EXPRESS SINCERE GRATITUDE TO THE MEMBERS OF THE
COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK FORCE AND ESPECIALLY OUR
REPRESENTATIVE ED HARRINGTON FOR THEIR EXTRAORDINARY
DEDICATION AND SERIOUSNESS OF PURPOSE.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK CITY ADMINISTRATOR CARMEN CHIU
AND HER TEAM ESPECIALLY RACHEL ALONZO FOR ALL OF THEIR WORK.
AND FINALLY I WANT TO THANK THE MANY COMMISSIONERS ADVOCATES
COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO
HAVE PARTICIPATED AND SHARED THEIR PERSPECTIVES SO FAR.
THAT INPUT IS GOING TO BE CRITICAL TO ENSURING THAT ANY
REFORMS WE CONSIDER HERE ARE THOUGHTFUL, BALANCED
AND REFLECTIVE OF THE VALUES OF SAN FRANCISCO.
AND I WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE MELANIE
MATHISEN, WHO'S BEEN DOING AMAZING WORK BOTH TRACKING THE
WORK OF THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE AND FACILITATING THE WORK
OF THE CHARTER WORKING GROUP. I LOOK FORWARD TO ENGAGING WITH
YOU ALL AND THE PUBLIC AS WE MOVE FORWARD.
AND THAT IS MY FIRST ITEM. >> SECONDLY, TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A REQUEST FOR A HEARING ON THE SAN FRANCISCO
ENVIRONMENT DEPARTMENT'S BUDGET.
EVERY DAY WE ARE CONFRONTED WITH NEW AND WORRYING EVIDENCE
OF THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT'S ABANDONMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION AS A POLICY PRIORITY.
SINCE LAST JANUARY THE ADMINISTRATION HAS ROLLED BACK
NEARLY 70 RULES THAT PROTECT OUR ECOSYSTEMS AND CLIMATE.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEEN A SUSTAINABILITY LEADER AND OUR
LEADERSHIP IN THIS AREA IS TODAY MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER
. DURING THE BOARD'S THIS BOARD'S
BUDGET DELIBERATIONS LAST JUNE I EXPRESSED CONCERN OVER THE
CUTS TO THE DEPARTMENT OF THE ENVIRONMENT THAT WERE THAT THE
MAYOR AND WE INCLUDED IN THAT BUDGET.
SPECIFICALLY I WAS WORRIED THAT BY THE SECOND YEAR OF THAT
BUDGET THAT IS THE 2026 2027 FISCAL YEAR THAT WILL BE THE
FIRST YEAR OF NEXT YEAR TWO OF THE TWO YEAR BUDGET WE CONSIDER
THIS JUNE THE $2.1 MILLION IN CUTS TO THAT DEPARTMENT
WOULD REQUIRE THE ELIMINATION OF 11 POSITIONS AND THE LAYOFF
OF AS MANY AS SEVEN PEOPLE. >> AS I UNDERSTAND IT, THOSE
LAYOFFS WILL ESSENTIALLY END SAN FRANCISCO'S ENVIRONMENTAL
POLICY WORK IN THE AREAS OF CLIMATE AND BUILDING
DECARBONIZATION AND HEALTHY ECOSYSTEMS INCLUDING
ELIMINATING COORDINATION AND TRACKING OF THE CITY'S
CLIMATE ACTION PLAN ACROSS DEPARTMENTS AND PARTNERS,
ELIMINATING EMISSIONS TRACKING AND CLIMATE MODELING.
ELIMINATING SUPPORT FOR THE CLIMATE EQUITY HUB AND LOW
INCOME ELECTRIFICATION SUPPORT. AND ELIMINATING THE
DEPARTMENT'S BIODIVERSITY WORK AROUND GREEN SPACE EXPANSION
AND HABITAT RESTORATION AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.
THE CUTS WILL ALSO LEAD TO THE ELIMINATION OF THE DEPARTMENT'S
TRANSPORTATION PROGRAM WORK INCLUDING WORK ON IMPLEMENTING
ONE OF THE COMMERCIAL GARAGE EV CHARGING ORDINANCE.
OTHER WORK TO ADVANCE THE CITY'S EV CHARGING POLICIES
INCLUDING CURBSIDE CHARGING AND WORK ON URBAN FREIGHT
DECARBONIZATION. AT THIS HEARING I'M GOING TO BE
ASKING THE DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENT AND THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE TO REPORT ON THE IMPACT THESE CUTS WILL HAVE ON SAN
FRANCISCO'S ACHIEVEMENT OF THE SUSTAINABILITY GOALS WE HAVE
SET AND HOW THEY PLAN FOR SAN FRANCISCO TO REMAIN A CLIMATE
LEADER IN THE ABSENCE OF THE PEOPLE WHO DO THAT WORK.
I WANT TO THANK THE CLIMATE EMERGENCY COALITION FOR THEIR
PARTNERSHIP ON SO MANY CLIMATE PRIORITIES AND THEIR ADVOCACY
AROUND PRESERVING SAN FRANCISCO'S INVESTMENTS
IN SUSTAINABILITY. AND I WANT TO THANK SOPHIE
MARIE IN MY OFFICE FOR HER WORK ON THIS HEARING REQUEST.
>> NEXT, I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING SUPPORT FOR
ASSEMBLY BILL 1265 AUTHORED BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER MATT HANEY
WHICH SEEKS TO EXTEND AND STRENGTHEN CALIFORNIA'S
HISTORIC TAX CREDIT PROGRAM. AS WE ALL KNOW, CALIFORNIA
SUFFERS FROM AN ACUTE HOUSING SHORTAGE.
THE STATE HAS SET AN AMBITIOUS GOAL OF BUILDING 2.5 MILLION
NEW HOMES BY 2030. AND WE ARE NOT ON TRACK TO MEET
IT. OUR STATE IS ALSO HOME TO MORE
THAN 300,000 HISTORIC BUILDINGS, MANY OF THEM VACANT
OR UNDERUSED. AND ALTHOUGH PROPERTY OWNERS
MAY WANT TO TRANSFORM THESE RESOURCES INTO VIBRANT
AND ATTRACTIVE AND USABLE SPACES, THE COST OF RESTORING
AND CONVERTING THEM CAN BE PROHIBITIVE REQUIRING
SPECIALIZED LABOR, CUSTOM MATERIALS AND STRUCTURAL
UPGRADES THAT MOST PROPERTY OWNERS CANNOT AFFORD WITHOUT
HELP. THE EXISTING HISTORIC TAX
CREDIT PROGRAM WAS A STEP IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION BUT ITS
FIRST COME FIRST SERVE STRUCTURE HAS FAILED TO DELIVER
EQUITABLE RESULTS. OF THE $40 MILLION ALLOCATED
FOR LARGE PROJECTS LAST YEAR, ONLY TWO PROJECTS INCLUDING SAN
FRANCISCO'S HEARST BUILDING RECEIVED FUNDING SIMPLY BECAUSE
THEY HIT SUBMIT SECONDS BEFORE OTHER THAN FOR DOZENS OF OTHER
WORTHY APPLICANTS. MEANWHILE, PROJECTS LIKE THE
CASTRO THEATER, THE HUNTINGTON HOTEL AND THE TAYLOR HOTEL WERE
LEFT WITHOUT SUPPORT. AB 1265 COULD HELP FIX THIS
BROKEN SYSTEM. IT EXTENDS THE STORE TAX CREDIT
FOR FIVE YEARS AND INTRODUCES CRITICAL REFORMS A $5 MILLION
PER PROJECT CAP SO MORE BUILDINGS COULD BE ASSISTED.
A MERIT BASED SCORING SYSTEM REPLACING THE RACE TO THE
BUTTON APPROACH AND REMOVAL OF THE ARBITRARY $50 MILLION CAP
ALLOWING THE PROGRAM TO MEET REAL DEMAND.
THIS POLICY CHANGE LEVERAGES EXISTING ASSETS TO CREATE
HOUSING, DRIVE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AND PRESERVE THE
CHARACTER OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. OVER THE LAST FIVE YEARS
PROJECTS USING THE HISTORIC TAX CREDIT HAVE CREATED 10,000
SKILLED JOBS AND GENERATED $55 MILLION IN STATE AND LOCAL
TAXES. MODIFYING THE PROGRAM WILL ONLY
PROVIDE ADDITIONAL BENEFITS FOR OUR WORKFORCE AND FUNDING FOR
STATE AND LOCAL PROJECTS. SUPPORTING HB 1265 WILL ALLOW
US TO PRESERVE OUR ARCHITECTURAL HERITAGE WHILE
SIMULTANEOUSLY ADVANCING OUR HOUSING GOALS.
AND I'M GOING TO HOPE THAT YOU WILL SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION
AND THE BILL ITSELF AS WE MOVE FORWARD.
>> AND LASTLY, COLLEAGUES, ACTUALLY YOU KNOW WHAT?
THAT'S NOT SOMETHING I'M DOING TODAY.
SO THE REST I WILL SUBMIT. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MILLER SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER, THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION
OF NEW BUSINESS. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. FOR THOSE OF YOU IN THE CHAMBER
WHO WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT, THIS IS
YOUR OPPORTUNITY IF YOU WOULD LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE
OF THE CHAMBER YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED ITEMS
36 THROUGH 41 ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE OR
OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT
MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
>> IF YOU WOULD COME UP TO THE PODIUM, TAKE A LOOK AT THE
PODIUM ONCE YOU DO COME UP THERE IS A TIMER.
THE SOFT BELL WILL LET YOU KNOW YOU HAVE 30S TO WRAP UP YOUR
COMMENTS AND THEN THE FINAL BELL WILL RING.
WE HATE TO INTERRUPT YOU BUT PLEASE KEEP YOUR COMMENTS TO
TWO MINUTES. NOW WE JUST WANT TO WELCOME OUR
FIRST SPEAKER. >> WELCOME.
OH, PLEASE EXCUSE MY VOICE OUT ON A PICKET LINE.
I AM A PUBLIC EDUCATOR WITH SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL
DISTRICT. I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE FEW
BOARD MEMBERS WHO HAVE SHOWN PUBLIC SOLIDARITY AS HAVE
EDUCATORS. I UNDERSTAND THAT TEACHERS
STRIKE STRIKE IS NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT I'M HERE BECAUSE
PUBLIC EDUCATION SHOULD ALWAYS BE ON THE BOARDS AGENDA.
I ALSO UNDERSTAND TEACHERS BEING ON STRIKE IS NOT JUST A
CONTRACT ISSUE. >> IT'S A CITY ISSUE WHERE
SCHOOLS ARE UNDERFUNDED, UNDERSTAFFED AND UNSAFE.
THE WHOLE CITY IS RESPONSIBLE. I'M COMING TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS BECAUSE SAN FRANCISCO CAN'T KEEP CLAIMING
IT VALUES KIDS WITHOUT BACKING IT UP.
NOW OUR CHILDREN HAVE THE ABILITY TO ATTEND PRIVATE
SCHOOLS. IT DEEPLY SADDENS ME THAT THIS
IS ONE OF THE WEALTHIEST CITIES IN THE WORLD AND PUBLIC
EDUCATOR IS ARE HAVING TO FIGHT FOR THE BARE MINIMUM FAIR WAGES
ADEQUATE STAFFING AND RESOURCES FOR OUR BABIES IN HEALTH CARE.
HEALTH CARE IS NOT A LUXURY IT'S A HUMAN RIGHT.
EVERY CONTRACT CREATES A BOND OF TRUST.
AND WHEN THOSE BONDS ARE REPEATEDLY BROKEN,
ACCOUNTABILITY BECOMES NECESSARY.
WHEN EDUCATORS ARE SUPPORTED, THEY EMPOWER, THEY INSPIRE,
THEY STABILIZE ENTIRE COMMUNITIES.
I TRULY BELIEVE IF WE INVESTED IN EDUCATION THE WAY WE INVEST
IN POLICING AND INFRASTRUCTURE SHARES WE WOULD NOT NEED AS
MUCH POLICING WHEN PEOPLE HAVE WHAT THEY NEED THERE IS NO
EXCUSE OR NO INCENTIVES FOR CRIMES THE NECESSITIES
EDUCATION AND OUR FIGHTING FOR ARE NOT NEGOTIABLE.
THEY SHOULD BE GUARANTEED HUMAN RIGHTS.
AS PUBLIC OFFICIALS SWORN TO SERVE THE PUBLIC INTEREST, I'M
ASKING THE BOARD TO PUBLICLY COMMIT FUNDS TO STABILIZE
EDUCATORS WAGES AND HEALTH CARE JUST AS YOU DO REPAIRS FOR
PEERS LIKE THAT WAS ON ITEM LAST WEEK'S AGENDA.
>> OUR CHILDREN CAME AWAY OUR EDUCATORS ONE WAY.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
I'LL JUST ASK NO APPLAUSE. WE APPRECIATE YOUR SUPPORT BUT
THERE'S A BOARD RULE THAT DOES NOT AUTHORIZE ANY AUDIBLE
SOUNDS OF SUPPORT OR ANYTHING AGAINST BUT YOU'RE WELCOME TO
SIGNAL AS SUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COOPERATION
. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SAN FRANCISCO IS ONE OF THE MOST
BEAUTIFUL CITIES IN THE WORLD IF NOT THE MOST BEAUTIFUL CITY
IN THE WORLD. AND EVERY DAY THOUSANDS OF
TOURISTS OF ALL RACES AND RELIGIONS FROM ALL AROUND
THE WORLD COME TO OUR CITY TO SEE YOUR MANY WORLD WONDERS.
>> JUST LAST WEEK WAS THE SUPER BOWL AND WE SAW EVEN MORE
PEOPLE AND MUCH SIMILAR TO THAT THE ASIAN PACIFIC ECONOMIC
COOPERATION CONFERENCE. OUR CITY WAS CLEANED UP AND THE
DOWNTOWN AREA WAS SPARKLING CLEAN.
>> THE LESS FORTUNATE ADDICTS AND CRIMINALS WERE HURT HOARDED
INTO THE SURROUNDING NEIGHBORHOODS.
AND I YOU KNOW, I IMPLORE YOU TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT THE
HUMANITARIAN CRISIS. IT'S NICE WE HAVE PROTESTS FOR
EVERYTHING ELSE UNDERNEATH THE SUN.
I DO AGREE OUR EDUCATION SYSTEM DOES NEED A TOP TO BOTTOM
REFORM. I'D LIKE TO SEE PEOPLE PROTEST
ROOTING FOR THE 5000 PEOPLE WHO HAVE DIED FROM PHENOL ON THE
STREETS OF SAN FRANCISCO BETWEEN THE YEARS 2019
AND 2036. THIS IS AN ABSOLUTE FEDERAL
GENOCIDE, FEAR AND OTHER FORM OF CHEMICAL WARFARE ON THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE. IT COMES FROM CHINA ACROSS THE
SOUTHERN BORDER THROUGH THE PORT OF OAKLAND INTO OUR
COMMUNITY. FINALES SHOWING UP ON
PLAYGROUNDS AND IN SCHOOLS YOU KNOW, I GOT TO SAY I DON'T
NECESSARILY APPROVE OF ANY LAW ENFORCEMENT POINTING THE
FIREARMS AT ELDERLY WOMEN AND CHILDREN.
>> BUT WITH THAT SAID, I DO BELIEVE YOU KNOW, FEAR NOT
DEALERS SHOULD BE DEPORTED FROM OUR COMMUNITY IF THEY'RE HERE
IN OUR CITY EXPLOITING OUR SANCTUARY CITY, TAKING
ADVANTAGE OF OUR COMMUNITY, THEY SHOULD BE DEPORTED.
WALKING AROUND DOWNTOWN TODAY I SAW COUNTLESS PEOPLE LEFT
EXPOSED TO THE ELEMENTS DYING ON THE SIDEWALK.
>> AND I'D LIKE TO SEE SOME OF OUR RESOURCES GO TO OUR SAN
FRANCISCO BROTHERS AND SISTERS ON THE STREETS.
SEEMS LIKE YOU GUYS PRIORITIZE ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS BEFORE YOU
DO CITIZENS AND IT'S HEARTBREAKING.
>> OH, THANK YOU. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
>> GOOD EVENING, PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS RICHARD PETERSON.
I'M NOT HERE TO TALK ABOUT PERSONAL TAXES TODAY.
I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT THE ORDINANCE THAT SAN FRANCISCO
HAS FOR ANTI STYROFOAM WHICH SEEMS TO BE WORKING QUITE WELL
IN THE FOOD INDUSTRY AND WE ARE MOVING TO THE BAGS AND THE LIKE
. BUT ONE OF THE ONE OF THE MAJOR
STYROFOAM CONTRIBUTORS IS EXPANDED STYROFOAM THAT IS
IN HOT TUB COVERS AND THOSE COVERS ARE SIMPLY AFTER A YEAR
ABSORB WATER AND ARE DISCARDED AND ONE COVER PROBABLY EQUALS
THOUSANDS OF CUPS. AND I HAVE I, I REPRESENTED THE
OWNER OF AIRFRAME SPA COVER WHO WAS A CLIENT OF MINE YEARS AGO
AND HE HAS DEVELOPED A SPA COVER THAT DOES NOT USE
STYROFOAM OR EXPANDED STYROFOAM.
AND IT IS CALLED THE AIR FRAME COVER.
IT USES CANVAS AND ALUMINUM FRAMING AND IS HOLLOW JUST LIKE
THE MANY OF THE MODERN SURFBOARDS ARE BECOMING HOLLOW.
THEY'RE NOT USING STYROFOAM IN THE CORES ANYMORE.
SO I HAVE SOME LITERATURE THAT I CAN HAVE THE CLERK HAND OUT.
I HAVE 12 COPIES SO IT'S ONE FOR THE CLERK AND THE REST FOR
THE WOULD COME FOR THE BOARD MEMBERS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ALL RIGHT. LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> AS MUCH AS GOOD EVENING.
MY NAME IS SUSANNA ROJAS. I AM THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF
GALA EVENT THE EQUATOR LATINO CULTURAL DISTRICT AND I AM HERE
TONIGHT TO THANK SUPERVISOR FIELDER AND SUPERVISOR
SUPERVISOR MALE GUIDE FOR SUPPORTING AND INTRODUCING THE
RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT OUR BUILDING TO REMAIN A CULTURAL
HUB. >> AS YOU HEARD THE GENTLEMAN
WERE BEFORE US PEOPLE WHO ARE BROWN AND WHO ARE OF A CULTURE
ARE NOW LABELED ILLEGAL AND CRIMINALS JUST BY FOR EXIST
IN RECOGNIZING AND SUSTAINING SPACES WHERE CULTURE CAN BE
CULTIVATED, WHERE WE CAN EXPRESS OUR CULTURE AND ELEVATE
OUR HISTORY AND THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS TO THIS CITY
AND THE WORLD ARE EVEN MORE IMPORTANT.
SO THEY WERE HATED SO MUCH PREVALENT.
SO WE THANK YOU FOR THAT AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SERVES WITH THE ARTS COMMISSION
AND WITH THE YOUR CD TO MAKE SURE THAT NOT ONLY WE KEEP THIS
BUILDING RELIABLE, RELIABLE AND A HUB FOR ART BUT ALSO THAT
WE CAN BRING BACK M.C. CLAY TO THE WONDERFUL ORGANIZATION THAT
IT ONCE WAS. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUSANA ROJAS FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER OUR GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS EMILY PIMENTEL AND I'M A LONG TIME RESIDENT OF
SAN FRANCISCO AND I'M HERE TODAY TO ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT
FOR THE RESOLUTION TO PROTECT THE CULTURAL INFRASTRUCTURE OF
THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER I AND IN MY TIME IN SAN FRANCISCO
I'VE BEEN TO THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER MANY TIMES
ALONG WITH MY DAUGHTER, WITH FRIENDS AND OTHERS AND THIS HAS
BEEN AN IMPORTANT PART OF OUR CITY AND I THINK AT THIS TIME
IT'S ESPECIALLY IMPORTANT TO PROVIDE SUPPORT TO THESE KINDS
OF INSTITUTIONS AND IN THIS CASE IT'S REALLY ABOUT
PROTECTING THE BUILDING THE INFRASTRUCTURE, THE THE
BUILDING AT 2868 MISSION STREET IS NOT JUST A BUILDING.
IT'S BEEN A LIVING CULTURAL INSTITUTION FOR VISUAL ARTS
AND MURALS AND PRINTMAKING. I KNOW OF ARTISTS OF ALGAE
BLOOM COLLECTIVE. ROBLES YOU KNOW JUST TO NAME A
FEW THAT I'VE KNOWN PERSONALLY OVER THE YEARS THAT HAVE USED
AND BEEN AT THE CENTER AND SUPPORTED IT FOR MANY
YEARS. >> ONE OF THE THINGS THAT I
THINK IS ALSO INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT IS AT A TIME WHEN
THESE INSTITUTIONS ARE STRUGGLING, IT'S IMPORTANT TO
ALSO PROTECT THE ARCHIVES AND CULTURAL ASSETS THAT BELONG
TO THE COMMUNITY. THE HISTORICAL ARCHIVES ARE
HOUSED AT 2868 MISSION AND THESE ARE NOT JUST RECORDS
. THESE ARE PART OF THE COMMUNITY
MEMORY FOR LATINO CULTURAL CONTRIBUTION AND INHERITANCE.
>> I ALSO SAY THAT THESE BUILDINGS COULD ALSO SERVE AS
CLIMATE RESILIENCE CENTERS. SO I THINK THAT'S SOMETHING TO
CONSIDER AS WELL FOR THESE. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU, EMILY BOOM BLUMENTHAL FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI, MY NAME IS NELLIE RAY.
YES, I HAVE LIVED IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 40 YEARS AFTER
LIVING IN NEW YORK AND I LOVE SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE OF ALL
THE CULTURAL COMMUNITIES THAT THEY HAVE FROM ALL OVER THE
WORLD. THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER HAS
BEEN A VERY IMPORTANT PART OF MY LIFE MY CHILDREN'S LIFE, MY
DAUGHTER WHEN SHE GRADUATED FROM HIGH SCHOOL SHE
PARTICIPATED IN THE SHOW SOLOMON HARRIS WHICH THE
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER WAS A PIONEER ON THAT THE DAY OF THE
DEAD WHETHER IT WOULD BE SAN FRANCISCO WITHOUT ALL THOSE
ARTISTS THE FRIDA KAHLO THAT WE BROUGHT TO A PART OF SAN
FRANCISCO IN THIS I URGE YOU TO PLEASE SUPPORT AND CONTINUE
WITH THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER, THE CULTURE.
IT'S VERY, VERY IMPORTANT ESPECIALLY IN THESE TIMES WHEN
THEY ARE DISCRIMINATING THE CULTURE GIVE US STRENGTH, THE
ARTS GIVE US STRENGTH. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH AND I
HOPE YOU WILL ADOPT THIS RESOLUTION.
>> THANK YOU, MOLLY REYES FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER WILL NOT JUST SUPERVISOR IS MY
NAME IS CLAYTON JOHN LEANDER. I AM A NONPROFIT MANAGEMENT
CONSULTANT AND I'M ALSO A MEMBER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
PUERTO RICAN CLUB WHICH HAS BEEN IN EXISTENCE IN THIS CITY
SINCE 1912 114 YEARS NOW I'M PROBABLY THE OLDEST ONE OF THE
OLDEST LATINO ORGANIZATIONS IN THE CITY.
WE ARE HERE TO SUPPORT THE RESOLUTION PROPOSED BY
SUPERVISOR FIELDER TO PRESERVE THE BUILDING OVER A MISSION
STREET KNOWN AS THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER IS A VITAL
ANCHOR INSTITUTION IN THIS CITY AS MANY OF YOU SEEN OVER THE
SUPER BOWL WEEKEND, THERE WAS A LOT OF EXCITEMENT AND COMMERCE
GENERATED FOR THE CITY. BUT AT THE HEART OF THE GAMES
WAS A CELEBRATION OF LATINO CULTURE AND AS AS A
REPRESENTATIVE ALSO THE LATINO COMMUNITY WE WE SEE THAT ALL OF
THE COLORS OF EVERYBODY IN THE COMMUNITY IS INCLUDED.
WE WOULD BE REMISS NOT TO TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION THERE HAS
BEEN SOME CONTROVERSY IN THE PRESS AND RUMORS ABOUT THE
ORGANIZATION THAT WAS OCCUPYING THE CENTER KNOWN AS MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER LATINO ARTS HAVING WORKED WITH OTHER
NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS ACROSS THE STATE AND THE COUNTRY.
INDEED, NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS GO THROUGH CYCLES WHERE THEY
NEED ASSISTANCE. I WAS VERY IMPRESSED BY THE
PUBLIC MEETINGS TO TRY TO REPAIR AND BRING TOGETHER SO
HOWEVER THIS PROCESS MOVES FORWARD, THE PUERTO RICAN CLUB
STANDS READY TO PARTICIPATE. LASTLY, I WOULD JUST PUT IN ONE
MORE NOTE THAT WHATEVER HAPPENS WITH THIS RESOLUTION IT ALSO
MUST BE HARMONIZED WITH THE FORTHCOMING RECOMMENDATIONS OF
THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE SINCE THE BUILDING OF THE
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER IS UNDER THE JURISDICTION OF THE
ARTS COMMISSION AND THAT HAS TO BE BALANCED OUT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU CLAYTON LEANDER FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS NANCY BILLION
AND THIS I'M HERE TO SPEAK ABOUT THE CLOSURE OF MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER. BUT FIRST I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT TODAY IS DAY TWO OF THE UCSF STRIKE.
SO THAT MEANS 50,000 S.F. STUDENTS WERE OUT OF SCHOOL
TODAY. I DID SEE SOME OF YOU GUYS
JOINING THE PICKET LINE RAISE YOUR HAND IF YOU JOINED A
PICKET LINE. I SAW YOU.
I SAW YOU. I SAW YOU.
I SAW YOU. THANK YOU.
SO SHOUT OUT TO YOU GUYS THOSE WHO DID NOT MAKE IT TO A PICKET
LINE I WOULD SAY YOU ARE PROBABLY FAILING THE 6500
EDUCATORS WHO ARE OUT OF SCHOOL RIGHT NOW.
>> IT WAS VERY CRAZY FOR ME TO SIT HERE TODAY AS ORGANIZATIONS
AND PARENTS SCRAMBLED TO PROVIDE CHILD AND LUNCHES ALL
OVER THE CITY AND I WATCHED YOU GUYS ALLOCATE $14 MILLION TO
THE SHERIFF'S TO BABYSIT 26 DRUNK AND OR HIGH PEOPLE.
THEY WILL HAVE SEVEN ADULTS PRESENT IN THOSE ROOMS WHERE
TEACHERS ARE FIGHTING FOR SMALLER CLASS SIZES AND HAVE
NOWHERE NEAR THAT TYPE OF RESOURCES.
THAT 14 MILLION IS LIKE HALF OF THE AMOUNT NEEDED TO PAY FOR
THE HEALTH CARE COVERAGE FOR THE FAMILIES OF ALL OF THE
EDUCATORS. >> SO LITERALLY YOU GUYS JUST
GAVE THE SHERIFFS HALF OF THE MONEY THAT THE TEACHERS NEED TO
PAY FOR THEIR HEALTH CARE IN A PLACE WHERE IT COSTS $1,000 PER
BEDROOM, $1,000 PER FAMILY TO COVER HEALTH CARE IS CRAZY
AND UNREASONABLE AND YOU GUYS ARE HOOKED UP.
>> THIS LUXURY HOTEL LAST WEEK WITH LIKE THAT AMOUNT OF MONEY
OR MORE SO I FEEL LIKE FIRST OF ALL IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE
TEACHERS THE CITY NEEDS TO STEP UP AND SUPPORT PUBLIC EDUCATION
AND THEN AT THE SAME TIME I WANT TO SAY THAT WE WERE IN A
GARDEN TODAY IN THE RAIN TAKING CARE OF KIDS BECAUSE MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER IS CLOSED. MISSION CULTURAL CENTER SHOULD
BE THE FIRST PLACE THAT WE OPEN AS A STRIKE SCHOOL BECAUSE WE
CAN PRINT POSTERS, WE HAVE DANCE PLACES, WE HAVE STAGES WE
CAN PRACTICE SPENDING TIME IN SMALL GROUPS WITH YOUNG
PEOPLE BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT MISSION CULTURAL CENTER IS
BUILT FOR RIGHT NOW THAT THAT PLACE IS CLOSED.
WE ARE HOSTING STRIKE SCHOOLS OUTSIDE IN PUBLIC GARDENS
AND IN FARMS AND ALL THAT. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
THE SPEAKERS TIME HAS CONCLUDED.
THANK YOU. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER WELCOME. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES EVERYONE. >> GREAT.
THANK YOU. HELLO EVERYONE.
MY NAME IS DANIELLE OROPEZA AND I'M HERE AS A STAFF MEMBER
OF KEVIN DE CUATRO THE LATINO CULTURAL DISTRICT.
I'M HERE AS A DANCER. I'M HERE AS SOMEONE THAT'S
PERFORMED IN CARNAVAL. I HAVE TRAINED AT MISSION
CONTROL CENTER WITH PEOPLE BEHIND ME AND PEOPLE BEHIND
HERE AS WELL. I'M NOT GOING TO SAY ANY NAMES
BUT THEY'RE FABULOUS. I'VE LOVED BEING IN COMMUNITY
WITH PEOPLE AND ONE THING THAT I DO WANT TO SAY IS THAT LATINO
ARTS IS NOT JUST FOR CONSUMPTION ON THE BIG SCREEN
DURING A HALFTIME SHOW AT THE SUPER BOWL.
IT IS NOT FOR CONSUMPTION WHEN YOU WANT TO GO OUT IN VISIT A
LOCAL BUSINESS AND PUT ON SOME CUTE EARRINGS IT IS IT IS
WITHIN OUR PEOPLE. IT IS WITHIN OUR GENERATIONS
AND MISSION CONTROL CENTER HAS REALLY FUELED AND PAVED THE WAY
FOR SO MANY GENERATIONS TO GROW UP AND BE PRIDEFUL OF THEIR
CULTURE AND BE ABLE TO CULTIVATE RESILIENCE
AND RESISTANCE IN A SOCIETY THAT IS SO HEAVILY ROOTED
IN THE SILENCING OF SO MANY OF THESE COMMUNITIES THAT HAVE
BEEN MARGINALIZED HISTORICALLY AND CURRENTLY IN A NEW EXTREME
WAY THAT WE HAVE NOT SEEN COVERED IN THE MEDIA AT LEAST.
SO I JUST WANTED TO LET YOU ALL KNOW THAT I'M HERE NOT ONLY AS
A COMMUNITY MEMBER BUT SOMEONE THAT IS REALLY BENEFITED FROM
THE MISSION CONTROL CENTER PERSONALLY WHETHER IT'S WITHIN
DANCE CLASSES, IN GALLERIES THAT I'VE BEEN A PART OF
IN GALLERIES THAT I'VE ASSISTED IN CURATING AND AND IN THE
YOUTH THAT I HELP FOSTER RELATIONSHIPS WITH FROM MY
DANCE SISTERS AND ALL OF MY MENTORS AND THE LOSS OF THIS
SPACE WOULD BE REALLY DETRIMENTAL TO MANY YOUTH
WHETHER YOU'RE IN THE MISSION, WHETHER YOU'RE IN SAN FRANCISCO
OR WHEN YOU'RE IN THE GREATER BAY AREA WE HAVE PEOPLE THAT
TRAVEL TO THE MISSION CULTURE CENTER FROM SAN JOSE FROM
SAUSALITO, FROM SAN RAFAEL AND IT IS NOT JUST FOR SAN
FRANCISCO, IT'S FOR THE GREATER BAY AREA AND FOR THE
GENERATIONS TO COME. SO I REALLY HOPE THAT YOU ALL
PRIORITIZE NOT ONLY THE PEOPLE'S VOICES THAT ARE
SPEAKING IN THIS ROOM BUT THE GENERATIONS TO COME AND THE
GENERATIONS THAT HAVE ALREADY PASSED THAT HAVE BEEN IMPACTED
BY THIS LONG LINGERING LEGACY THAT NEEDS TO CONTINUE.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU, DANIELA OROPEZA FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME FRANCISCO.
WHEN HAS NO CHANCE. I'LL START BY SECONDING
EVERYTHING THAT NANCY BILLY JUST SAID WHEN A NOT JUST DEAR
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF THE BOARD.
>> MY NAME IS FRANCISCO HERRERA AND TODAY I'M REPRESENTING
NUEVO SOL DE LABOR AND DOMESTIC WORKERS CENTER AND COMMUNE
AND THE CULTURAL FOUNDATION IN THE MISSION.
TO ASK THAT YOU JOIN US IN PROTECTING OUR CULTURAL
INFRASTRUCTURE AT 2868 MISSION STREET.
>> FOR OVER HALF A CENTURY THIS SPACE HAS ENRICHED OUR LIVES,
REPRESENTED OUR STORY HERITAGE ,CULTURAL TRADITIONS
AND ARTISTIC EXCELLENT THAT REPRESENT ALL THE COUNTRIES
THAT MAKE UP THIS CONTINENT KNOWN AS AMERICA TURTLE ISLAND.
AND SPECIFICALLY THIS PART OF A COLONY A STEWARD AT TERRITORY
GELMAN. MY CHILDREN HAVE STUDIED
AND PRESENTED THEIR WORK AT THIS PROPERTY.
OUR DAY LABORERS AND DOMESTIC WORKERS MEMBERSHIP ORGANIZED
IN THAT SPACE SINCE 1989 THROUGH THE ARTS PLANNING
MEETINGS, COMMUNITY CELEBRATIONS AND COLLABORATIONS
IN THE COMMUNITY. >> FROM THE FIRST BAP TISM OF
OUR DEAR BROTHER ARIEL VARGAS CONDUCTED AT THIS LIFE GIVING
SPACE IN 1971 THROUGH LAST YEAR'S EFFORTS BY NEIGHBORS ALL
MEETINGS AND CULTURALLY EVENTS AS WELL AS COMMUNITY CULTURAL
FOUNDATION TRAINING SESSIONS WHERE PEOPLE LEARN TO TRANSLATE
THEIR EXPERIENCE INTO POETRY SONG, DANCE, FILM THE CULTURAL
IMPORTANCE OF THIS BUILDING MUST BE PROTECTED WELL SEISMIC
WHILE SEISMIC RETROFIT IS NEEDED.
THIS RESOLUTION ASSURES THAT THE RETROFITTED BUILDING REMAIN
DEDICATED TO LATINO ARTS AND CULTURE WHEN ESPECIALLY
IN THIS TIME WHEN WE HAVE TO ORGANIZE, HEAL AND RESPOND TO
THE SCAPEGOATING AND ICE TERRORISM OUR COMMUNITY'S
PRESENTLY ENDURING RESILIENCE IS OUR GOAL AND RESILIENCE
REQUIRES SPACE ACCESS AND CONTINUITY.
>> PLEASE SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION.
GRACIAS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> THANK YOU. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS
AND STAFF. MY NAME IS ROBERTO ADL VARGAS
AND I'M A CULTURAL WORKER IN SAN FRANCISCO, SAN FRANCISCO
NATIVE AND I'M ON THE BOARD OF INSTITUTO FAMILIA DE LA RAZA.
AND INSTITUTO STANDS IN SUPPORT OF THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER
AS A VITAL HUB FOR CULTURE HERE FOR FAMILIES TO COME TOGETHER
AND CHILDREN TO LEARN. IT IS, AS FOLKS HAVE SAID, A
VITAL RESOURCE FOR PEOPLE WANTING TO PRESERVE OUR
CULTURE. IT'S ALSO A VITAL RESOURCE FOR
THE SURROUNDING BUSINESSES. AND WHAT FOLKS HAVEN'T
MENTIONED YET IS THE HEALTH BENEFIT.
>> YES. I WORK IN PUBLIC HEALTH AND WE
KNOW THAT THERE ARE CERTAINLY PUBLIC HEALTH BENEFITS WHEN
COMMUNITY HAS A PLACE TO COME TOGETHER TO EXERCISE, TO DANCE
,TO BE TOGETHER IN SOCIAL SUPPORT.
AND SO I WANT TO ADD THAT 50 YEARS AGO THE COMMUNITY CAME
TOGETHER TO FOUND THIS ORGANIZATION AND JUST A COUPLE
OF WEEKS AGO COMMUNITY CAME TOGETHER AGAIN TO STAND
IN SUPPORT OF THIS ORGANIZATION.
YES, IT IS CHALLENGED AND WE KNOW THAT ARTS ORGANIZATIONS
ACROSS THE CITY ARE CHALLENGED. CULTURAL CENTERS ACROSS THE
CITY ARE CHALLENGED. AND SO I'D LIKE TO ENCOURAGE
OUR CITY LEADERS TO STAND WITH THE ARTS COMMISSION AND TAKE A
LOOK AT THE THE INFRASTRUCTURE THAT SUPPORTS CULTURAL CENTERS
,THE POLICIES THAT SUPPORT CULTURAL CENTERS THAT EXCLUDE
CULTURAL CENTERS FROM BEING ABLE TO APPLY FOR OTHER
RESOURCES, OTHER CITY RESOURCES OUTSIDE OF WHAT IS DESIGNATED
FOR CULTURAL CENTERS. >> WE KNOW THAT THERE ARE OTHER
WAYS THAT PEOPLE ARE TAKING CARE OF FOR EXAMPLE CHILD CARE,
AFTERSCHOOL PROGRAMING AND HEALTH BENEFITS AND SO THE
CENTERS SHOULD BE ELIGIBLE FOR A PLAN FOR THOSE KINDS OF
RESOURCES AS WELL. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME.
OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ADOLFO VELASQUEZ BORN AND RAISED HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO IN THE MISSION DISTRICT.
>> I HAVE VISITED CULTURAL CENTER THROUGHOUT MY 66 YEARS
BEING HERE TAKING MANY CLASSES. I KNOW MANY PEOPLE THAT HAVE
TAKEN CLASSES. THE VARIETY OF CLASSES THAT ARE
BEING OFFERED IS SUCH AN IMPORTANT INSTITUTION IN THE
MISSION THAT WE NEED TO DO EVERYTHING THAT POSSIBLE TO
KEEP IT GOING. ALL RIGHT.
>> I'M ALSO A RECIPIENT OF SOME EDUCATION IN SAN FRANCISCO
STATE WHERE I STAND ON THE SHOULDERS OF MANY OF THE
FOUNDING MEMBERS OF THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER.
PART OF MY RESPONSIBILITY IS TO CARRY ON THEIR LEGACY.
>> SO IN I'M ALSO IN THE DOCTORAL PROGRAM AT STATE WHERE
MY FOCUS IS ON NATIVE AMERICAN ARTISTIC COLLEGE STUDENTS.
WHAT I PLAN TO DO AFTERWARDS I'LL BE FINISHED WITH MY DEGREE
NEXT YEAR IS TO OPEN UP A PROGRAM WITH WITH INDIGENOUS
STUDENTS IN MINE AUTISTIC SPECIFICALLY THAT WOULD FIT
NICELY AT THE CULTURAL CENTER. KNOWING HOWEVER IT'S GOING TO
GO THROUGH THE RETROFIT. BUT I URGE YOU TO PASS THIS
RESOLUTION AND YOU KNOW IT ALSO PART OF MY DISSERTATION LOOKS
AT THE SENSIBLE LONGING FOR NATIVE AMERICAN STUDENTS BUT IT
ALSO TRANSFERS TO OUR LATINO POPULATION.
RIGHT? HAVING AN INSTITUTE KEEPING AN
INSTITUTION AS IMPORTANT AS A MAJOR CULTURAL CENTER FEEDS OUR
SENSE OF BELONGING HERE IN THE CITY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. HELLO, MY NAME IS JASON WYMAN.
I AM AN ARTIST AND CULTURAL ORGANIZER WHO WORKS CREATES
LIVES AND LIVES IN THE MISSION DISTRICT.
>> IT'S BEEN MY HOME FOR 22 YEARS.
I'VE BEEN IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR OVER 28.
I'M HERE TODAY TO SPEAK ON THE IMPORTANCE OF PRESERVING
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS.
YES. AND I AM ALSO HERE AS A
NEIGHBOR WHO TRULY UNDERSTANDS THE DEEP IMPORTANCE OF NOT JUST
AND UCLA BUT ALL OF THE CULTURAL CENTERS THAT MAKE UP A
ROBUST ECOSYSTEM OF PROGRAMS REGROUND MURALS, PERFORMANCES,
GALLERIES, SHOWCASES, FESTIVALS AND MORE CULTURAL CENTERS THAT
HAVE ENRICHED ME AS A NEIGHBOR ,HAVE TAUGHT ME AS AN ARTIST,
HAVE NURTURED ME AS A PERFORMER AND HAVE SHOWN ME WHAT A CITY'S
COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY BASED, CULTURALLY SPECIFIC PRODUCTION
MAKES POSSIBLE. >> LOVE ART POWER OR THAT WHICH
FUELS MOVEMENTS. >> THAT IS WHY IT IS CRUCIAL
THAT SAN FRANCISCO TAKE STEPS TO SECURE THE FUTURE OF OUR
CULTURAL CENTERS. I PERSONALLY WATCH THE CITY
SPECIFICALLY TARGET CULTURAL CENTERS OVER THE LAST FOUR
YEARS. ONE WAY THE FOUR CENTERS WITH
PHYSICAL LOCATIONS HAVE BEEN TARGETED IS THROUGH THEIR
BUILDINGS. WHAT IS HAPPENING TO UCLA IS
STRUCTURAL AND THE CITY CONTROLS AND LITERALLY OWNS THE
STRUCTURE. >> FOR NOW I URGE YOU TO
SUPPORT THE RESOLUTION TO PROTECT ON CECILIA REGARDLESS
OF ANY SINGLE NONPROFIT. AND I ALSO URGE THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO EXPAND ITS VIEW AND LOOK AT HOW SAN FRANCISCO
IS CURRENTLY HAMSTRINGING ITS CULTURAL CENTERS THROUGH ITS
BUDGETING, ADMINISTRATIVE OVERSIGHT AND RETROFITTING
PROCESSES. >> I'M HAPPY TO SHARE AND CHAT
MORE TO ENSURE THAT OUR CULTURAL CENTERS DO NOT MERELY
SURVIVE BUT THRIVE AND CONTINUE FUELING PEOPLE CENTERED
CULTURALLY SPECIFIC MOVEMENTS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND BEYOND. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD EVENING. MY NAME IS FRIDA KAHLO.
MY HUSBAND DIEGO AND I WERE MARRIED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
CITY HALL IN 1940. I WAS HOSPITALIZED IN ST LUKE'S
HOSPITAL AND MY PRESENCE HAVE CONTINUED TO INSPIRE
AND INFLUENCE ARTISTS OF THE PAST AND THE PRESENT.
I'M HERE TODAY TO FIGHT FOR EQUITY AND MAKE A SIGNIFICANT
CONTRIBUTION TO THE VITAL IS VITAL TO THE CITY'S IDENTITY
TOURISM AND LOCAL ECONOMY. WE HAD TO SERVE 8000 DIVERSE
PEOPLE A MONTH AROUND AND AROUND 100,000 PEOPLE A
YEAR. WE HAVE BEEN NEGLECTED
AND UNDERFUNDED FOR THE LAST 48 YEARS.
AND WHILE WE ARE THANKFUL WE'RE FINALLY UNDERGOING A RETROFIT.
I AM DISGUSTED THAT WITH ALL THE EMPTY BUILDINGS AVAILABLE
THAT THE ARTS COMMISSION AND THE CITY BOARD SUPERVISORS
HAS NOT GIVEN US A PLACE TO CONTINUE OUR PROGRAMING DURING
THE RETROFIT. I WANT A WRITTEN LEASE THAT
EXPLICITLY STATES THAT AN ASSURED AND CLAY WILL RETURN TO
THE BUILDING AND THAT WE WILL NOT BE DISPLACED OR EVICTED.
I SAID EVICTION BECAUSE IT IS A TRAUMATIC LANGUAGE THAT IS USED
IN OUR LEASE. I URGE YOU ALL TO KEEP US ALIVE
AND CONTINUE TO SERVE OUR OUR COMMUNITY.
I HAVE GIVEN TOURS AT THE CENTER LED ART WORKSHOPS FOR
THOUSANDS OF SAN FRANCISCO'S UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT
AND HELP OUR TIME AROUND OUR 10,000 PRINT COLLECTIONS WHICH
TELLS THE HISTORY OF SAN FRANCISCO SEEN THROUGH THE EYES
OF THE PRINCE. AND DURING MY TENURE HERE AT
MTC, L.A. IS ONE OF THE PEOPLE WHO WAS AFFECTED BY THE
LAYOFFS. AND FOR A CITY WITH AROUND
342,000 RESIDENTS WITH A NET WORTH OF $1 MILLION PRACTICALLY
ONE THAT IS 1 IN 4 SAN FRANCISCANS RANKING SECOND
RICHEST IN THE WORLD INCLUDING HUNDREDS OF BILLIONAIRES.
IT IS A COCOON MAINLY CATASTROPHIC AND ABSOLUTE
FAILURE WITH LEADERSHIP FIGHTING OVER CHUMP CHANGE.
PLEASE PROVIDE MCI L.A. WITH MORE FUNDING AND HELP US SAVE
OUR CULTURE. >> LAKOTA RA KURA GRACIAS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS AND COMMUNITY HERE.
MY NAME IS LAURA YANO. I'M A SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE.
I RETIRED CAREER AS A U.S. TEACHER STANDING HERE IN MY USF
T-SHIRT IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE STRIKING EDUCATORS OUTSIDE ALSO
STANDING IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE KAISER HEALTH CARE WORKERS
CURRENTLY ON STRIKE. >> I WANT TO TALK JUST TO MAKE
SOME POINTS ABOUT MISSION CULTURAL CENTER.
FIRST OF ALL, MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS SAVES
LIVES. IT SAVES LIVES BY GIVING
COMMUNITY A PLACE TO GATHER, BY SAVING COMMUNITY MEMORY
AND ACHIEVEMENTS. THAT IS THE MOST IMPORTANT
THING THAT I CAN SAY HERE TODAY I HAVE WITNESSED MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER SAVING LIVES BECAUSE I TAUGHT FOR TEN YEARS
AT. >> SORRY I'M KIND OF NERVOUS.
I TAUGHT FOR TEN YEARS AT A HORACE MANN WHICH IS JUST ONE
BLOCK AWAY AND SO MANY OF MY STUDENTS WENT TO MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER AND ATTENDED PROGRAMS.
THEY DANCED, THEY MADE ART, THEY COMMUNED, THEY LEARNED
THEIR CULTURE. THEY LEARNED OTHER CULTURES.
IT WAS A CRITICAL CRITICAL RESOURCE.
AND IT'S HEARTBREAKING THAT IT'S CLOSED.
MISSION CULTURAL CENTER IS A CULTURAL HUB.
>> IT'S A DYNAMIC CENTER FOR CREATING A DISSEMINATING
AND STORING CULTURAL AND COMMUNITY CONTRIBUTIONS
VALUE WISDOM WORTH HISTORY AND EXPERIENCES.
>> THE ARCHIVES ARE PRICELESS AND BEAR WITNESS TO
CONTRIBUTIONS OF GENERATIONS OF LATINO COMMUNITY.
THE MISSION COMMUNITY IN PARTICULAR AND IN GENERAL
GENERATIONS OF ACTIVISM AND CULTURAL ACHIEVEMENTS
AND WISDOM THEY MUST BE PROTECTED AND PRESERVED AT ALL
COSTS. >> THE BUILDING MUST BE
RESERVED FOR MISSION CULTURAL CENTER AND THE RETROFIT MUST
PRESERVE NOT DESTROY THE CULTURE.
PLEASE SUPPORT THE RESOLUTIONS TO ENSURE THE COMMUNITY
STABILITY IN THESE UNPREDICTABLE AND UNSTABLE
TIMES. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER HELLO.
GOOD AFTERNOON. I'M SYLVIA SUGARMAN.
I'M THE PROGRAM DIRECTOR AT THE COMMUNITY MUSIC CENTER.
WE'VE BEEN IN THE MISSION DISTRICT FOR OVER 100 YEARS
TEACHING MUSIC EDUCATION AND WE HOPE THAT YOU'LL DO EVERYTHING
IN YOUR POWER TO SUPPORT MISSION CULTURAL CENTER AT THIS
TURNING POINT IN THE IN THE CENTER'S HISTORY SO THAT IT CAN
CONTINUE TO BE A CHERISHED SPACE FOR THE NEXT GENERATION
OF COMMUNITY MEMBERS, NEIGHBORS, ARTISTS AND CULTURAL
ORGANIZERS. >> YOU'VE HEARD MANY POWERFUL
STORIES AND TESTIMONIES TO THE IMPORTANCE OF THE MICHIGAN
CULTURAL CENTER. I CAN SHARE JUST ONE WAY IN OUR
COMMUNITY THAT IT'S MADE A HUGE DIFFERENCE IN THE LIVES OF
YOUNG PEOPLE. >> FOR OVER TEN YEARS ONE OF
OUR PROGRAMS THE MISSION DISTRICT YOUNG MUSICIANS
PROGRAM WHICH IS A TUITION FREE PROGRAM FOR YOUNGSTERS TO LEARN
AND PERFORM LATIN MUSIC WE DIDN'T HAVE THE SPACES UMC SO
WE PARTNERED WITH MCLA AND WERE ABLE TO HAVE WEEKLY PRACTICES
AT THE CENTER AND THIS WAS IMPORTANT NOT JUST BECAUSE IT
WAS SPACE BUT BECAUSE THE YOUTH WERE ABLE TO BE IN AN
ENVIRONMENT THAT WAS IMMERSIVE, THAT THEY WERE IN A SPACE WHERE
THEY COULD SEE THEIR OWN HISTORY ON THE WALLS THROUGH
THE VISUAL ART WHERE THEY COULD PERFORM AND PARTICIPATE
IN VARIOUS IMPORTANT CULTURAL CELEBRATIONS WHETHER IT WAS
CINCO DE MAYO OR DIA DE LOS MUERTOS AND OUR STUDENTS TOLD
US HOW IMPORTANT THAT WAS FOR THEM.
>> SO THEY WERE NOT JUST LEARNING MUSIC, LEARNING MUSIC
MAYBE THAT THEY HEARD AT HOME OR IN THEIR FAMILY CELEBRATIONS
BUT THEY STARTED TO UNDERSTAND THAT THEY WERE PART OF A
CULTURAL LEGACY, THAT THEY WERE PART OF PASSING ON CULTURAL
TRADITIONS AS THEY SAW AMONGST THE WALLS OF MICHIGAN CULTURAL
CENTER. >> YOU'VE HEARD IT FROM THE THE
SISTER FROM KIOWA AND THE QUATRO FROM LAURA FROM FRIDA
ABOUT HOW IMPORTANT IT IS FOR SO MANY OTHER STUDENTS
AND TEACHERS AND ARTISTS IN OUR COMMUNITY.
WE HOPE THAT YOU WILL DO EVERYTHING IN YOUR POWER TO
SUPPORT MICHIGAN CULTURAL CENTER GOING FORWARD.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING.
>> I'M RENEE ANANDA RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO, GREW UP
IN THE MISSION DISTRICT. I BENEFITED GREATLY FROM THE
WIDE RANGE OF PROGRAMS, CLASSES AND CULTURALLY EVENTS THAT WERE
OFFERED BY THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER.
>> IT'S A UNIFYING ARTISTRY THAT COMBINED NOT ONLY JUST THE
LATINO ASPECTS OF OF OUR COUNTRY BUT ALSO THE
AFRO-CARIBBEAN. IT SHOWS THE CONNECTION AND IT
WAS REALLY A SAFE PLACE FOR ME. HAVING THAT HERITAGE BEING ABLE
TO GO TO THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER AND SEEING THE
CONNECTION IT WAS THERE IN MY YOUTH.
I HAVE A DAUGHTER. SHE'S GONE THERE AS WELL.
AND AS A PLANNER HAVING THAT PROFESSION AS A BACKGROUND I
THINK IT'S EXCELLENT THAT THE RESOLUTION LOOKS INTO THE
FUTURE NOT JUST FOR NOW AND MAKING SURE THAT THIS
CONTINUES INTO MULTI GENERATIONS.
SO A I COMMEND THE SUPERVISORS FOR MAKING THIS RESOLUTION.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING FOR SUPERVISOR
AND STAFF. MY NAME IS MARCUS LOPEZ.
I'M A RESIDENCE OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR 56 YEARS AND I'M
HERE TO SUPPORT THE MISSION OF CULTURE CENTER.
I GREW UP IN THE MISSION, WENT TO SCHOOL IN THE MISSION AND I
DEVELOPED MY MUSIC CAREER AND THE MISSION AND IT HAS SEEN
ME GROW AND DEVELOP INTO A YOU KNOW WHAT I AM TODAY AND UP
PLAY MANY PLACES ON THE MISSION ESPECIALLY MUSIC CULTURE CENTER
WHICH IS IMPORTANT TO FOR THE COMMUNITY AND OUR YOUTH SEE
MANY MANY IMPORTANT ARTS AND VISUALS THEATER MUSIC AND I
THINK BY ELIMINATING THIS PLACE IT WILL BE A HORRENDOUS BLOW.
SO TO OUR COMMUNITY AND MAINLY TO OUR YOUTH BECAUSE BY GETTING
THE YOUTH INVOLVED IN MUSIC YOU KNOW YOU KEEP HIM OUT OF THE
STREETS, YOU KNOW, GIVE HIM A GOOD INDICATION MAYBE YOU CAN
MAKE MUSIC AS A CAREER AND YOU'RE ALDERLEY EDGE LIKE I
HAVE DONE IT AND BE PRODUCTIVE FOR THE FOR THE ART CULTURE
IN OUR COMMUNITY. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER BOARD OF
SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR OFFICE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THE TITLE OF TWO SPEECHES TO HIGHEST LAW OF THE LAND.
IT WAS A MONUMENTAL OCCASION THAT I REMEMBER AND PASS IT TO
THE KIDS ALL AROUND THE WORLD. ON FEBRUARY 2019 I SAT IN FRONT
OF THE BUDDHIST MONK SOCIETY OF S.A. LA ANGEL.
SIX MONTHS EARLIER TO LEND A VOICE ALONG WITH THE JAZZ
AND REALLY MISSED CHINATOWN UNIVERSE OF 2018 TO SUPPORT
MAGGIE TO RECOGNIZE HER AS A VOICE OF THE BUDDHIST MONK.
MAGGIE WONG WAS SENT TO HONG KONG TO COMPETE FOR THE TITLE
OF MISS CHINESE INTERNATIONAL HOST BY TVB.
>> AS I SAT EXHAUSTED FROM MAKING ROUNDS OF SPONSORSHIP,
THE BUDDHIST MONK TEACHER SPOKE.
HE SPOKE OF A VARIETY OF ISSUES INCLUDING SELF-CONFIDENCE,
FAMILY, SELF-CONTROL. HOWEVER, I WAS FLABBERGASTED BY
THE FOUR SIMPLE WORDS THAT HE UTTERED AT THE VERY END OF THE
SPEECH. HE SAID THE USUAL ENGLISH
SOMEBODY GONG IN TRANSLATION I JUST SPEAK WITH YOUR HEART.
VALENTINE'S IS COMING IN FOUR DAYS.
BEFORE THAT I MUST SAY MY FIANCEE LEGION UN PEN NAME IU
POP STAR OF SOUTH KOREA. I WILL SLEEP DIRECTLY AS
AMBASSADOR OF GUCCI WHO HAPPENS I RETAIL STORE NEXT TO MADE
IN LADY SQUARE. I SAY I LOVE YOU.
I WILL THANK YOU FOR A TWEETY BIRD THAT YOU MAY ASK BUGS
BUNNY OF AND SYLVESTER SIX FLAGS.
I THANK YOU. I CANNOT WAIT TO MEET YOU ON
YOUR BIRTHDAY ALONG WITH BEATS AND IN CONCERT STAFFORD.
LOVE THAT MY WORK THE PARTY'S OVER FOR ME TO BE HEART WORK
AHEAD OF ME AS WELL AS SUPPORT A SUPERVISOR.
I'M HERE TO ASK CHIEF SOFTWARE ARCHITECT OF A.I. I'M HERE TO
DELIVER WORLDWIDE CONSTITUTION FOR JOEL BIDEN AND KAMALA
HARRIS. I'M HERE TO PROVIDE A BRIGHT
SUPPORT FOR MUSIC FOR MUSIC INDUSTRY.
IF YOU LOOK AT IT SUPER BOWL TO STREET LIGHTS THAT'S ON THE
SUPER BOWL FOR THE PREVIOUS TWO YEARS.
MY SOFTWARE TO BE ABLE TO SUPPORT THAT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S GET THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ISABELLE PERAZA.
I WAS A VOLUNTEER AT MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FROM 1991
THROUGH 2022. AND ERICA PASSIVE YOU CAN THINK
OF INCLUDING THREE STINTS ON THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS DURING
MY LAST INT WAS ENDED IN 2022. >> DURING THAT TIME I GAVE AS
MUCH TIME AS I COULD AS A SINGLE MOM, A WORKING MOTHER, A
35 YEAR EMPLOYEE OF THE CALIFORNIA ATTORNEY GENERAL'S
OFFICE. THANK YOU JOHNNY BAKER
AND THANK YOU, BY THE WAY, FOR SAYING ALL THESE WONDERFUL
THINGS ABOUT HER. >> BUT IT WAS IMPORTANT TO ME
AND TO MANY OTHER PARENTS AND FAMILIES IN THE MISSION TO
HAVE A PLACE WHERE WE COULD TAKE OUR CHILDREN THAT WAS A
SAFE SPACE WHERE THEY FELT APPRECIATE NEEDED FOR THEIR
BACKGROUNDS, THEIR SKILLS. IT WAS A PLACE TO DEVELOP AS
PAINTERS, AS MUSICIANS. >> THEY PROVIDED TEACHERS
AND INSPIRATION WHERE OUR SCHOOLS WERE LACKING.
>> MY SON WAS ABLE TO RECEIVE WONDERFUL MUSIC TRAINING THAT
WAS NOT AVAILABLE AT THE SCHOOL OF THE ARTS WHERE HE LATER WAS
A STUDENT. THEY FINALLY INITIATED A WORLD
MUSIC PROGRAM BUT MOST OF WHAT THEY WERE TEACHING DID NOT
REFLECT HIS BACKGROUND. >> THAT HAS CHANGED.
THERE WERE MANY OTHER SCHOOL PROGRAMS THAT ALSO WERE
SUPPLEMENTED BY WAS WHAT WAS OFFERED AT THE MISSION CULTURAL
CENTER. >> IT WASN'T JUST AT THE
CENTER. THE CLASSES WERE OFFERED WHERE
SKILLS WERE DEVELOPED. WE ALSO DID OUTREACH TO NORTH
BEACH PARTICIPATING IN ART IN THE ALLEY WITH OUR YOUTH
PROGRAMING WITH OUR DANCERS OR MUSICIANS.
MANY OTHER PLACES WHERE WE PROVIDED ARTS AND CRAFTS
AND EXPOSE THE KIDS IN THE MISSION TO MANY OTHER
NEIGHBORHOODS. AND ALL THE BEAUTIFUL THINGS
THAT WE ADDED TO THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I HOPE THAT THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO COMMITS TO
MAINTAINING THIS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
THANK YOU. I'M DARREN ALLEN, EXECUTIVE
DIRECTOR OF LIVABLE CITY. WE PRODUCED SUNDAY STREETS.
I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH'S
PROPOSAL TO ELIMINATE $215,000 IN FUNDING FOR SUN STREETS.
>> THAT'S OUR ENTIRE GRANT FOR SUN STREETS.
AND I WE'RE NOT UNSYMPATHETIC TO THE NEED TO CUT FUNDING.
>> AND I DID LET DE KNOW AHEAD OF TIME THAT LITTLE LESS MONEY
WE CAN SURVIVE. I DO QUESTION THE WISDOM OF
SAVING 215,000 AT THE COST OF WIPING OUT SUN STREETS
COMPLETELY. >> OKAY.
AND LET ME BE CLEAR THAT WE DON'T DEPEND COMPLETELY ON A
CITY I PERSONALLY MATCH EVERY DOLLAR I RAISE MATCHING DOLLARS
FOR EVERY CITY DOLLAR FROM SPONSORS, FROM DONORS AND MY
FRIENDS. SO WE'RE NOT LIKE ONLY
DEPENDENT ON THE CITY. >> BUT IT'S THE 18 YEAR
TRADITION AND I WOULD THINK THAT THE CITY COULD FIND A WAY
TO CUT OUR BUDGET BUT GIVE US SOMETHING.
SO I GOT A RUNNING CHANCE. RIGHT NOW I'VE GOT SPONSORS
SAYING WELL DARREN, WHAT DO WE DO?
YOU KNOW WHAT IF WHAT DO WE DO IF YOU CAN'T DO ALL THE EVENTS
,HOW DO WE DO THE REFUNDS? IT'S THIS IS WASTING MY TIME.
I NEED TO BE BUILDING THIS PROGRAM.
I ALSO WANT TO POINT OUT THAT THIS PROGRAM IS A PLATFORM THIS
EVENT IS A PLATFORM FOR OTHER EVENTS TO SALVADORAN SOUL
AND CONTROL THE INDIGENOUS BADR AND BEATS THE BUTCHER TOWN JAZZ
FESTIVAL ALL TAKE PLACE IN SUNDAY STREETS.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> MADAME'S IN WAS HERE.
>> ALLOW ME TO INTRODUCE MYSELF .
I AM THE KATRINA I WAS CREATED BY GUADALUPE POSADA DURING THE
VICTORIAN ERA BUT I WAS REALLY MADE A STAR BY DIEGO RIVERA WHO
CEMENTED MY ICONIC STATUS IN MEXICAN CULTURE WITH HIS
MURAL SUNDAY STROLL IN THE ALAMEDA YOU CAN CALL ME AN
ANGEL OF DEATH OF SORTS WITH A WHIMSICAL FLAIR SO AS TO REMOVE
THE FEAR. >> I AM A BLEND OF THE AZTEC
COSMIC VISION OF THE AFTERLIFE CALLED MACTAN THAT EMBRACES THE
BEAUTY AND ELEGANT MORBIDITY OF MEXICAN CULTURE BLENDED WITH
OUR EUROPEAN TRADITIONS. >> IN SHORT, I AM THE ONE THAT
COMES FOR YOU WHEN IT'S YOUR TIME TO TAKE YOUR JOURNEY.
I CAME TO THE TERRESTRIAL REALM BECAUSE I GOT A TELEGRAM IN THE
COSMOS THAT THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER IS IN CRISIS.
>> THIS ICONIC COMMUNITY INSTITUTION FOR 50 YEARS HAS
BEEN THE HEART IN THE PILLAR OF THE BURIAL LATINO COMMUNITY
AND BEYOND BRIDGING NORTH AND SOUTH IT HAS ALWAYS BEEN A
PORTAL FOR ME AND MY ENTOURAGE TO JOIN THE SKELETON FIESTA
WHERE EVERYONE'S ANCESTORS ARE INVITED.
>> BUT ENOUGH ABOUT ME. >> I WOULD LIKE TO INTRODUCE
YOU TO A FRIEND OF MINE. MY NAME IS NANCY CHIDOKA.
I AM A MISSION RESIDENT AND SMALL BUSINESS OWNER.
>> I HAVE OWNED A LEGACY CULTURAL STORE FOR 30 YEARS
AND I AM HERE TODAY TO THANK YOU IN ADVANCE FOR YOUR SUPPORT
FOR SAVING THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER.
WE ARE ONE HUNDRED AND 50% COMMITTED AND DETERMINED OUR
COMMUNITY IN SPITE OF THE POLITICAL LANDSCAPE IS NOT SHY
OF INCREDIBLE OBSTACLES. >> WE ARE COMMITTED TO
COMBINING RESOURCES ARTS TALENT ,OUR INTELLIGENCE TO MAKE THIS
HAPPEN. >> I WANT TO THANK YOU
IN ADVANCE AND INVITE YOU TO JOIN THE FUN GRACIOUS NICE TO
SEE YOU, NANCY. I THOUGHT THAT WAS YOU.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD EVENING, BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ASHLYNN TAM AND I'M THE YOUTH INTIMATE PARTNER
VIOLENCE PREVENTION COORDINATOR AT ASIAN WOMEN'S SHELTER.
I WANT TO THANK BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WALTON CHAN MELGAR
SALTER MENTOR MAN MAHMOOD WANG FIELDER AND DORSEY FOR
SPONSORING THE RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE FEBRUARY AS TEEN
DATING VIOLENCE AWARENESS AND PREVENTION MONTH TO
IN COLLABORATION WITH BLACK WOMEN AND REVOLT AGAINST
VIOLENCE AND SAN FRANCISCO YOUTH COMMISSION.
>> WHEN WE HEAR DOMESTIC VIOLENCE WE OFTEN THINK OF ONLY
ADULTS EXPERIENCING UNHEALTHY AND ABUSIVE RELATIONSHIPS
AND YOUTH. >> BUT YOUTH ALSO EXPERIENCE
UNHEALTHY TOXIC AND ABUSIVE RELATIONSHIPS.
>> IT'S IMPORTANT AS ADULTS TO TO SUPPORT THE CONTINUATION OF
RAISING AWARENESS AND EDUCATION FOR OUR YOUNG PEOPLE TO HAVE
HEALTHY RELATIONSHIPS. I ALSO WANT TO UPLIFT
AND RECOGNIZE THIS YEAR'S THE TEN YEAR ANNIVERSARY OF THE
PASSING OF THE CALIFORNIA HEALTHY YOUTH ACT WHICH
MANDATES ALL PUBLIC, MIDDLE AND HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS LEARN
ABOUT HEALTHY RELATIONSHIPS, CONSENT AND HOW TO RECOGNIZE
RECOGNIZE DATING VIOLENCE AND DOMESTIC VIOLENCE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT WEEK. >> HELLO MY NAME IS TAYLOR.
I'M THE TREE PREVENTION QUARTERBACK REVOLT AGAINST
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE. I WANTED TO START OFF BY
ECHOING ANGELA AND THANKING ALL OF YOU WHO JOINED THE YOUTH
COMMISSIONERS IN RECOGNIZING THAT DATING VIOLENCE AFFECTS
THEIR CLASSMATES ABILITY TO BE SAFE TO SHOW UP AS STUDENTS,
FRIENDS AND THEMSELVES. I ALSO WANT TO ECHO EARLIER
CALLS FOR A HEARING ON COMMUNITY VIOLENCE ESPECIALLY
ITS IMPACT ON THOSE WHO ARE 12 TO 14 DATING VIOLENCE
AND SEXUAL VIOLENCE PREVENTION ARE A PART OF THIS EFFORT.
NOT BEING ABLE TO END A RELATIONSHIP KNOW HOW TO ASK
FOR CONSENT LOVE WITHOUT OWNERSHIP ACCEPT REJECTION
AND RECOGNIZE DATING VIOLENCE ARE SAFETY ISSUES REGARDING
COMMUNITY VIOLENCE TEEN DATING VIOLENCE IS CORRELATED WITH
FIGHTS SOMETIMES GUN VIOLENCE AND INCIDENTS ON AND OFF AS A
FEW CITY CAMPUSES IT WILL PERPETUATE AS LONG AS OUR YOUTH
LACK THE RESOURCES TO REFLECT ON THEIR LIVED EXPERIENCES
AND THE HOPE FOR THEIR FUTURES. THIS FEAR AND LOSS IS FELT
HEAVILY IN OUR HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS ESPECIALLY AT JOYOUS
OCCASIONS OR EVEN AT CHOICE OCCASIONS LIKE BRIGHTON HIGH
SCHOOL'S BSU BLACK LEADERSHIP SUMMIT THIS PAST FRIDAY.
NO YOUTH SHOULD FEAR FOR THEIR SAFETY IN A RELATIONSHIP OR
FEEL THE NEED TO AVENGE A FRIEND OR A LOVED ONE.
WE LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING ALONGSIDE YOU ALL SUPERVISED
THE YOUTH COMMISSION, OUR CHIP CLINICS, FELLOW NONPROFITS, THE
COOPERATIVE RESTRAINING ORDER CLINIC AND MOVE TO MAKE SURE WE
RESPOND TO YOUTH VIOLENCE WHEN IT OCCURS WITH SERVICES THAT
INCLUDE MINORS AND EMPOWER OUR YOUTH AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS
WITH THE TOOLS AND SAFE SPACES TO PREVENT IT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING AND THANK YOU
FOR HAVING US. I AM DR. PAMELA TAIT OF BLACK
WOMEN REVOLT AGAINST DOMESTIC VIOLENCE.
I WANTED TO JUST THANK EVERYONE FOR THE RESOLUTION FOR THE
THIRD YEAR AND MOVING FORWARD WITH THAT.
TAYLOR AND ANGELINA SPOKE VERY WELL ON THAT AND SO I JUST
WANTED TO SAY THANK YOU. I ALSO WANTED TO SPEAK UP ON
THE EMCEE ELLE THEY ARE THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO I'M
LOOKING AT MYRNA AND MY DAUGHTER PARTICIPATED WITH
THEM. I ACTUALLY BOTH SONS SO ALL
THREE OF MY CHILDREN PARTICIPATED WITH THEM
AND REALLY GOT EXPOSURE TO ART SO MUCH SO THAT MY MY DAUGHTER
WENT ON TO SOTA AND ACTUALLY WAS PART OF THE WORLD MUSIC
PROGRAM. I JUST HEARD SOMEONE MENTION
SHE DOES LATINO DRUMMING WORLD MUSIC SHE DOES AFRICAN DRUMMING
,SHE DOES TAIKO AND SO ALL OF THAT STARTED AT MCO.
IT IS AN IMPORTANT PART OF SAN FRANCISCO EXPOSURE TO THE ARTS
AND I PRAY AND HOPE THAT YOU ALL WILL FIND MONEY TO SUPPORT
AND KEEP IT OPEN. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER HELLO.
WITH RESPECT TO THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER THE BUILDING
KNOWN AS THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER ON MISSION STREET, THANK
YOU ALL FOR ALL OF YOUR SUPPORT.
THOSE OF YOU WHO HAVE ALREADY EXPRESSED SUPPORT SUPERVISORS
FIELD OR MELGAR WALTON AND JAN, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR EVERYBODY
ELSE CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO KEEPING THE BALL
ROLLING. IF YOU'VE ALREADY BEEN THERE
YOU NEED NO SWAYING AND IF YOU HAVEN'T WELL I ADVISE YOU TO DO
YOURSELVES A SERVICE AND MAKE IT AN OPPORTUNITY THAT YOU CAN
STILL ENJOY GOING FORWARD. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CHOSEN AND I SERVE AS A COMMISSION STAFF FOR THE
SAN FRANCISCO YOUTH COMMISSION .
TODAY I WANT TO SPEAK ON ITEM 41 AND EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO
THE BOARD FOR WORKING WITH US THE YOUTH COMMISSION, SAN
FRANCISCO ASIAN WOMEN'S SHELTER AND BLACK WOMEN REVOLT AGAINST
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AND BRINGING AWARENESS TO TEEN DATING
VIOLENCE. WE AIM TO BUILD AN ENVIRONMENT
AND CULTURE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE TO HAVE HEALTHY RELATIONSHIPS
AND TO RECOGNIZE THE SIGNS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AND ABUSE
WHETHER IT'S PHYSICAL OR DIGITAL.
YOUNG PEOPLE DESERVE TO HAVE SAFE, HEALTHY AND COMMUNICATIVE
RELATIONSHIPS AND THAT'S WHY WE APPRECIATE THE WORK
AND EDUCATION THAT THE BLACK WOMAN REVOLT AND US OF US
PROVIDE TO YOUNG PEOPLE IN SCHOOLS AND THE COMMUNITY
EDUCATION AND PREVENTION START AT A YOUNG AGE AND WE NEED ALL
HANDS ON DECK TO SUPPORT THE PEOPLE ON THE GROUND DOING THE
WORK AND RAISING AWARENESS AMONG OUR STUDENTS.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION
AND THANK YOU TO ALL OF THE CO-SPONSORS.
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND SUPERVISORS MELGAR CHAN
SADR, MAHMOOD WONG FIELDER, DORSEY AND CHERYL.
AND I URGE YOU TO SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, DIRECTOR CHANG FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD EVENING, SUPERVISOR ERS MY NAME IS CAROLYN MEYER.
I HAVE BEEN TAKING CLASSES AT MISSION CULTURAL CENTER SINCE
THE EIGHTY'S AND VOLUNTEERING THERE FOR ABOUT THE LAST 20
YEARS AND I COME TO YOU WITH A PROPOSAL TONIGHT I KNOW IT'S
ALL ABOUT THE MONEY. WE NEED MONEY TO FUND MISSION
CULTURAL WE NEED MONEY TO FUND OTHER CULTURAL CENTERS AND DO
THE RETROFITTING. SO HERE'S MY PROPOSAL WE KNOW
THAT MAYOR LURIE IS AN INCREDIBLE NEGOTIATOR AND WE
KNOW ONE OF THE WORLD'S BIGGEST ENTERTAINERS.
>> MEXICAN AMERICAN ENTERTAINERS COMES FROM THE
MISSION DISTRICT. DO I HAVE TO MENTION HIS NAME?
CARLOS SANTANA. >> SO I THINK IT WOULD BE GREAT
IF THE MAYOR AND CARLOS SANTANA COULD HAVE A LITTLE DISCUSSION
MAYBE ABOUT A CONCERT THAT COULD BENEFIT EXCUSE ME BENEFIT
MISSION CULTURAL AND SOME OF THE OTHER CULTURAL CENTERS
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THAT'S MY PROPOSAL. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, CAROL AND MEYER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 36
THROUGH 41 ITEMS 36 THROUGH 41 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR
ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE. SO MANY PEOPLE HAVE ACCUSED
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU FOR PRESENT CAN I REQUEST TO ACT AS
A CO-SPONSOR FOR ITEM NUMBER 41?
>> THANK YOU. OKAY.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL I WOULD LOVE TO BE ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR
TODAY OF 40 RUTH A SOLID DAY PLEASE.
>> OKAY. NOTED SUPERVISOR DORSEY I HAVE
A CO SPONSOR ITEM 36 SUPERVISOR WALTON PLEASE SEVER ITEM 41.
>> >> SUPERVISOR KILGOUR PLEASE SEVER ITEM 39 AND I'D ALSO LIKE
TO BECAUSE CO SPONSOR OF ITEM 40 THANK YOU.
>> OKAY. AND I WOULD LIKE TO SEVER ITEM
40 AND SO ON THE REMAINING BALANCE OF THE ITEMS MADAM
CLERK COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 36 THROUGH 38.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
AND I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDOLIN MIN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON RIGHT
WALTON EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 39 ITEM
39 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO DECLARE A COMMITMENT BY THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO TO PROTECT AND PRESERVE THE LONG TERM
FUTURE FOR A CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS AND CULTURE IN THE MISSION
AT 2868 MISSION STREET. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH MADAM
CLERK. FIRST I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP ON THIS AND YOUR
STAFF'S WORK TO ADDRESS THE SITUATION.
THANK YOU TO ALL MY COMMUNITY PEOPLE AND MY DANCE SISTERS FOR
BEING HERE TO TALK ABOUT THIS REALLY IMPORTANT ISSUE.
>> YOU KNOW, FOLKS THINK THAT THE PROBLEM AT MISSION CULTURAL
CENTER IS THAT THERE'S A LACK OF FUNDING AND WHILE THAT IS
TRUE RIGHT NOW THE ORGANIZATION THAT RUNS THE MISSION CULTURAL
CENTER IS OUT OF COMPLIANCE AND IN DEBT.
THIS HAS BEEN COMING FOR YEARS AND I JUST WANT TO CENTER THE,
YOU KNOW, STORY AS TO WHAT THE CITY DID IN OUR FAILURE IN YOU
KNOW, CAUSING THE SITUATION THAT WE HAVE TODAY WHICH MAY
RESULT IN A LOSS OF A FUNDAMENTAL PART OF THE SOUL OF
THE COMMUNITY. SO MANY YEARS AGO WHEN WE KNEW
THAT THE BUILDING NEEDED RETROFITTING A BUILDING THAT IS
OWNED BY THE CITY AND TAKEN CARE OF BY THE ORGANIZATION FOR
THE PURPOSE OF SERVING THE COMMUNITY THROUGH THE ARTS JUST
LIKE OTHER BUILDINGS IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT IS IN OUR
CHARTER FROM A SECTION DATING BACK TO 1972 THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN ARTS AND CULTURE CENTER, THE BABY
OPERA HOUSE AND OTHERS. >> SO YOU KNOW, IT SPELLS OUT
THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE CULTURAL CENTERS.
ALL OF THESE ARE IN UNDERSERVED COMMUNITIES AND COMMUNITIES FOR
WHICH THE CONNECTION TO ARTS AND CULTURE IS DEEPLY IMPORTANT
TO OUR IDENTITY AND SOUL. >> WHEN WE FOUND OUT THAT THE
BUILDING NEEDED SEISMIC RETROFIT HITTING THE ARTS
COMMISSION, THE ORGANIZATION THAT THE DEPARTMENT THAT IS
IN CHARGE OF PROVIDING THE FUNDING FOR THESE ORGANIZATIONS
BASICALLY SAID OH YEAH, WE'RE GOING TO DO THIS PROVIDED NO
TIMELINE, NO PLAN, NO TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE, DIDN'T EVEN SAY A
DATE WHEN THE WORK WAS GOING TO START AND BASICALLY LEFT THE
ORGANIZATION TO FEND ON ITS OWN.
SO AS FORMER SUPERVISOR RONAN AND I FOR YEARS CALLED FOR A
PLAN IN SUPPORT FROM THE CITY OF THIS VERY IMPORTANT CULTURE
AND INSTITUTION AND JUST SOME DIGNITY AND RESPECT FOR THE
COMMUNITY THAT WAS FACING THIS INEVITABLE THING THAT IT NEEDED
TO BE RETROFITTED. SO FORMER SUPERVISOR RONAN PUT
AN AD BACK INTO AT THE BUDGET TO HELP THE ORGANIZATION BUT
AGAIN IT WAS REELECTED FROM THE DEPARTMENT AS TO THE HELP THAT
WAS PROVIDED. SO HERE WE ARE ALL THESE YEARS
LATER. TWO YEARS AGO I ATTENDED A
MEETING AT THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER WHERE ARTS COMMISSION
STAFF IN FRONT OF 200 PEOPLE IN THE COMMUNITY WITH SUCH
TOTAL DISRESPECT COULD NOT SAY THAT THE COMMUNITY COULD COME
BACK INTO THE CENTER AFTER IT WAS RETROFITTED AND HID BEHIND
YOU KNOW, ALL THE LACK OF CLARITY IN THE LANGUAGE THAT
DIDN'T NEED TO HAPPEN, YOU KNOW.
SO WHEN I SAID LAST WEEK THAT, YOU KNOW, HAD THIS BEEN THE
BALLET OR THE OPERA, THIS WOULDN'T HAVE HAPPENED, I STAND
BY THAT 100%. I THINK THAT WE NEED TO TO
TREAT THE CITIZENS OF SAN FRANCISCO WITH RESPECT WITH
DIGNITY, WITH TRANSPARENCY, WITH CLARITY AND WE CAN DO THAT
NOW. AND I KNOW THAT WITH UNDER
SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S LEADERSHIP THAT WILL HAPPEN AND THAT YOU
KNOW, I ASK FOR THE NEW LEADERSHIP AT THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE TO LEAD THE WAY TO MAKE THE COMMITMENTS TO THE
COMMUNITY TO MAKE SURE THAT THIS BUILDING SERVES THE
FUNCTIONS THAT THE VOTERS OF SAN FRANCISCO COMMITTED TO.
WHEN WE PUT THAT IN THE CHARTER AND THAT IT CONTINUES TO
PROVIDE THE SPACE FOR LOVE, COMMUNITY ARTS AND CULTURE THAT
ARE NECESSARY FOR THE MISSION COMMUNITY REALLY PEOPLE COME
FROM ALL OVER THE BAY AREA IN THE COUNTRY TO THE MISSION
CULTURAL CENTER AND WHILE THE FUNDING THAT THE CITY PROVIDES
WAS ESSENTIAL FOR THE ORGANIZATION, IT WASN'T THE
ONLY FUNDING THAT THE ORGANIZATION HAD BECAUSE THE
BUILDING ACTUALLY GENERATING A SIGNIFICANT AMOUNT OF INCOME
IN RENTS IN ART SHOWINGS IN ECONOMIC ACTIVITY IT
PROVIDED LIVELIHOOD FOR ARTISTS FOR GENERATIONS AND THAT NEEDS
TO CONTINUE TO HAPPEN. SO EVEN THOUGH YOU KNOW THERE
IS SOME FUNDING THAT IS NECESSARY FROM THE CITY, WHAT
IS ESSENTIAL IS THE LAND ACCESS TO THE BUILDING THAT PLACE
IN THE COMMUNITY AT THE CORNER OF 25TH AND MISSION BECAUSE IT
IS SUCH AN IMPORTANT PART OF OUR CULTURE OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
AND YOU KNOW, I HOPE THAT WE ALL DO THE RIGHT THING.
THANK YOU AGAIN AS SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP.
AND I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, IT IS A STRONG MESSAGE TO SEND TO
THE COMMUNITY THAT WE CAN DO IT .
>> THANK YOU. FIELDER I JUST WANTED TO TURN
THANKS TO ROGER MELGAR FOR ALL THOSE REMARKS AS AN ACTIVE
PARTICIPANT IN MCLA AND YOUR FAMILY AND SO MANY DOZENS OF
PEOPLE HERE IT IS IT IS A PRICELESS PRICELESS PLACE OF
REALLY FUTURE MAKING FOR THE MISSION AS MANY PEOPLE HAVE
SAID, SAN FRANCISCO AND BEYOND BAY AREA AND THERE ARE
SUGGESTIONS HERE ABOUT HOW TO GET THERE PEOPLE WITH OTHER
KINDS OF CAPITAL INVOLVED AND WE DO HAVE ENOUGH OF THESE
ON FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE IN THE ROOM AND SO I WOULD LOVE
TO TALK TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE ABOUT HOW WE CAN PUT OUR
COLLECTIVE MINDS AND POWER TOGETHER AT THIS BOARD AND ALSO
TAKE UP THE SUGGESTION IN PUBLIC COMMENT AROUND
ENSURING THAT ANY RESTRUCTURING AROUND THE ARTS COMMISSION ALSO
INCLUDES DEEP COMMITMENTS TO CULTURAL INSTITUTIONS AND THAT
ALSO MEANS THE RESPECT THAT THEY'RE DESERVED AND THEREFORE
ALSO THE STAFF AND LEADERSHIP THAT ALSO SEE THAT.
AND SO I LOOK FORWARD TO FUTURE CONVERSATIONS WITH THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE AND AND MY COLLEAGUES ABOUT THAT AND I WANT TO
APPRECIATE EVERYONE WHO CAME OUT TODAY IN SUPPORT OF THIS.
ALL RIGHT. AND WITH THAT WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
40. >> ITEM 40 RESOLUTION TO
RECOGNIZE FEBRUARY 12TH 2026 AS RUTH ASAWA DAY IN HONOR OF HER
WORK AS AN ARTIST AND ADVOCATE FOR ARTS EDUCATION IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO COLLEAGUES THIS RESOLUTION
WOULD RECOGNIZE FEBRUARY 12TH, 2026 AS RUTH ASAWA DAY IN THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> RUTH ASSAD WAS RUTH ASAWA WAS ONE OF THE MOST ADMIRED
ARTISTS EDUCATORS AND CIVIC LEADERS OF THE 20TH CENTURY.
BORN IN 1926, IN NORWALK, CALIFORNIA, SHE WENT ON TO
BUILD A SIX DECADE CAREER THAT SPANNED DRAWING, PAINTING,
PRINTMAKING, BRONZE CASTING, PUBLIC ART AND OF COURSE THE
ICONIC LOOP TROIS SCULPTURES THAT MADE HER WORLD RENOWNED
WHILE SHE WAS BASED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
HER INFLUENCE EXTENDED FAR BEYOND OUR CITY.
HER WORK IS CELEBRATED AROUND THE WORLD AND TODAY IT IS
FEATURED IN THE LARGEST EXHIBITION EVER DEDICATED TO A
WOMAN ARTIST AT THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART IN NEW YORK.
>> BUT SAN FRANCISCO WAS HER HOME AND HER LEGACY IS DEEPLY
WOVEN INTO THE FABRIC OF OUR CITY FROM FOUNTAINS AND MURALS
TO SCULPTURES THAT REMAIN PUBLICLY ACCESSIBLE TO THIS DAY
TO OUR VERY OWN RUTH ASAWA SCHOOL OF THE ARTS.
RUTH RUTH'S ALWAYS LIFE STORY IS ALSO A STORY OF RESILIENCE.
SHE WAS THE FOURTH OF SEVEN CHILDREN BORN TO JAPANESE
IMMIGRANT FARMERS AND ARE JUST 16 YEARS OLD.
SHE WAS FORCIBLY REMOVED FROM HER HOME AND INCARCERATED BY
THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT DURING WORLD WAR TWO.
EVEN UNDER THOSE HARSH, HARSH CONDITIONS SHE FOUND WAYS TO
CREATE BY TAKING ART LESSONS FROM FELLOW DETAINEES AFTER THE
WAR DESPITE FACING DISCRIMINATION THAT BLOCKED HER
FROM BECOMING A STUDENT TEACHER, SHE CONTINUED HER
EDUCATION AT BLACK MOUNTAIN COLLEGE WHERE SHE STUDIED
ALONGSIDE LEADING ARTISTS AND DEVELOPED THE VALUES THAT
WOULD SHAPE HER LIFELONG ADVOCACY FOR ACCESSIBLE ARTS
EDUCATION THAT COMMITMENT DEFINED SO MUCH OF HER WORK
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. IN 1968 SHE FOUNDED THE
ALVARADO SCHOOL ARTS WORKSHOP BRINGING PROFESSIONAL ARTISTS
AND PARENTS INTO PUBLIC SCHOOLS TO TEACH CHILDREN THROUGH HANDS
ON ART MAKING. AT ITS HEIGHT, THE PROGRAM
REACHED MORE THAN 50 SCHOOLS AND BECAME A NATIONAL MODEL FOR
ARTS, EDUCATION AND PUBLIC SERVICE PROGRAMS ACROSS THE
COUNTRY. ASAWA ALSO SERVED ON SAN
FRANCISCO'S ARTS COMMISSION NATIONAL THE CALIFORNIA ARTS
COUNCIL, THE NATIONAL ENDOWMENT FOR THE ARTS AND AS A TRUSTEE
OF THE FINE ARTS MUSEUMS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
AND SHE PLAYED A KEY ROLE IN FOUNDING SAN FRANCISCO'S
PUBLIC ARTS HIGH SCHOOL WHICH PROUDLY BEARS HER NAME TODAY
THE RUTH ASAWA SAN FRANCISCO SCHOOL OF THE ARTS.
IN 2022 SHE WAS POSTHUMOUSLY AWARDED THE NATIONAL MEDAL OF
ARTS HONORING NOT ONLY HER GROUNDBREAKING MODERNIST WORK
BUT ALSO HER BELIEF THAT CREATIVITY SHOULD BE ACCESSIBLE
TO ALL. >> SAN FRANCISCO FIRST DECLARED
FEBRUARY 12TH AS RUTH ASAWA DAY IN 1982 AND IT SEEMS ESPECIALLY
APPROPRIATE TO RENEW THAT RECOGNITION IN THIS YEAR.
THAT IS THE 100TH ANNIVERSARY OF HER BIRTH.
COLLEAGUES ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS RESOLUTION TODAY SO
THAT WE CAN OFFICIALLY RECOGNIZE FEBRUARY 12TH, 2026
AS RUTH ASAWA DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP AND AND
WITH THAT WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 41.
>> ITEM 41 IS A RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE THE MONTH OF FEBRUARY
2026 AS TEEN DATING VIOLENCE AWARENESS AND PREVENTION MONTH
IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SUAREZ WELL, THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENEM AND I JUST
WANTED TO SAY THANK YOU SO MUCH TO ALL OF MY COLLEAGUES FOR
THEIR SPONSORSHIP AND ALSO WANT TO THANK EVERYONE WHO CAME OUT
TO SPEAK THIS EVENING. I KNOW IT'S PRETTY LATE BUT
THIS IS IMPORTANT AND I JUST APPRECIATE EVERYONE'S SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
AND WE WILL TAKE THIS ONE. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT. MR. PRESIDENT, CAN YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL ON
BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR THE LATE MS. JOHNNY MAY BAKER
AND I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA, MADAM
CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY AND WE ARE ADJOURNED